<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>netbeans soapUI plugin</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
		<section name="soapUI NetBeans Plugin">
		<p>The soapUI NetBeans Plugin provides all soapui functionality directly from within 
		<a target="_new" href="http://www.netbeans.org/">NetBeans 5.5/6.0</a> allowing one integrated development and 
		testing environment for Web Services in java. Since soapUI 2.0, the plug-in hosts soapUI projects just as standard
		NetBeans projects, ie the previously available "soapUI Navigator" tab has been removed and soapUI projects are 
		managed like any other NetBeans projects. Here are some screenshots:</p>
	
		<columns><column>
		<thumbnail src="images/netbeans1.gif" size="250" caption="(Request/Response Editors)" alt="Request/Response Editors in soapUI Netbeans Plugin"/>
		</column><column>
		<thumbnail src="images/netbeans2.gif" size="250" caption="(Tools / soapUI Menu with LoadTest Runner in background)"  alt="Tools / soapUI Menu with LoadTest Runner in background in soapUI Netbeans Plugin"/>
		</column><column>
		<thumbnail src="images/netbeans3.gif" size="250" caption="(Axis2 Wizard with WS-I Basic Profile Report in background)" lat="Axis2 Wizard with WS-I Basic Profile Report in background in soapUI Netbeans Plugin"/>
		</column></columns>
		
		<subsection name="Getting Started with WS Testing in Netbeans">
		<p>Download the NBM from <a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=136013&amp;package_id=210125">SourceForge soapUI Downloads</a> or 
		via the NetBeans Plugin manager. If you downloaded it from SourceForge, install 
		as described in the <a href="installation.html">soapUI Installation</a> document. See the 
		<a href="#Demonstration_Movies">soapUI demonstration movies</a> below for some hands-on tutorials,
		otherwise the existing <a href="../gettingstarted/index.html">Getting Started with soapUI</a> applies also to the NetBeans Plugin, as does
		the <a href="../userguide/index.html">User Guide</a>. The only real difference is that the standalone soapUI Desktop has
		been replaced by the NetBeans tabbed interface for editors.</p>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="Creating a soapUI Project">
		<p>As mentioned above, soapUI projects are managed as standard NetBeans projects. To create a new soapUI project, select the
		New Project -> SOA -> Web Service Testing Project option:</p>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/newproject1.gif" alt="Creating a New Web Service Testing Project in the NetBeans plugin"/></p>
		<p>After selecting "Next", one will be prompted to create the project, together with options for:
		<ul>
		<li>Specifying the initial WSDL to import</li>
		<li>Generating a TestSuites and/or MockService for the specified WSDL</li>
		<li>Specifing an existing soapUI Project which will be imported instead</li>
		</ul>
		</p>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/newproject2.gif"  alt="Specifying URL, Web Service Testing Project Wizard in the NetBeans plugin"/></p>
		<p>Depending on which options that have been selected, a number of dialogs will be shown to query for related information. Once
		the project has been created, it will be visible in the standard NetBeans "Projects" view in the same way as it is displayed in 
		soapUI Navigator when running the standalone version of soapUI:</p>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/newproject3.gif" alt="Show Project view in the NetBeans plugin"/></p>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="Log and Property Views">
		<p>The standard soapUI Log tabs are made visible via the Window\soapUI Log menu option which will open the tabs in a window at
		the bottom of the NetBeans desktop:</p>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/soapuilog.gif" alt="Log Window in the NetBeans plugin"/></p>
		<p>The item specific properties displayed at the bottom-left in the standalone version of soapUI can be viewed or edited by 
		opening the NetBeans Properties Window from the Window menu.</p>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/soapuiproperties.gif"  alt="Item Specific properties in the NetBeans plugin"/></p>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="Demonstration Movies">
		<p>As of NetBeans 6.0 M9 / OpenESB 2.0, the soapUI NetBeans plugin is bundled with the OpenESB add ons, 
		downloadable from <a target="_new" href="https://open-esb.dev.java.net/Downloads_OpenESB_Addons_NB6.html">https://open-esb.dev.java.net/Downloads_OpenESB_Addons_NB6.html</a>.
		The following demonstration movies are available that show how to get started with common soapUI tasks in NetBeans:</p>
		<ul>
		<li><a href="demos/soapui-netbeans-demo-1/soapui-netbeans-demo-1.html">soapUI NetBeans Demo Movie 1</a> shows how to create a simple WSDL, implement and deploy that WSDL with a BPEL process, and
		finally test the deployed process with the soapUI module.</li>
		<li><a href="demos/soapui-netbeans-demo-2/soapui-netbeans-demo-2.html">soapUI NetBeans Demo Movie 2</a> shows how to create a simple WSDL, create a Mock Implementation of that WSDL with the soapUI 
		module, create a java application client that calls the Mock Implementation, and then finally how to implement the WSDL 
		with a BPEL process.</li>
		<li><a href="demos/soapui-netbeans-demo-3/soapui-netbeans-demo-3.html">soapUI NetBeans Demo Movie 3</a> shows how to create a simple JAX-WS Web Service and deploy/test it with the 
		soapUI module.</li>
		</ul>		
		</subsection>

		
		<p><hr size="1"/>Next: <a href="installation.html">Installing soapUI NetBeans Plugin</a></p>
		</section>
    </body>
</document>
