<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>netbeans soapUI plugin - netbeans project integration</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
		<section name="NetBeans Project Integration">
		<imgtable src="images/create_project_menu.gif" alt="WSDL files direct creation"><div>
		Version 1.7.1 of the NetBeans soapUI Plugin introduces a soapUI sub-menu in the popup menu of NetBeans 
		Projects and WSDL files allowing direct creation of and access to an associated soapUI project for the 
		containing NetBeans project. The menu allows direct access to all objects in this associated soapUI project 
		and selected soapUI functionality.</div>
		<p>When displaying the menu for the first time, a "Create Project" option will be available that creates 
		a soapui-project.xml file in the root of the containing NetBeans project. Upon creation, the project will 
		also be added to the soapUI Navigator window and named after the corresponding NetBeans project.</p></imgtable>
				
		<subsection name="Project Menu">
		<imgtable src="images/project_menu.gif" alt="project menu soap test"><div>
		Once created, the soapUI Project submenu contains the following actions:</div>
		
		<ul>
		<li><b>Show Project</b> : Opens the soapUI Navigator and selects the associated project</li>
		<li><b>Interfaces</b> : A submenu containing all Interfaces/Operations/Requests in the associated
		soapUI Project and associated actions. Selecting one of these items opens the corresponding editor window 
		in the NetBeans Desktop</li>
		<li><b>TestSuites</b> : A submenu containing all TestSuites/TestCases/TestSteps/LoadTests in the associated
		soapUI Project and associated actions. Selecting one of these items opens the corresponding editor window 
		in the NetBeans Desktop</li>
		<li><b>MockServices</b> : A submenu containing all MockServices/MockOperations/MockResponses in the associated
		soapUI Project and associated actions. Selecting one of these items opens the corresponding editor window 
		in the NetBeans Desktop</li>
		<li><b>Preferences</b> : Opens the soapUI Preferences Dialog</li>
		<li><b>Online Help</b> : Opens the online NetBeans help page in an external browser</li>
		<li><b>soapui.org</b> : Opens the online soapui.org website in an external browser</li>
		</ul>
		</imgtable>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="WSDL Menu">
		<imgtable src="images/wsdl_menu.gif" alt="SOA test WSDL Menu"><div>
		Once created, the soapUI WSDL File submenu contains the same actions as the project menu described above and 
		adds the following:</div>
		<ul>
		<li><b>Import WSDL</b> or <b>Update Project</b>: imports the selected WSDL into the associated soapUI Project.
		If the project already contains imported WSDLs/Interfaces, the Update Project option will be displayed instead
		and will import/update from the selected WSDL instead. If there are Binding-Name mismatches, soapUI will 
		prompt for updated associations or new imports.</li>
		<li><b>Check WS-I Compliance</b> : Runs the WS-I Basic Profile Analysis tools as described in the
		<a href="../userguide/interfaces/wsi.html">User Guide</a>.</li>
		<li><b>Generate Code..</b> : Shows the Generate menu for generating java clients/stubs for a selection
		of frameworks as described in the <a href="../userguide/tools/topdown.html">User Guide</a></li>
		</ul>
		</imgtable>

		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="Deleting the associated soapUI Project">
		<p>To delete the associated soapUI project correctly you need to:</p>
		<ol>
		<li>Remove the project from the soapUI Navigator with the right-button "Remove" action</li>
		<li>Delete the soapui-project.xml file from the NetBeans project root</li>
		</ol>		
		
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="Associating an existing soapUI Project">
		<p>If you already have a soapUI project that you want to associate with your existing NetBeans project
		so it shows up and works correctly in the popup menus, do as follows:</p>
		<ol>
		<li>Remove the project from the soapUI Navigator with the right-button "Remove" action</li>
		<li>Copy the project file to the root of your NetBeans project and rename it to "soapui-project.xml"</li>
		<li>Import the moved/renamed project file back into your soapUI Navigator via the workspace nodes right-button
		"Import Project" action</li>
		</ol>
		<p>After this the project integration should find your project file correctly and also its corresponding project
		in the soapUI Navigator</p>
		</subsection>
		

		 <p><hr size="1"/>Next: <a href="../plugin/index.html">The Maven Plugins</a></p>
		</section>
    </body>
</document>
