<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>SOAP Load Test Graphs</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
		<section name="Diagrams">
		<p>soapUI provides 2 diagrams for behavioral analysis of LoadTest Statistics over time (neither 
		provides any exact values/legends). These are:</p>
		<ul>
			<li>A <b>Statistics</b> diagram showing all statistics for a selected TestStep</li>
			<li>A <b>Statistic History</b> diagram showing a selected Statistic for all TestSteps</li>
		</ul>
		<p>Both diagrams share a "Resolution" setting which controls how often the diagram should be updated. 
		This can be set either to "Data" or a number of milliseconds:</p>
		<ul>
		<li><b>Data</b> - means that the diagram will be updated whenever the main LoadTest Statistics are
		updated, which in turn is controlled by the "Sample Interval" setting in the LoadTest Options dialog. 
		This is the default setting and sufficient if you have a high throughput of TestCase runs (which will 
		constantly update the Statistics. If you have a LoadTest that has long-running TestCases, this option 
		will result in a diagram that updates very infrequently which may both be confusing and not what is 
		desired.</li>
		<li><b>XXX</b> - an interval in milliseconds, the diagram will be updated every XXX ms regardless of if
		the underlying Statistics have changed or not.</li>
		</ul>
		
		<p>Be aware of the fact that all statistics for these diagrams are always collected internally, i.e.
		you can open the diagram after running your LoadTests and see the results. This is recommended as it 
		does not take any performance from the UI during LoadTesting.</p>
		
		<subsection name="The LoadTest Statistics Graph">
		<p>The statistics diagram shows a number of statistics for a selected TestStep or the TestCase
		Total. The toolbar at the top contains a combo-box for selecting which step to display and a 
		button to the far right for exporting the currently selected steps data to a comma separated file.</p>
		
		<p align="center"><img src="images/loadtest_statistics_diagram.gif" alt="Load Test Statistics Graph"/></p>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="The Statistics History Graph">
		<p>The statistics history diagram shows a selected statistic for all TestSteps in the TestCase. 
		The toolbar at the top contains a combo-box for selecting which statistic to display and a 
		button to the far right for exporting the currently selected statistics data to a comma separated file.</p>
		
		<p align="center"><img src="images/loadtest_statistics_history_diagram.gif" alt="Load Test Statistics History Graph"/></p>
		
		</subsection>

		<p><hr size="1"/>Next: <a href="comparison.html">JMeter Load Test Comparison</a></p>
		</section>
    </body>
</document>

