<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Web Service Monitoring - TCPMon SOAP Monitor in soapUI</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
		<section name="SOAP Monitor">
		<p>soapUI 2.0 adds powerful SOAP Monitoring possibilities, allowing you to capture and perform SOAP traffic analysis 
		between an existing client and server. The captured traffic can be used to generate both TestCases and MockServices,
		and soapUI Pro adds (extremely cool) Coverage possibilities allowing you to monitor the actual utilization of the 
		monitored WSDL contract(s).</p>
		<p>Start the SOAP Monitor from the Project popup menu with the "Launch SOAP Monitor" action:</p>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/start_monitor.gif" alt="SOAP Monitoring Launcher in soapUI"/></p>
		<p>Specify which port the monitor should listen on and which mode it should run in:</p>
		<ul>
		<li><b>Http Proxy</b> : starts the monitor as an HTTP Proxy. When selecting this option, configure the monitors' host:port as
		the proxy for the client you want to monitor. Also, set proxy host:port in global settings.</li>
		<li><b>HTTP Tunnel</b> : starts the monitor as a HTTP Tunnel, point your client directly at the host:port of the monitor (with
		the rest of the URL intact. The "Add endpoint" option will add the created tunnels endpoint to all interfaces in the project
		, for easy redirection of requests within soapUI. Also specify key store, password, key password, trust store and trust store 
		password. <b>Client key store</b> and <b>key store password</b> are used for authetication on end point server.</li>
		</ul>
		<p>The Incoming Request/Response WSS settings are used to select the <a href="../projects/wss.html#Incoming_WSS">Incoming WSS
		 configurations</a>
		 to use for decrypting or validating monitored messages, which can be useful for viewing encrypted content
		and validating security</p>
		<p>Reuse request state is used for HTTP attributes that may persist from request to request, such as cookies and authentication
		 credentials. 
		</p>
		<subsection name="Main Window">
		<p>The SOAP Monitor is displayed with the following window components (top to bottom):</p>
		<ul>
		<li>The main toolbar with options for starting/stopping/re-configuring the SOAP Monitor</li>
		<li>The available monitor tabs ("Traffic Log" and "Coverage" in soapUI Pro)</li>
		<li>A traffic-log toolbar with actions to create requests, TestCases, MockServices and clear the log</li>
		<li>A filter bar for filtering out which requests to show in the traffic log</li>
		<li>The traffic log itself containing rows for captured messages</li>
		<li>A "Message Content" inspector that displays the actual content of the message selected in the table. All standard
		request/response editor views and inspectors are available</li>
		</ul>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/monitor_1.gif" alt="Web Service Monitoring - SOAP Monitor in soapUI"/></p>
		<p>Once started, the monitor will display captured messages as rows in the log table with their relevant data. Requests
		that belong to Interfaces/Operations available in the containing project will automatically be mapped to these and 
		use underlying schema-information in the message inspectors in the Message Content views:</p>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/monitor_3.gif" alt="Web Service Monitoring - Message Content in SOAP Monitor in soapUI"/></p>
		<p>By default, the log will keep the 100 most recent messages, this can be adjusted in the SOAP Monitor options dialog
		available from the top toolbar.</p>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="Using Captured Messages">
		<p>The 3 left-most buttons in the traffic tables toolbar allow for creation of new items from captures messages:</p>
		<ul>
		<li><b>Create Requests</b> : creates requests under their corresponding operations for each selected request in the traffic log</li>
		<li><b>Create TestCase</b> : prompts to create a TestCase (or add to an existing one), by creating TestRequests corresponding
		to the currently selected requests in the traffic log</li>
		<li><b>Create MockService</b> : prompts to create a MockService (or add to an existing one), by creating MockOperations or MockResponses
		corresponding to the currently selected requests in the traffic log</li>
		</ul>
		<p>The combination of the last 2 can be used to record and simulate an entire converation between a client and server for 
		replaying, testing, etc..</p>
		</subsection>
		 <p><hr size="1"/>Next: <a href="coverage.html">SOAP Monitor Coverage</a></p>
		</section>
    </body>
</document>
