<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Inspecting WSDL - the WSDL Content Viewer in soapUI</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
		<section name="WSDL Content Viewer">
		<p>The Interface viewer allows relatively easy navigation and inspection of the entire contract for an imported WSDL, 
		including all imported and included WSDL and XSD files and their contained types, definitions, etc.</p>
		
		<p>The navigation tree to the left shows contained elements in the contract, selecting a node will 
		highlight that element in its containing file to the right, automatically switching tabs if necessary.
		Elements referring to other elements in the contract are also double clickable and will focus to the
		referenced element in the tree as follows;</p>
		<table>
		<tr><th>Double-click on</th><th>will focus on (if available)</th></tr>
		<tr><td>Global Element</td><td>its Complex Type</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Message Part</td><td>its Complex Type or Global Element</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Operation input/output</td><td>its Message</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Binding Operation input/output</td><td>its corresponding Operation input/output</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Port</td><td>its Binding Operation</td></tr>
		</table>
		
		<p>The viewer toolbar has the following actions (left to right)</p>
		<ul>
		<li><b>Back</b> - navigates to the previously selected node</li>
		<li><b>Forward</b> - navigates to the next selected node (after navigating back..)</li>
		<li><b>Update Definition</b> - updates the WSDL contract as described under 
		<a href="index.html#Updating_the_Interface_Definition">Updating the Interface Definition</a></li>
		<li><b>Export WSDL</b> - prompts to export the entire sadly and all imported and included files to a local folder. Import or Includes
		are replaced with valid relative ones.</li>
		</ul>
		
		<p>The following screenshot shows the viewer for the PayPal API;</p>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/interface_viewer.gif" alt="the WSDL Content Inspector"/></p>
	
		 <p><hr size="1"/>Next: <a href="wsi.html ">WS-I Compliance for Compliance Tests</a></p>
		</section>
    </body>
</document>