<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
  ~ soapUI, copyright (C) 2004-2008 eviware.com
  ~
  ~ soapUI is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it under the
  ~ terms of version 2.1 of the GNU Lesser General Public License as published by
  ~ the Free Software Foundation.
  ~
  ~ soapUI is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without
  ~ even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.
  ~ See the GNU Lesser General Public License for more details at gnu.org.
  -->

<document>
    <properties>
        <title>userguide - REST Resources</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
		<section name="REST Resources">
		<p>As described in the <a href="index.html">REST Services Overview</a>, Resources are available as child
        items to a REST Service and contain either child resources or requests. Resources are created either
        when initially creating the REST Service or by selecting the "New Resource" option from the Service/Resource
        popup. Either way, the following dialog will be displayed:</p>
         <p align="center"><img src="images/new-resource.gif"></img></p>
            <p>The dialog has the following options:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>Resource Name : the name of the resource</li>
                <li>Resource Path/Endpoint : a path or complete endpoint for the resource</li>
                <li>Extract Params : select this option to extract parameters/path information from the specified
                endpoint/path.</li>
                <li>Parameters : a table containing extracted or manually added parameters.</li>
                <li>Create Request : option to create a default request for the resource</li>
            </ul>
            <p>The Extract Params button will parse the specified endpoint and try to extract query, matrix and
            template parameters from it. Also a hostname will be removed and a path components corresponding to
            the REST Services Base Path and containing Resources' path will be removed. For example specifying</p>
            <source>http://search.yahooapis.com/ImageSearchService/V1/imageSearch?appid=YahooDemo&amp;query=Madonna&amp;output=xml</source>
            <p>and pressing the Extract button will result in</p>
            <p align="center"><img src="images/extract-params-sample.gif"></img></p>
            <p>As you can see, the host has been removed and query parameters have been extracted.</p>
         <subsection name="Properties and Actions">
             <p>The following properties are available at the bottom left for a REST Resource:</p>
             <ul>
                 <li>Name : the name of the resource</li>
                 <li>Description : a short description</li>
                 <li>Path : the path of the resource relative to parent resource/service</li>
             </ul>
             <p>Right-clicking a resource shows a popup with the following actions:</p>
             <ul>
                 <li>Show Resource Viewer - opens the Resource Viewer (see below)</li>
                 <li>New Request - prompts to create a new Request for this Resource</li>
                 <li>New Child Resource - prompts to create a new child Resource to this Resource using the above
                 described dialog</li>
                 <li>Clone Resource - prompts to clone this Resource including all Requests and children</li>
                 <li>Rename - prompts to rename the Resource</li>
                 <li>Delete - prompts to delete the Resource</li>
                 <li>Online Help - shows this page in a browser</li>
             </ul>
         </subsection>
            <subsection name="REST Resource Viewer">
                <p>The REST Resource View is as follows:</p>
                <p align="center"><img src="images/resource-editor.gif"></img></p>
                <p>The toolbar at the top contains an action to create a new request for this Resource together
                with a text field to edit the path of the Resource. The "Resource Parameters" tab contains
                all parameters for this resource as described in <a href="params.html">Parameters and Representations</a></p>
            </subsection>

		 <p><hr size="1"/>Next: <a href="requests.html">REST Requests</a></p>
		</section>
    </body>
</document>
