<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Web Service testing Tutorial with soapUI - create tests from a WSDL</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
		<section name="Getting Started with soapUI">
		<p>Below you'll find a step-by-step guide to creating your first soapUI project with some requests and a TestCase. The
		sample will use the amazon.com web service</p>
		
		 <p>Although soapUI should be easy to get started with, you will need to have a good grasp of the following 
		 concepts and technologies to get the most out of soapUI's functionality.</p>
		 <ul>
		 	<li>WSDL - basic concepts (services, ports, bindings, port types), relation to xml-schema</li>
		 	<li>SOAP - basic concepts, relation to WSDL (bindings, etc), different encoding types (soap-encoded/literal) and 
		 	message styles (document/rpc)</li>
		 	<li>XML and related technologies - XPath, XML Schema, namespaces, etc</li>
		 </ul>
		
		 <p>You can find most specifications at <a target="_new" href="http://www.w3.org">W3C Web Site</a> and tutorials
		 at several sites, for example <a target="_new" href="http://www.w3schools.com">W3Schools Web Site</a> and
		 <a target="_new" href="http://www.zvon.org/o_html/group_web_services.html">zvon.org Web Site</a>.</p>
		
		<subsection name="Install and Run soapUI">
		
		<p>Install and Run soapUI in one of the following ways:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>By launching the latest version with Java WebStart from this sites' <a href="../index.html">top page</a></li>
		<li>By downloading and installing soapUI using the windows installer from 
		<a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=136013">SourceForge soapUI Web Site</a>, which 
		includes the required 1.6 JRE (Java Runtime Environment). Use the installer if you are unsure about your systems Java 
		installation or if you want startup menu icons and an uninstaller.</li>
		<li>By downloading the binary distribution from 
		<a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=136013">SourceForge</a> 
		(for example "soapui-1.5-bin.zip") and unzipping it manually and running the included bin\soapui.bat (or .sh) 
		script (you	will need Java in your path).</li>
		</ul>
		<p>In any case, soapUI should start and display an empty Workspace to get started with.</p>
		</subsection>
		
		 <subsection name="The Getting Started guide">
		 
		 <table>
		 	<tr>
		 		<th>Page</th>
		 		<th>What it describes</th>
		 	</tr>
		 	<tr>
		 		<td><a href="your_first_soapUI_project.html">Your first soapUI Project</a></td>
		 		<td>Shows how to open and start a soapUI Project and how to make your first Web Service Request</td>
		 	</tr>
		 	<tr>
		 		<td><a href="functional.html">Getting Started with Functional Testing</a></td>
		 		<td>Shows you how create a Web Service Test and how to do validations</td>
		 	</tr>
		 	<tr>
		 		<td><a href="loadtest.html">Getting Started with Web Service Load Testing</a></td>
		 		<td>Shows you how create a Web Service load test</td>
		 	</tr>
		 	<tr>
		 		<td><a href="mocking.html">Getting Started with Web Service Mocking</a></td>
		 		<td>Shows you how create a Web Service Mock</td>
		 	</tr>
		 </table>
		 </subsection>
		 

		 
		
		 <p><hr size="1"/>Next: <a href="your_first_soapUI_project.html">Your first soapUI Project</a></p>
		</section>
    </body>
</document>
