<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Quick start with soapUI Sample Project file</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
		
			<section name="soapUI example Movies">
			<div>
			<p>
			As an easy start, before doing the tutorial watch the Sample Project Movie.		
			</p>
			<p>
			<br/>
				<ul STYLE="list-style-image: url(../images/film.png)">
					<li><a href="#" onclick="openVideo('../movies/sample_project/sample_project.html');"><b>Sample Project Movie</b> (17:23)</a></li>
				</ul>
			<br/>
			</p>
			</div>		
		</section> 
		
		
						
				<table class="relatedInfo" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0">
	<tr class="a">
    	<td width="75" style="padding-top:5px">
        	<img src="../images/where_do_i_start.jpg" alt="Start soapUI Testing" longdesc="http://www.soapui.org"></img>
        </td>
        <td>
            <table class="relatedInner">
              <tr>
                <td>
                	<span class="relatedInfoHeader">Did you know?</span>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>
                    <div>
						<p>
						There is a commercial version of soapUI out called <b><i>soapUI Pro</i></b>.
						</p>
						<p>
						<b><i>soapUI Pro</i></b> contains productivity enhancements as well as offers Professional World Class support. contains productivity enhancements as well as offers Professional World Class support.
						</p>
                    </div>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr align="right">
              	<td>
                	<span class="relatedLinks"><a href="http://www.eviware.com/component/option,com_wrapper/Itemid,41/" title="try soapUI Pro" onclick="javascript:urchinTracker:('/downloadTrial');">
                                               <img src="images/try_pro_100.png" alt="Try soapUI pro to soap test" width="101" height="20" longdesc="http://www.eviware.com"/></a></span>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </table>
		</td>
	</tr>
</table>
		

		
		<section name="soapUI Sample Project">
			<p>We know that getting started with a new application always is a challenge. 
			In order to make it easier for you, soapUI comes shipping with a sample soapUI Project file. 
			This soapUI Projects illustrates some of the basic concepts of soapUI and can be used as a soapUI 
			starting point; try out the project, run the included MockService and the included tests in 
			order familiarize yourself with the soapUI interface, and then move on to the Getting 
			Started tutorial. 
			</p> 
			<p>
			Here are the main concepts that are illustrated in the soapUI Project.
			</p>
		</section>
		<section name="Web Service Mocking">
			<p>
			Web Service Mocking is way to fake the functionality of a Web Service in soapUI; to create a Mock Up.
			But why do you need such functionality?
			</p> 
			
			<p>
			Web Service Mocking is very useful in projects where implementation of the 
			Web Service has not started or is not finished for use yet or where you for some 
			other reasons can't access the Web Services live.
			</p> 
			
			<p>
			In other words, Web Service Mocking makes it possible for you to start creating test for a 
			Web Service the same time you start to develop the same Web Service. This means, when the real 
			Web Service is ready for testing; you can already have the tests done. This can be extremely 
			powerful and will make it possible to work according to Test Driven or Agile Methodologies.
			</p> 
			
			<p>
			In soapUI you can create a MockService simply by choosing to add a 
			Web Service Request to a MockService in order for the MockService to 
			listen to it. Or you can even right-click the Interface Icon and choose "Generate MockService", which
			will generate a MockService containing each defined response in the Interface.
			</p>
			
			<p align="center"><img src="images/add_to_mockservice.gif" alt="Add to Web Service Mock"/></p>
			
			<p>
			You can then choose how to Respond to the Request and choose how to 
			Dispatch (send out) different responses.
			</p>
			
			
			<p>
			Now, let's take a look at how the Mock Service works. Open the MockService, called <i>SampleServiceSoapBinding MockService</i>, by 
			double clicking on it.
			</p>
			
			
			<p align="center"><img src="images/mockservice_view.gif" alt="Web Service Mock Response View"/></p>
			
			<p>
			Browse through the different Interfaces in the 
			MockService; login, logout, search, and buy, and see what we do with  
			different requests. As you see all the requests are dispatched using 
			scripts. This is by far the most common way of dispatching, but early 
			on in a project you might just want to create a set of responses and 
			dispatch them in sequence or at random.
			</p>
			
			<p>
			You can start the MockService by pressing the MockService Start button.
			</p>
			
			<p align="center"><img src="images/start_mockservice.gif"  alt="Starting a Web Service Simulation"/></p>
			
		</section>
		
		<section name="Web Service Inspection">
			<p>
			Web Service Inspection a fancy way of saying looking at the Web Service. 
			Good support for Web Service inspection can be very important early in the project when you want to 
			find out how a Web Service.
			</p>

			<p>
			Inspecting the Web Service can be done in two ways; inspecting the Web Service and 
			making Web Service requests.
			</p>
			
		<subsection name="Inspect a WSDL">
				<p>
				You can inspect a WSDL by Double Clicking Interface Icon. 
				You then get the Interface Viewer, a very useful tool for seeing what the WSDL 
				contains and how it is structured.
				</p>

				<p align="center"><img src="images/interface_viewer_small.gif" alt="Inspecting a WSDL"/></p>
		
				<p>
				This is a structured way of looking at your WSDL. Just browsing the XML of the WSDL is very
				cluttered and a WSDL often is to complicated too look at in its entirety and 
				therefore it is seldom done, resulting in lower WSDL understanding. In other words, since WSDL's 
				are so complicated people don't read it, and remember, the WSDL is the specification 
				(contract actually, bet let's not get into that...) 
				and how well you use it depends on how well you understand it. This is a serious problem 
				early on in projects, the people in the project don't understand the Contract. 
				The soapUI Interface Viewer is a great tool for solving this problem.
				</p>
				
				<p>
				Now let's Inspect the Web Service. Inspect the Sample Project WSDL by double clicking the 
				SampleServiceSoapBinding Interface Icon. 
				Use the Interface Viewer to familiarize yourself with the WSDL, the move on to Web Service Requests.
				</p>
		
				
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Make Service Requests"> 		
				<p>
				Expand the login Interface and double click the login request. 
				Login by using the username Login and the password Login123. 
				You should now have gotten the response containing a sessionID 
				<i>9575658833177431</i>
				</p>
		
				<p><b>Go ahead, try it!</b></p>
		
				<p align="center"><img src="images/first_request.gif" alt="Web Service Request View"/></p>
		
				<p>
				No response? don't forget to start the MockService. We also need to 
				copy the sessionID and use it to logout.
				</p>
			</subsection>
		</section>
		
		<section name="Functional Tests of Web Services">
		<subsection name="Test Structure for Web Services"> 	
			<p>
				Let's move on and look at how tests work in soapUI. We have created three different 
				TestSuites all containing different TestCases. A TestCase is made up of several 
				steps, called TestSteps. The structure of a soapUI project is like this;
			</p>
			
				<ul>
				<li>Project</li>
				<li>Interface</li>
				<li>TestSuites</li>
				<ul>
					<li>TestCases</li>
					<ul>
						<li>TestSteps</li>
						<li>LoadTests</li>
					</ul>
				</ul>
				<li>MockServices</li>
				</ul>
			
		
			<p>
			As you can see there is also something called LoadTests, we can gather what they 
			are, but we'll go into detail more what they actually do and how they actually work later.
			</p>
			</subsection>
			
			<subsection name="SOAP Functional Tests in detail"> 
			<p>
			Now let's examine a Functional Test in a TestCase. Expand the TestSuite Sample 
			Simple TestSuite and then double click the TestCase Simple Login and Logout w. Properties Steps. 
			As you can see the case consists of 5 TestSteps. 
			</p>
			
			<p align="center"><img src="images/simple_test_view.gif"  alt="Web Service Functional Tests"/></p>
			
			<p>
			You can also click the 
			Description tab in order to see the in test documentation.
			</p>
			
			<p align="center"><img src="images/description.gif" alt="Web Service Test Case Description"/></p>
			
			<p>
			The step consists of three different types of TestSteps; One PropertyStep, 
			Two Test Requests and Two PropertyTransfer Steps.
			This is what they do:
			</p>
			
			<ul>
				<li><b>PropertySteps: </b> Stores Properties for later use. In our case it's the Username and Password required to login.</li> 
				<li><b>Test Requests: </b> The actual requests to the server. In this case login and logout. </li> 
				<li><b>PropertyTransfers: </b> A step used for moving properties between different steps. This might 
				be from a Property Step to a request like the step Property Transfer: Move 
				Username and Password does, or to move properties from a Test Request to another, 
				like the step Property Transfer: Move sessionID does. </li> 
			</ul>
			</subsection>
			
			<subsection name="Functional Tests continued">
			<p>
			Double Click on each step and examine how they work. Double Click the TestSteps and you'll 
			get the TestStep editor. You can for example see that the step 
			<i>Property Transfer: Move Username and Password</i> moves does two transfers in two Properties.
			</p>
			
			<p align="center"><img src="images/PropertyTransfer_moveuser.gif" alt="Transfering Test Properties"/></p>
			
			<ul>
				<li>
					First it takes does the TransferUser Transfer. It takes the Property <i>Username</i> from 
					the step <i>Properties: Username and Password</i> and moves it to the step 
					<i>Test Request: login</i>.
				</li>
				<li>
					Then it takes does the TransferPass Transfer. It takes the Property <i>Password</i> from 
					the said step <i>Properties: Username and Password</i> and also moves it to the step 
					<i>Test Request: login</i>.
				</li>
			</ul>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="SOA Test Assertions">
			<p>
				An important feature in Test is the assertions in Test Requests. Open the Test Step 
				<i>Test Request: logout</i>. 
			</p>
			<p align="center"><img src="images/Assertions.gif"  alt="SOA Test Assertions"/></p>					
			<p>
				In the TestStep we have four assertions, all asserting different 
				things; That the response is a SOAP response, that it complies with the schema, that is isn't 
				a SOAP fault and something called an XPATH match. The XPath Match validates that a certain 
				element has the value expected.
			</p>
			<p align="center"><img src="images/xpath_match.gif" alt="XPATH Matching of SOAP"/></p>		
			</subsection>
			
			<subsection name="The Test Run">
			<p>
			Now that we have examined the TestCase, let's run it!
			Press the Play Button and the Test will run and the Test Case progress bar should be full 
			and green.
			</p>
			
			<p>  
			<b><i>Does it turn red after only a step?</i></b>
			</p>
			
			<p> 
			Don't forget to start the MockService. 
			</p>
			
			<p>
			<b><i>Or... did you run the TestStep earlier?</i></b> 
			</p>
			
			<p>
			Look at the response, maybe the response is that you already have a session?
			</p>
			
			<p> 
			We logged in earlier and aren't allowed to log in again, let's just go to the 
			MockService, stop it and restart it, clearing any server side sessions. 
			Now, rerun the test.
			</p>
			</subsection>			
		</section>
		<section name="SOA Load Tests">
			<p>
			Something very useful in soapUI is the ability to quickly create LoadTests. 
			Why is this useful? The earlier you are able to run load tests, the earlier you 
			can discover any performance issues. In soapUI you create a LoadTest simply by 
			choosing a functional test, right-clicking it and saying New LoadTest. Done!
			</p>
			
			<p align="center"><img src="images/new_loadtest.gif "  alt="SOA Load Test"/></p>
			
			<p>
			This makes soapUI LoadTest extra good since the immediately enable you to load test 
			the functionality not that the Web Service can respond quickly to the same Request 
			over and over again. LoadTests are byproducts of the Functional Tests.
			</p>
			
			<p>
			<b>Now, let's examine a Load Test!</b>
			</p>
			
			<p>
			Go to the TestSuite Sample expanded TestSuite and the TestCase Search and Buy 
			TestCase. There you will find for LoadTests, one for each LoadTest strategy.
			Choose the Simple Strategy LoadTest. The simple strategy is a basic strategy with 
			a random delay.
			</p>
			
			<p align="center"><img src="images/simple_strategy_loadtest.gif" alt="Load Test Pre Configured Strategy"/></p>
			
			<p>
			The first figure to configure is the Test Delay, this sets the 
			number of milliseconds our base delay will be (1000 is one second). 
			The second figure is the random variable which sets how the delay should be 
			changed at random, the value 0.5 means it should be half, that is between 500 
			and 1000 milliseconds. 
			</p>
			
			<p>
			What would the value 0 mean? That's right no random delay at all, just 1000 
			milliseconds all the time.
			</p>
			
			<p>
			<b>Now, let's run it!</b>
			</p>
			
			<p>
			As you see the numbers of the test are continuously updated. You can see figures like 
			the response times throughput per second (tps) assertions errors and more. You can 
			also press the graph button and see a graph of the test run.
			</p>
			
			<p align="center"><img src="images/LoadTest_Graph.gif"  alt="Web Service Test Graph"/></p>
			
			<p>
			Read more about <a href="../userguide/loadtest/index.html">the Load Test Interface here </a> 
			and the <a href="../userguide/loadtest/configuration.html">different Load Testing strategies here</a>.
			</p>
			
			<p>
			You can also do LoadTest Assertions. One of the more important is the Max Errors Step. 
			This is used for allowing the maximum number of errors allowed in a test run.
			</p>
			
			<p align="center"><img src="images/max_errors_assertions.gif"  alt="Load Test Max Assertion"/></p>
			
			<p>
			This will lead us to the final example, discovering an error in our MockService.
			</p>
			
			<subsection name="An error in our MockService"> 		
				<p>
				Go to the TestSuite <i>Sample TestSuite fails if we don't get faults</i> and the TestCase 
				<i>TestCase: Searching after Logging out LoadTests</i>. There you will find a load test called
				<i>LoadTest with Multiple Tests (will fail)</i>. Open it and run it. After a time this test will fail
				</p>
			
				<p align="center"><img src="images/failed_loadtest.gif"  alt="A Failed Load Test"/></p>
			
				<p>
				<b>Why?</b>
				</p>
			
				<p>
				Because multiple users are simultaneously logging in with the same username, which is not allowed by the MockService
				</p>
			
				<p><b>Go ahead, try it!</b></p>
			
				<p align="center"><img src="images/first_request.gif"  alt="Web Service Request"/></p>
			</subsection>
		</section>
		<section name="Web Service Tutorial Continuation">
		<p>
		Now you can continue running the tests and look at different ways of doing tests.
		</p>
		
		<p>
		<b>Enjoy!</b>
		</p>
		
		</section>
    </body>
</document>