<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Web Service testing Tutorial with soapUI - Your First Web Service Test Project</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
		<section name="Your first soapUI Project">
		<p>If you have a copy of soapUI up and running, let's get going by creating your first project!</p>
		<p>We are going to do the following:
		<ol>
			<li>Set up a test project</li>
			<li>Add a WSDl that defines the Web Service</li>
			<li>Make some Requests</li>
		</ol>
		</p>
		

		 <subsection name="Create or Import a Web Service testing project">
		 
		<columns><column>
		<ul>
		<li>Right click on the workspace node in the left navigation pane and select "New WSDL Project"</li>
		<li>You will be prompted for a project name and then for a local file where the project should be saved</li>
		<li>If all is OK an empty project will be created in the workspace</li>
		</ul>
		<p>If you have downloaded the offline version, a sample project is included in the root folder; select 
		"Import Project" instead and browse to the sample-soapui-project.xml file.</p>
		<p>Read more about projects in the <a href="../userguide/projects/index.html">soapUI User Guide</a></p>
		</column>
		<column>
		<img src="images/getting_started_1.gif" alt="Create a project from a WSDL"/></column></columns>
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection name="Add a WSDL to create tests from">
		<columns><column><div>
		Now that you have a project you can start adding Interfaces (i.e. Web Service PortTypes) to it.</div>
		<ul>
		<li>Right click on the project node and select "Add WSDL from URL"</li>
		<li>You will be prompted for the URL to the Interfaces WSDL; enter 
		<pre>http://webservices.amazon.com/AWSECommerceService/<br/>AWSECommerceService.wsdl</pre> 
		to add the amazon web service and select "Ok".</li>
		<li>soapUI will prompt you if you want to create default requests for each operation, simply select "Yes"</li>
		<li>soapUI will now add the SOAP/Http Binding for the amazon "AWSECommerceServicePortType" PortType to your project
		and create nodes for each operation.</li>
		</ul>
		<p>Read more about interfaces in the <a href="userguide/interfaces/index.html">soapUI User Guide</a></p>
		</column>
		<column><img src="images/getting_started_2.gif" alt="Add WSDL to create tests from"/></column></columns>
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection name="Try some Web Service requests">
		<columns><column><div>
		Now that you have added the amazon Web Service you can start playing around with some requests. 
		When you added the interface in the previous step soapUI created default requests for each operation in 
		accordance with their WSDL and Schema definition.</div>
		<ul>
		<li>Expand the Interface node and any Operation node under it, you should see the created "Request 1".</li>
		<li>Double-click the request node to open the request editor in the right part of soapUI (see image below)</li>
		<li>The request editor is divided into 3 parts:
			<ul>
				<li>A toolbar at the top with a number of request related actions/options</li>
		   		<li>A request area to the left</li>
		   		<li>A response area to the right</li>
		   </ul>
		   </li>
		   <li>The default request created by soapUI will have "?" for each value that needs to be supplied in the request, 
		   replace or remove any values as required and post request by pressing the left-most toolbar button (a green arrow)</li>
		   <li>The request will run in the background and its response will be displayed in the right editor</li>
		</ul>
		<p>Read more about working with requests in the <a href="../userguide/requests.html">soapUI User Guide</a></p>
		</column>
		<column><img src="images/getting_started_3.gif" alt="Web Service Requset in soapUI"/></column></columns>
		
		<p align="center"><img src="images/getting_started_7.gif"  alt="Soap Test Request and Response View"/></p>
		 </subsection>
		 
		
		 <p><hr size="1"/>Next: <a href="functional.html">Getting Started with Functional Testing for Web Services</a></p>
		 </section>
	</body>
</document>
