<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>eclipse Web service testing with the soapUI Plugin</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
		<section name="Getting Started with Testing Web Services">
		<p>The eclipse-plugin can be either downloaded from 
		<a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=136013">SourceForge download pages</a> or 
		through the update site (see below). If downloading, just unzip the file into your eclipse directory and start/restart eclipse.</p>
		
		<subsection name="eclipse Update Site">
		<p>An eclipse update site is now available at http://www.soapui.org/eclipse/update/site.xml, Install the 
		soapUI eclipse plugin with the following steps:</p>
		<columns>
		<column><div><ol>
		<li>Select "Help"/"Software Updates"/"Find and Install..."</li>
		<li>Select the "Search for new features to install" option</li>
		<li>Press the "New Remote Site" button and add the information shown in the image to the right</li>
		<li>Select Finish and the follow the dialogs to install the soapUI feature... restart eclipse and get going!</li>
		</ol></div>
		</column>
		<column>
		<img src="images/new_update_site.gif" alt="eclipse update for soa testing"/>
		</column></columns>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="The soapUI Perspective">
		<columns>
		<column>
		<div>Once installed, open the soapUI Perspective by using the standard Window/Open Perspective/Other.. Command and 
		selecting "soapUI" from the list. The perspective will open 2 views;</div>
		<ul>
		<li>A "soapUI Navigator" view to the left containing the same Navigator and Details tab as the standalone soapUI 
		version.</li>
		<li>A "soapUI Logs" view to the bottom containing the same log tabs as the standalone soapUI version. </li>
		</ul>
		<p>Navigation/actions work the same as in the standalone version, windows are opened as tabs on the eclipse desktop
		and can be moved/docked around as usual</p>
		<p>Of course, the above mentioned views can be added to any perspective using the Window/Show View/Other... Command
		and selecting either one of them in the soapUI group.</p>
		</column>
		<column>
		<img src="images/show_view.gif" alt="soap test tool"/>
		</column></columns>
		
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="soapUI Preferences">
		<p>Most soapUI Settings are available from the standard Window/Preferences dialog under the soapUI node;</p>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/eclipse-preferences.gif" alt="soap test"/></p>
		
		</subsection>
		</section>
    </body>
</document>
