<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
  ~ soapUI, copyright (C) 2004-2008 eviware.com
  ~
  ~ soapUI is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it under the
  ~ terms of version 2.1 of the GNU Lesser General Public License as published by
  ~ the Free Software Foundation.
  ~
  ~ soapUI is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without
  ~ even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.
  ~ See the GNU Lesser General Public License for more details at gnu.org.
  -->

<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Web Service Functional Testing - SOAP TestRequests</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
		<section name="SOAP Requests">
		 
		 <p>SOAP TestRequests extends standard requests with the possibility to
		add any number of Assertions that will be applied to the response received for the request for validating its content.</p>
		 <p> TestRequests are either created from standard requests using their "Add to Testcase" action or from the TestCase Editors popup 
		 menu with the "Insert Step -&gt; Test Request" option (shown to the right), which will prompt for which Interface or Operation
		  the request should be create for.</p>
		  
		  <p>When you create a SOAP Test Request the following dialog will prompt to add certain standard assertions</p>
		  <p align="center">
			<img src="images/add_request_to_testcase.gif" alt="Add Request to TestCase dialog containing Standard Assertions"/>
			</p>
		 <p>SOAP TestRequests are submitted either manually through their editors submit actions or when running
		 the TestCase containing the request. The requests response is validated against a requests assertions and the
		 requests icon changes to reflect the result of the validations; green means that all validations were ok, red means that some validations 
		 failed. A grey background icon indicates that the request has not yet been submitted for validation, a white 
		 background indicates that the TestRequest lacks assertions</p>

		  <subsection name="TestRequest Actions">
		   <p>
		  The following SOAP Request specific actions are available from the test-request nodes' right-button menu:
		  <ul>
		  		<li><b>Change Operation</b> - prompts to change the operation for this TestRequest (see below)</li>
		  		<li><b>Select Operation</b> - selects this TestRequests operation in the Navigator</li>
		  		<li><b>Clone Assertions (soapUI Pro only)</b> - prompts to clone assertions from this TestRequest to 
		  		other TestRequests (see below)</li>
 		  </ul></p>
		 </subsection>
		 
		 	 
		  <subsection name="TestRequest Details Tab">
		   <p>
		 The "Details" tab shown in the bottom-left shows the same properties when a TestRequest node is selected in 
		 the navigation tree as for a standard request ( 
		 see the <a href="../requests.html#Request_Details_Tab">Request Details Tab</a> for more detailed information) 
		 and adds two read-only properties:
		 <ul>
		 <li><b>Interface</b> : the name of the Interface for this TestRequest</li>
		 <li><b>Operation</b> : the name of the Operation for this TestRequest</li>
		 </ul>
		 
		 </p>
		 </subsection>
		 
		  <subsection name="Change Operation">
		 <p>Selecting to change the operation for a TestRequest opens the following dialog:</p>
		 <p align="center"><img src="images/change_operation.gif"/></p>
		 <p>The list of Interfaces displays those available in the current project, the list of Operations
		 is updated accordingly.</p>
		 </subsection>
		 
		  <subsection name="The TestRequest Editor">
		  <p>Double-clicking a TestRequest in either the navigator or the TestCase Editor Pane opens the requests
		  editor which is more or less a copy of the standard Request Editor with the following exception:</p>
		  <ul>
		  	<li>The second toolbar button "Add to Testcase" has been replaced with "Add Assertion" which prompts
		  	to add an assertion to the TestRequest</li>
		  	<li>The clone action now clones the TestRequest and appends the cloned request to the containing TestCase</li>
		  	<li>Under the request/response panes there is a now a tabbed pane containing 2 tabs; the "Assertions" tab and
		  	the "Request Log" tab (both described below).</li>
		  </ul>
		 <p>All other editing, submittal, validation functionality is the same as in the request editor</p>
		 </subsection>
		 
		
		 <p><hr size="1"/>Next: <a href="rest-requests.html">REST Requests</a></p>
		</section>
    </body>
</document>
