<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>functional Web Service testing</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
		<section name="SoapUI Projects for testing WSTF Scenarios">
		<p>
		Included with the SoapUI 2.5.1 Release are soapUI Projects containing TestSuites/TestCases for validating 
		<a href="http://www.wstf.org/" >WSTF scenario</a> implementations. Current TetsRequest are configured for SOAP 1.1 versions of 
		WSTF scenarios part (see the Interface property of particular TestRequest). This can be reverted to soap1.2 version by changing 
		the operation of the request to soap12binding which already	is included in Projects as one of the interfaces.</p>
        <p>Two different projects, for two scenarios are added</p>
        <ul>
            <li><a href="#WSTF_SC002_Project">WSTF SC002 Project</a> - for testing if 
            <a href="http://www.wstf.org/docs/scenarios/sc002/sc002.xml" >sc002 - Notify-Echo</a> is properly implemented</li>
            
            <li><a href="#WSTF_SC003_Project">WSTF SC003 Project</a> - for testing if 
            <a href="http://www.wstf.org/docs/scenarios/sc003/sc003.xml" >sc003 - WS-Addressing</a> is propertly implemented</li>
        </ul>
						
		<subsection name="WSTF SC002 Project">
		<p>The project is divided into TestSteps and TestCases as specified in <a href="http://www.wstf.org/docs/scenarios/sc002/sc002.xml#sec4">
		WSTF specification</a> and every TestRequest has assertions in order to validate the given scenario.</p>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/wstfSc002_project.gif" alt="WSTF sc002 project"/></p>
		<p>XML project file which can be used for remote or local project import can be found at 
		<a href="projects/WSTF-SC002-Scenario-soapui-project.xml">http://www.soapui.org/wstf/projects/WSTF-SC002-Scenario-soapui-project.xml</a>.</p>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="WSTF SC003 Project">
		<p>This project is testing properly implemented WS-Addressing scenarios. It is divided into TestSteps 
		and TestCases as specified in <a href="http://www.wstf.org/docs/scenarios/sc003/sc003.xml#sec3">
		WSTF specification.</a> For "Sync" tests, TestCases consist of only one TestRequest which have properly defined assertions in order to validate 
		given scenario. For "Async" tests, due to the need to test response on a new connection there is a property named publicIp defined 
		on the Project level that must manually be set to a publicly accessible IP address. Main TestRequest has "wsa:replyTo" (for example for "1.4 Async Echo + Wsa TestCase") 
		or "wsa:FaultTo" (1.6 Async Faulting Echo + Wsa TestCase) use this "publicIp" property for indicating where to redirect the response.  
		</p>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/asyncTestCase_wsaInspector.gif" alt="Async TestCase - WS-A inspector setting"/></p>
		<p>Also there are more TestSteps defined for this kind of TestCases. Last TestStep in every "Async" test is a MockResponse TestStep which have appropriate 
		assertions defined. It is important for MockResponse to have properly set "Handle Response", "Handle Fault" and "Start Step" set to 
		previous TestRequest.</p>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/asyncTestCase_example.gif" alt="Async WSTF sc003 Project TestCase"/></p>
		<p>XML project file which can be used for project import can be found at
		<a href="projects/WSTF-SC003-Scenario-soapui-project.xml">http://www.soapui.org/wstf/projects/WSTF-SC003-Scenario-soapui-project.xml</a>.</p>
		</subsection>
		
		</section>
    </body>
</document>

