<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Managing Web Service Endpoints - soapUI</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
		<section name="Service Endpoints">

		 <p>
		 Selecting the Service Endpoints action from the interface context menu opens a dialog showing the 
		 available service endpoints for this interface and each endpoints default authentication settings.
		 If the interface was imported from a WSDL definition, that services
		 ports URL will be available in this list, and you are free to add, edit, or remove as many service endpoints as
		 you want. 
		 </p>
		 <p>
		 If your endpoints are already URL-encoded, you should select the "Preencoded Endpoints" option 
		 in the <a href="../preferences.html#HTTP_Settings">Http Settings</a> dialog to avoid that they get reencoded 
		 during requests. When deleting an endpoint, all requests that had that endpoint will have their 
		 endpoint set to null.
		 </p>
		 <p align="center">
			<img src="images/service_endpoints.gif" border="0" alt="The Service Endpoint editor"/>
		 </p>
		 <p>Specified authentication values will be used for all Requests/TestRequest that use the endpoint, unless
		 any of the values have been overridden at the request level.</p>
		 <p>The <b>Assign</b> options prompts to assign the selected endpoint to requests, the following options are 
		 displayed:</p>
		 <ul>
			 <li><code>- all requests -</code> : will assign the selected endpoint to all requests for operations in 
			 the current interface.</li>
			 <li><code>- all requests with no endpoint -</code> : will assign the selected endpoint to all requests
			  for operations in the current interface that have no endpoint.</li>
			 <li><code>&lt;endpoint&gt;</code> : will assign the selected endpoint to all requests
			  for operations in the current interface that have this endpoint.</li>
		 </ul>
		 <p>
		 Assigning endpoints with this option will <b>not</b> assign to TestRequests, use the "Set TestCase Endpoint"
		 action in the <a href="../functional/testcases.html#The_TestCase_Editor">TestCase Editor</a> for this instead.
		 </p>
		
		<p align="center"><img src="images/assign_endpoint.gif" border="0" alt="Assigning a Service Endpoint for Web Service Tests"/></p>
			
		 <p>
		 When closing the dialog with the "Ok" button, the available endpoints will be selectable in associated
		 operations request or test requests editor panes.
		 </p>
		  
		  <p><hr size="1"/>Next: <a href="interfaceeditor.html">WSDL Content Viewer</a></p>
		</section>
    </body>
</document>

