<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Web Service Overview- The Interface view</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
		<section name="Interface View Tab: Main View">
			<p>
				The interface view contains useful information and metrics about your project, such as where files are stored, WSDL Style Binding and more.
				This is intended as a very quick way of getting information and overview of the Interface.
			</p>
			<img src="images/interfaceview.gif" border="0" alt="Interfacce overview in soapUI"/>
			
			<p>
			Please note that the Use of the Operations is listed per operation and not with the style. 
			We usually  refer to them together (Document/Literal), but since it can change per operation, that where it has to be shown.
			</p>
            <subsection name="Service Endpoints">

		 <p>
		 Selecting the Service Endpoints action from the interface context menu opens a dialog showing the
		 available service endpoints for this interface and each endpoints default authentication settings.
		 If the interface was imported from a WSDL definition, that services
		 ports URL will be available in this list, and you are free to add, edit, or remove as many service endpoints as
		 you want.
		 </p>
		 <p>
		 If your endpoints are already URL-encoded, you should select the "Preencoded Endpoints" option
		 in the <a href="../preferences.html#HTTP_Settings">Http Settings</a> dialog to avoid that they get reencoded
		 during requests. When deleting an endpoint, all requests that had that endpoint will have their
		 endpoint set to null.
		 </p>
		 <p align="center">
			<img src="images/service_endpoints.gif" border="0" alt="The Service Endpoint editor"/>
		 </p>
		 <p>Specified authentication values will be used for all Requests/TestRequest that use the endpoint, unless
		 any of the values have been overridden at the request level.</p>
		 <p>The <b>Assign</b> options prompts to assign the selected endpoint to requests, the following options are
		 displayed:</p>
		 <ul>
			 <li><code>- all requests -</code> : will assign the selected endpoint to all requests for operations in
			 the current interface.</li>
			 <li><code>- all requests with no endpoint -</code> : will assign the selected endpoint to all requests
			  for operations in the current interface that have no endpoint.</li>
			 <li><code>&lt;endpoint&gt;</code> : will assign the selected endpoint to all requests
			  for operations in the current interface that have this endpoint.</li>
		 </ul>
		 <p>
		 Assigning endpoints with this option will <b>not</b> assign to TestRequests, use the "Set TestCase Endpoint"
		 action in the <a href="../functional/testcases.html#The_TestCase_Editor">TestCase Editor</a> for this instead.
		 </p>

		<p align="center"><img src="images/assign_endpoint.gif" border="0" alt="Assigning a Service Endpoint for Web Service Tests"/></p>

		 <p>
		 When closing the dialog with the "Ok" button, the available endpoints will be selectable in associated
		 operations request or test requests editor panes.
		 </p>

            </subsection>

<subsection name="WSDL Content Viewer">
		<p>The Interface viewer allows relatively easy navigation and inspection of the entire contract for an imported WSDL,
		including all imported and included WSDL and XSD files and their contained types, definitions, etc.</p>

		<p>The navigation tree to the left shows contained elements in the contract, selecting a node will
		highlight that element in its containing file to the right, automatically switching tabs if necessary.
		Elements referring to other elements in the contract are also double clickable and will focus to the
		referenced element in the tree as follows;</p>
		<table>
		<tr><th>Double-click on</th><th>will focus on (if available)</th></tr>
		<tr><td>Global Element</td><td>its Complex Type</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Message Part</td><td>its Complex Type or Global Element</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Operation input/output</td><td>its Message</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Binding Operation input/output</td><td>its corresponding Operation input/output</td></tr>
		<tr><td>Port</td><td>its Binding Operation</td></tr>
		</table>

		<p>The viewer toolbar has the following actions (left to right)</p>
		<ul>
		<li><b>Back</b> - navigates to the previously selected node</li>
		<li><b>Forward</b> - navigates to the next selected node (after navigating back..)</li>
		<li><b>Update Definition</b> - updates the WSDL contract as described under
		<a href="index.html#Updating_the_Interface_Definition">Updating the Interface Definition</a></li>
        <li><b>Generate Documentation</b> - Prompts to generate HTML documentation for this WSDL (uses
            <a href="http://tomi.vanek.sk/index.php?page=wsdl-viewer" target="_new">WSDL Viewer</a> by Tomi Vanek) which
            will be opened in an external browser.</li>
		<li><b>Export WSDL</b> - prompts to export the entire sadly and all importe and included files to a local folder. Import or Includes
		are replaced with valid relative ones.</li>
		</ul>

		<p>The following screenshot shows the viewer for the PayPal API;</p>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/interface_viewer.gif" alt="the WSDL Content Inspector"/></p>
	           </subsection>
		 <p><hr size="1"/>Next: <a href="wsi.html">WS-I Compliance</a></p>
		</section>
    </body>
</document>
