<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Web Service Compliance - WS-I Tools</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
		<section name="WS-I Compliance">
		<p>soapUI includes integrated support for the <a target="_new" href="http://www.ws-i.org">WS-I organizations</a> Basic Profile validation 
		tools for 2 situations:</p>
		<ol>
		<li><b>Validating WSDL definitions</b> - from the <a href="../index.html#Interface_Actions">Interface Menu</a> with the 
		"Check WSI Compliance" option. This will run the WS-I Test Tools and validate the WSDL definition accordingly.</li>
		<li><b>Validating SOAP request/response messages</b> - from within the Request Editors response popup with the 
		"Check WSI Compliance" option (as described under <a href="../requests.html#Message_Validation">Message Validation</a>)</li>
		</ol>
		<p>In either case, you first need to download either the java or C# version (soapUI will use whichever is available) of 
		the WS-I Interoperability Testing Tools 1.1 from the WS-I 
		<a href="http://www.ws-i.org/deliverables/workinggroup.aspx?wg=testingtools" target="_new">deliverables</a> page. 
		Once downloaded, unzip the file into a local directory and specify the contained "wsi test tools" directory
		in the soapUI together with the desired settings;</p>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/wsi_settings.gif" alt="WS-I Tool Setting"/></p>
		<subsection name="Creating WS-I Reports">
		<p>When running one of the integrated validations described above, the corresponding WS-I Analyzer configuration file 
		will be generated and the WS-I Analyzer will be invoked in a separate process; a progress dialog will be shown while 
		the tool is running. If all goes well, you will be presented with a WS-I Compliance Report in a separate desktop window, 
		otherwise an error will be displayed.</p>
		<p>A generated report looks as follows:</p>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/wsi_report.gif" alt="Interoperability Testing Report"/></p>
		<p>The top toolbar contains a button for exporting the report to an HTML file.</p>
		<p>Also, a "Config" tab is available for displaying the configuration file used to invoke the WS-I tools, for example:</p>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/wsi_config.gif" alt="WS-I Tool Configuration Tab"/></p>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="Displaying the WS-I Tool Output">
		<p>Selecting the "Show Log" option in the <a href="../preferences.html#WSI_Settings">WSI Settings Tab</a> 
		will display ongoing output from the command-line tools which can be useful for debugging purposes;</p>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/wsi_showlog.gif" alt="WS-I Test Log"/></p>
		  <p><hr size="1"/>Next: <a href="refactoring.html">Refactoring Web Service tests with WSDL Refactoring</a></p>
		</subsection>
		 
		</section>
    </body>
</document>