<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Web Service structure view - soapUI Pro outline editor</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
		<section name="soapUI Pro Outline Editor">
		<p>The soapUI Pro Outline Editor is available for all request and response messages and shows a tree view 
		of the current message content. The
		left column of the editor shows the tree structure and the center column shows editable node values.
		Grayed node-values are not editable due to unavailability or schema restrictions. 
		Node values in the center column are editable by selecting or editing as usual. The right column shows 
		the schema type for the corresponding node if available. This column can be hidden with the toggle button 
		in the toolbar.</p>
		
		   <table class="relatedInfo" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0">
                <tr class="a">
                    <td width="75" style="padding-top:5px">
                        <img src="../images/where_do_i_start.jpg" alt="Start soapUI Testing"
                             longdesc="http://www.soapui.org"></img>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                        <table class="relatedInner">
                            <tr>
                                <td>
                                    <span class="relatedInfoHeader">Did you know?</span>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td>
                                    <div>
                                    	<p>soapUI Pro allows you to view your requests as hierarchies. This gives you a structured view of your input, and makes your work easier and faster.</p>
                                        <p>The different editors in soapUI pro will improve your productivity and make Web Service Testing fun.</p>
            </div>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr align="right">
                                <td>
                                    <span class="relatedLinks">
                                        <a href="http://www.eviware.com/component/option,com_wrapper/Itemid,41/"
                                           title="try soapUI Pro"
                                           onclick="javascript:urchinTracker:('/downloadPro');">
                                            <img src="images/try_pro_100.png" alt="Try soapUI pro to soap test"
                                                 width="101" height="20" longdesc="http://www.eviware.com"/>
                                        </a>
                                    </span>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                        </table>
                    </td>
                </tr>
            </table>
		
		<p>If the underlying schema definition for a specific node
		has documentation annotations, these will be displayed in the tooltip as shown in the screen-shot below.</p>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/outline_editor.gif" alt="Structured View of Web Service messages in soapUI Pro"/></p>
		<p>The toolbar has the following actions (left to right):</p>
		<ul>
		<li>Collapses all child nodes if possible (ALT+SHIFT+C)</li>
		<li>Expands all child nodes if possible (ALT+SHIFT+E)</li>
		
		<li>Collapses all sibling nodes if possible (ALT+CTRL+C)</li>
		<li>Expands all sibling nodes if possible (ALT+CTRL+E)</li>
		
		<li>Moves down to the next sibling node, skipping any child nodes (ALT+DOWN)</li>
		<li>Moves up one sibling, skipping any intermediate child nodes (ALT+UP)</li>
		<li>Moves to the current nodes parent node (ALT+LEFT)</li>
		<li>Moves to and expands the current nodes first child node if available (ALT+RIGHT)</li>
		<li>Toggle Type-Column</li>
		<li>Help - displays this page</li>
		</ul>
		<p>The following additional keyboard commands are available when the Outline-Table has focus:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>DOWN - moves down one row and expands new row if possible</li>
		<li>UP - moves up one row</li>
		<li>ALT+C - collapses current node if possible (i.e. hides all child nodes)</li>
		<li>ALT+E - expands current node if possible (i.e. shows all child nodes)</li> 
		</ul>
		<p>A number of right-button actions are available
		for creation of XPath assertions and Property-Transfers/Expansion when editing 
		<a href="functional/mockresponse.html">Mock Response</a> and 
		<a href="functional/testrequests.html">Test Request</a> steps.</p>
		
		
		 <p><hr size="1"/>Next: <a href="messageinspectors.html">Message Inspectors</a></p>
		</section>
    </body>
</document>