<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>soapUI Userguide Overview</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
		<section name="soapUI Overview">
		 
		 <subsection name="Prerequisites">
		 <p>Although soapUI should be easy to get started with, you should have a good grasp of the following
		 concepts and technologies to get the most out of soapUI's functionality.</p>
		 <ul>
		 	<li><b>WSDL</b> - You should have a grasp of basic concepts like services, ports, bindings, port types, and the relation to XML Schema</li>
		 	<li><b>SOAP</b> - You should have a grasp of basic concepts and relation to WSDL (bindings, etc), different encoding types (soap encoded/literal) and 
		 	message styles (document/rpc)</li>
            <li><b>REST/HTTP</b> - Understand the concepts behind REST and HTTP-based services/resources.</li>
		 	<li><b>XML and related technologies</b> - Useful knowledge is XPath, XML Schema, namespaces, etc</li>
		 </ul>
		 <p>You can find most specifications at <a target="_new" href="http://www.w3.org">W3C</a> and tutorials
		 at several sites, for example <a target="_new" href="http://www.w3schools.com">W3Schools</a> and
		 <a target="_new" href="http://www.zvon.org/o_html/group_web_services.html">zvon.org</a>.</p>
		 </subsection>
		 
		 
		 				
				<table class="relatedInfo" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0">
	<tr class="a">
    	<td width="75" style="padding-top:5px">
        	<img src="../images/where_do_i_start.jpg" alt="Start soapUI Testing" longdesc="http://www.soapui.org"></img>
        </td>
        <td>
            <table class="relatedInner">
              <tr>
                <td>
                	<span class="relatedInfoHeader">Did you know?</span>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>
                    <div>
						<p>
						There is a commercial version of soapUI available; <b><i>soapUI Pro</i></b>.
						</p>
						<p>
						<b><i>soapUI Pro</i></b> contains productivity enhancements as well as offers Professional World Class support.
						</p>
                    </div>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr align="right">
              	<td>
                	<span class="relatedLinks"><a href="http://www.eviware.com/component/option,com_wrapper/Itemid,41/" title="try soapUI Pro" onclick="javascript:urchinTracker:('/downloadTrial');">
                                               <img src="../images/try_pro_100.png" alt="Try soapUI pro to soap test" width="101" height="20" longdesc="http://www.eviware.com"/></a></span>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </table>
		</td>
	</tr>
</table>
		 
		 



		
		 <subsection name="The soapUI Interface">
		 <p>soapUI is a standard desktop application adhering to established User Interface concepts for Integrated Development Environments, as available in for example
		 Eclipse, NetBeans and IDEA. Most actions have keyboard shortcuts and tooltips, you should have no problems finding 
		 your way around. soapUI makes heavy use of "Inspectors"; i.e. tabs that can be shown and hidden by selecting them.</p>

		 <p>The soapUI window is divided into the following views:</p>
		 <table><tr>
		 <td><i>left</i><br/>The main navigator showing a hierarchy of all projects, interfaces, etc. (see below)
		 <ul>
		 	<li> Selecting an item will show available overview information in the bottom left "Properties" panel</li>
		 	<li> Double clicking or pressing enter on a selected item will open the items' editor
		 	to the right if available</li>
		 </ul>
		 </td>
		 <td><i>right</i><br/>The soapUI desktop containing editors and viewers for those double clicked items in the navigator.
		 <ul>
		 <li>Cycle between active panes with Ctrl-Tab or use Ctrl-W to switch</li>
		 <li>Maximize, Minimize, Resize or Move as usual using each panes window menu</li>
		 <li>Focusing on a pane will automatically put focus on its item in the navigator, scrolling into view if necessary</li>
		 </ul>
		 </td></tr>
		 <tr><td><i>bottom-left</i>
		 <ul>
		 <li>The <b>Properties</b> panel will show information on the item currently selected in the navigator</li>
		 </ul>
		 </td><td><i>bottom right</i><br/>A color coded log view showing log messages from soapUI</td></tr></table>
		 <p align="center">
			<img src="images/soapui_overview.gif" border="0" alt="an overview of the Web Testing tool, soapUI"/>
		</p>
		<p>You can set a centered background image for the default desktop by placing a soapui-backgroung.gif/jpg/png file in the
		soapUI bin folder when using the default desktop</p>
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection name="The Navigator">
		 <p>
             The following objects are currently shown in the navigator tree:
		 
		 <ul>
		 	<li><b>Projects</b> node : the soapUI workspace
		 	<ul>
		 		<li><p><a href="projects/index.html">Project</a> node(s) : for each project in the workspace</p>
		 		<ul>
		 			<li><p><a href="interfaces/index.html">Interface</a>/<a href="rest/services/index.html">Service</a> node(s) : for each WSDL Interface or REST Service
                         in the project</p>
		 			<ul>
		 				<li><p><a href="interfaces/index.html#Operations">Operation</a>/<a href="rest/resources.html">Resource</a> node(s) : for each WSDL Operation
                             or REST Resource in the containting Interface/Service</p>
		 				<ul>
		 					<li><p><a href="requests.html">Request</a> node(s) : for each WSDL or REST Request created for the
                                 containing Operation or Resource</p></li>
                             <li><p><a href="rest/resources.html">REST Resource</a> node(s) : for each child REST Resource</p></li>
		 				</ul>
		 				</li>
		 			</ul>
		 			
		 			</li>
		 			<li><p><a href="functional/testsuites.html">TestSuite</a> node(s) : for each TestSuite in the project</p>
					<ul>
						<li><p><a href="functional/testcases.html">TestCase</a> node(s) : for each TestCase in the testsuite</p>
		    			<ul>
							<li><p><b>TestSteps</b> node, contains the TestCases'</p>
			    			<ul>
			    				<li><p><a href="functional/testcases.html#Test_Steps">TestStep</a> node(s) : for each TestCase-step, together with a colored
			    				icon indicating the status of that step.</p></li>
			    			</ul>
			    			</li>
							<li><p><b>LoadTests</b> node, contains the TestCases'</p>
			    			<ul>
			    				<li><p><a href="loadtest/index.html">LoadTest</a> node(s) : for each loadtest in the containing TestCase</p></li>
			    			</ul>
			    			</li>
		    			</ul>
						</li>
		 			</ul>
		 			</li>
		 			<li><p><a href="mock/services.html">MockService</a> node(s) : for each MockService in the project</p>
					<ul>
						<li><p><a href="mock/operations.html">MockOperation</a> node(s) : for each MockOperation in the MockService</p>
		    			<ul>
							<li><p><a href="mock/responses.html">MockResponse</a> node(s) : for each MockResponse in the containing MockOperation</p>
			    			</li>
		    			</ul>
						</li>
		 			</ul>
		 			</li>
		 		</ul>
		 		</li>
		 	</ul>
		 	</li>
		 </ul>
		 The tree can be navigated using the standard keyboard actions. An items' associated desktop panel can 
		 	be opened by double clicking it or selecting it and pressing Enter.
		</p>
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection name="Property Mode">
		 <columns><column>
		 <div>The Navigator described above contains a small toggle button on top of the tree. Pressing it will 
		 put the Navigator into <i>Property Mode</i>, displaying all <a href="properties.html">Properties</a> for their 
		 corresponding objects in the tree (green = read/write, black = read-only), giving an overview of all
		 defined or available properties within a project.</div>
		 <ul>
		 <li>Items containing custom properties (Projects, TestSuites, TestCases, MockServices and MockResponse) will
		 in the tree get a <i>Properties child node</i> contain that objects custom properties.</li>
		 <li> Double clicking a property prompts to set its value.</li>
		 <li> Right clicking the Properties node open a menu for adding new properties.</li>
		 </ul>
		 <p>One of the main Use cases for this mode is the possibility to drag a property from the tree into any
		 text editor that supports <a href="properties.html#Property_Expansion">Property Expansion</a>, making it
		 extremely easy to create property expansions as desired. If the property being dragged contains an XML value,
		 the <a href="xpath_selector.html">XPath Selector</a> will be displayed after a drop, allowing for further
		 property-expansion refinement</p>
		 </column><column><img src="images/property_mode.gif" alt="Working in property mode"/></column></columns>
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection name="Drag and Drop">
		 <p>soapUI provides extensive support for dragging and dropping items in the Navigator, resulting in corresponding Clone or Move 
		 operations, alternatively add or import actions, for example dragging a Request to a TestCase creates a TestRequest Step corresponding
		 to the dragged Request. It is also possible to drag and drop within or between the TestSuite and TestCase editors and the Navigator to 
		 rearrange, move, or copy items.</p>
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection name="Main Menu">
		 <p>Most actions in soapUI are performed through toolbar buttons or context sensitive right-button menus. 
		 The following actions are available from the main menu:</p>
		 <p>
				 <b>File Menu</b>
				 <p>The first 9 actions are the same as those for the Workspace popup menu, please go to the
				 <a href="workspaces.html">Workspaces</a> page for details. After these come the following actions:</p>
				 <ul>
				 	<li><b>Preferences</b> - Sets global <a href="preferences.html">soapUI Preferences</a></li>
				 	<li><b>Save Preferences</b> - Saves the current global settings</li>
				 	<li><b>Import Preferences</b> - Prompts to import global settings from another location (for example
				 	an old soapUI installation). After loading, soapUI may need to be restarted for all settings to be 
				 	activated</li>
				 	<li><b>Recent</b> - Contains submenus for recent editors, projects, or workspaces for easy switching</li>
				 	<li><b>Exit</b> - Prompts to exit soapUI</li>
				 	<li><b>Exit without saving</b> - prompts to exit soapUI without saving anything</li>
				 	<li><b>Online Help</b> - displays this page in an external browser</li>
				 </ul>
				</p>
		 
		 <p>

				 <b>Tools Menu</b>
				 <ul><li>Contains actions for invoking integrated tools as described in the
				 <a href="tools/index.html">Tool Integrations</a> section.</li></ul>

		  	 </p>
		 
		  <p>
		 <b>Desktop Menu</b> -
		 Shows actions related to the currently selected Desktop.
		 <ul>
		    <li><b>Switch Windows</b> - opens a <i>Switch Window</i> dialog for switching to another open editor</li>
		    <li><b>Maximize Desktop</b> - hides or shows the Navigator and Log-Inspectors</li>
			<li><b>Close Current</b> - closes the currently active desktop pane</li>
			<li><b>Close All</b> - closes all desktop panes</li>
			<li><b>Closes Others</b> - closes all desktop panes except the currently active one</li>		 
             <li><b>Open TestCase Layout (soapUI Pro Tabbed Desktop only)</b> - enabled if a TestCase is selected in the
             Navigator; will create a desktop with the TestCase to the left and all TestStep windows in a Tab Group to
             the right.</li>
		 </ul>
		 </p>
		 
		 <p>
		 <b>Help Menu</b> - general information and soapUI Pro specific actions
		 <ul>
             <li><b>Starter Page</b> - Opens the Starter Page which is by default shown when soapUI starts</li>
			<li><b>User Guide</b> - Opens the soapUI User Guide</li>
			<li><b>Getting Started</b> - Opens the soapUI Getting Started documents </li>
			<li><b>System Properties</b> - Opens a list of all currently defined system properties (see below)</li>
			<li><b>Update License</b> (soapUI Pro only) - see <a href="licensemanagement.html">License Management</a></li>
			<li><b>Show License Details</b> (soapUI Pro only) - see <a href="licensemanagement.html">License Management</a></li>
			<li><b>soapUI.org/eviware.com</b> - Opens http://www.soapui.org or http://www.eviware.com</li>		 
			<li><b>About soapUI</b> - Shows a version information dialog</li>
		 </ul>
		 </p>
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection name="System Properties">
		 <p>The System Properties option from the help menu opens a simple dialog showing all current defined system properties, 
		 which can be useful for debugging system or security settings, etc…</p>
		 <p align="center"><img src="images/systemproperties.gif" alt="System Properties in soapUI"/></p>
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection name="Log Tabs">
 
 		 <p>The bottom right of the soapUI workspace contains a number of log windows, each displaying 
 		 corresponding output;</p>
 		 <p align="center"><img src="images/log_tabs.gif" alt="the soapUI Logs Tab"/></p>
 		 <p>Right clicking on a log will show a popup menu with options to clear and enable or disable the 
		 log and to copy selected rows to the clipboard. Also, log-entries can be selected or copied to the clipboard for transfer to 
 		 external tools. An option to set the maximum number of rows is available (default is 1000), when exceeding this
 		 limit, old rows are removed from the log (i.e. fifo).</p>		 
		
		 <p>The following tabs are currently displayed (when needed):</p>
		 <ul>
		 <li><b>soapUI log</b> - general notifications and messages</li>
		 <li><b>http Log</b> - http wire log for sent http requests for viewing the actual
		 data sent and received on the socket (disabled during LoadTesting)</li>
		 <li><b>jetty log</b> - mock-service related status notifications from</li>
		 <li><b>groovy log</b> - log messages from groovy scripts using the available log object (disabled
		 during loadtest but can be enabled from File/Preferences/UI Settings)</li>
		 <li><b>error log</b> - log with diagnostic information for errors that arise during execution, this log
		 should be included in any bug-reports if it contains related error information. Please note that not
		 all errors logged have to be actual errors in soapUI, for example if a target server or service is not
		 available, a socket connection error will be shown here, which may well be due to "natural" causes.</li>
             <li><b>memory log</b> - shows an scrolling monitor over how much of the memory allocated to soapUI that
             is being used. Right-clicking open a menu with a "GC" option to trigger the Garbage Collector.</li>
		 </ul>

		 <p>soapUI uses <a target="_new" href="http://logging.apache.org/log4j/docs/index.html">log4j</a> for logging, 
		 you can customize the log4j configuration by putting a log4j xml configuration file named "soapui-log4j.xml" 
		 in the soapUI bin directory (or the current working directory when not running from there).</p>
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <p><hr size="1"/>Next: <a href="tabbeddesktop.html">soapUI Pro Tabbed Desktop</a></p>
		</section>
    </body>
</document>