<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Working with Web Service Requests</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
		<section name="Working with Requests">
		 
		 <p>An unlimited number of requests can be added to an operation in soapUI. Each request can have its
		 own message content, endpoint, encoding, etc. Requests are mainly managed through the request-editor displayed
		 when double clicking a request node in the navigator (described below)</p>
		 
		 
		 				
				<table class="relatedInfo" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0">
	<tr class="a">
    	<td width="75" style="padding-top:5px">
        	<img src="../images/where_do_i_start.jpg" alt="Start soapUI Testing" longdesc="http://www.soapui.org"></img>
        </td>
        <td>
            <table class="relatedInner">
              <tr>
                <td>
                	<span class="relatedInfoHeader">Did you know?</span>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>
                    <div>
						<p>
						In <b><i>soapUI Pro</i></b> you have two more request and response editors; The Form editor and the Outline Editor. 
Both will improve your productivity and make Web Service Testing more fun.

						</p>
						<p>
						<b><i>soapUI Pro</i></b> contains productivity enhancements as well as offers Professional World Class support.
						</p>
                    </div>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr align="right">
              	<td>
                	<span class="relatedLinks"><a href="http://www.eviware.com/component/option,com_wrapper/Itemid,41/" title="try soapUI Pro" onclick="javascript:urchinTracker:('/downloadTrial');">
                                               <img src="../images/try_pro_100.png" alt="Try soapUI pro to soap test" width="101" height="20" longdesc="http://www.eviware.com"/></a></span>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </table>
		</td>
	</tr>
</table>
		 
		 
		 

		 
		 <subsection name="Request Actions">
		 <p>
             The following actions are available from the request nodes' right-button menu:
		  <ul>
		  <li><b>Show Request Editor</b> - opens the Request Editor described below</li>
		  <li><b>Add to TestCase</b> - prompts to add the request to a TestCase. If no
		  TestCase is available, soapUI will prompt to create both a TestSuite or TestCase if 
		  required</li>
		   <li><b>Add to MockService</b> - prompts to add the requests' operation to a MockService. If a response is 
		   available for the request, it will be used as the default MockResponse.</li>
		    <li><b>Add as MockResponse Step </b> - prompts to create a <a href="functional/mockresponse.html">MockResponse Step</a>  
		  this request in an existing or new TestCase. If a response is available for the request, it will be used as the response content.</li>
		  <li><b>Copy to TestRequests (soapUI Pro only)</b> - opens dialog for copying/merging this request to existing
		  TestRequests (see below)</li>
		  <li><b>Clone Request</b> - prompts to clone this request, the cloned request will be added to the operation and 
		  its request-editor will be opened</li>
		  <li><b>Rename</b> - prompts to rename the request in the navigator</li>
		  <li><b>Delete</b> - prompts to remove the request from its operation</li>
		  <li><b>Online Help</b> - Displays this page in an external browser</li>
		  </ul>
		  </p>
		 </subsection>
		 
		  <subsection name="Request Details Tab">
			The "Details" tab shown in the bottom-left shows the following values when a Request node is selected in 
			the navigation tree
			<h4>General Properties</h4>
			<ul>
				 <li><b>Name</b> : the name of the request</li>
				 <li><b>Description</b> : an arbitrary description of the request, displayed as a tooltip over the 
				   requests node in the Navigator.</li>
				 <li><b>Message Size</b> : The number of characters in the current request message (including whitespace).</li>
				 <li><b>Encoding</b> : The encoding used by the request</li>
				 <li><b>Endpoint</b> : The endpoint for the request</li>
				 <li><b>Bind Address</b>  : The local IP Address to bind to when sending the request.</li>
				 <li><b>WS-Addressing</b>  : enables/disables ws-addressing.</li>
				 <li><b>Follow Redirects</b> : follows HTTP Redirect response messages </li>
				 <li><b>Skip SOAP Action : </b> : does not add SOAPAction header to request </li>
			</ul>
			<h4>Security/Authentication Properties</h4>
			(override any defaults set for the endpoint)
			<ul>
				 <li><b>Username</b> : The username to use if the request requires authentication</li>
				 <li><b>Password</b> : The password to use if the request requires authentication</li>
				 <li><b>Domain</b> : The domain to use if the request requires NTLM authentication)</li>
				 <li><b>WSS-Password Type</b> : Selects the type of WS-Security username/password token to dynamically add to each outgoing request. 
				 The above specified Username and Password values will be used for the corresponding header values</li>
				 <li><b>WSS-TimeToLive</b> : If set, automatically inserts a WSS TimeToLive token in any outgoing requests using 
				 the specified TimeToLive (in milliseconds)</li>
				 <li><b>SSL Keystore</b> : sets path to SSL keystore for request</li>
				 
			</ul>
			<h4>Attachment-Related Properties</h4>
			<ul>
				 <li><b>Enable MTOM/Inline</b> : Enable MTOM-based transfer and inlining of binary data in the 
				 request (see <a href="attachments.html">Attachments</a>).</li>
				 <li><b>Force MTOM</b> : Always use MTOM packaging for requests, even if there are no MTOM attachments.</li>
				 <li><b>Inline Response Attachments</b> : the entire HTTP response for a request (including
				  MIME/XOP attachments, etc..) will be shown in the response editor instead of attachments being parsed and
				  visible in the Response Attachments tab.</li>
				 <li><b>Expand MTOM Attachments</b> : received MTOM attachments will be inlined into the response
				  message editor, allowing correct viewing and validation of the actual message.</li>
				 <li><b>Disable Multipart</b> : Tells soapUI not to pack attachments with the same type into a multipart attachment, 
				  see <a href="attachments.html#Multipart_Attachments">Multipart Attachments</a> for more details.</li>
				 <li><b>Encode Attachments</b> : Tells soapUI to automatically encode attachments that have a corresponding WSDL part with 
				  the xsd-type set to either base6Binary or hexBinary.</li>
				 <li><b>Enable Inline Files</b> : enables/disables inline files , see <a href="attachments.html">Working with WS Attachments and Inline Files</a> </li>
				 <li><b>Entitize Properties</b> : entitize property-expansion values </li>
			</ul>
			<h4>Post-Processing Properties</h4>
			<ul>
				<li><b>Strip Whitespaces</b> : Strips outgoing requests of any unnecessary whitespaces and XML comments, required by some servers.</li>
				<li><b>Remove Empty Content</b> : Removes empty elements/attributes from outgoing requests. This can be useful in 
				Data Drive TestRequests which contain elements/attributes that not always contain data and should be removed in those cases.</li>
				<li><b>Prity Print</b> : enables more readable text format</li>
				<li><b>Dump File</b> : file where response will be stored</li>
				<li><b>Max Size</b> : maximum numbers of bytes to receive</li>
			</ul>
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection name="The Request Editor">
		 <p>The request editor is opened by either double-clicking a request in the navigator or by selecting 
		 its <b>Open Request Editor</b> popup menu item, and displays the current request and response messages together
		 with a toolbar and a number of detail tabs as shown below in a configurable <a href="#Editor_Layouts">Editor Layout</a>.</p>
		 <p align="center"><img src="images/request_editor.gif" alt="The soapUI Request editor"/></p>
		 <columns><column><div>
		 Vertically on the left side of each editor are tabs for each editor view. The 'XML' source view is always available, as is the 'Raw' source view.
		 soapUI Pro also adds the following addition views:</div>
		 <ul>
		 <li>An <a href="outlineeditor.html">Outline Editor</a> for both request and response messages.</li>
		 <li>A <a href="formeditor.html">Form Editor</a> for easier editing of request messages.</li>
		 <li>An <a href="overviewview.html">Overview View</a> for easier inspection of response messages.</li>
		 </ul>
		 <p>The following inspectors are available at the bottom of each message editor;</p>
		 <ul>
		 <li>HTTP Headers : shows the request/response <a href="#HTTP_Headers">HTTP Header editor/viewer</a></li>
		 <li>Attachments : show the associated request/response <a href="attachments.html">Attachments</a> editor</li>
		 <li>SSL Info (Response only) : shows detailed response <a href="#SSL_Details">SSL Details</a> for the 
		 current response</li>
		 <li>WS-A : shows <a href="#WS-A_Inspector">WS-Addressing header properties</a></li>
		 </ul>
		 <p>In soapUI Pro, the bottom right corner (under the scrollbar) contains a button to show a panorama view of
		 the current editor view, allowing easier navigation around large/complex messages/views (available in all editor views, 
		 see screenshot to the right)</p>
		 </column><column><img src="images/panorama_popup.gif" alt="Using the soapUI Panorama functionality"/></column></columns>
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection name="Editor Toolbar">
		 <p align="center"><img src="images/request_toolbar.gif" border="0" alt="The soapUI editor toolbar"/></p>
		 <p>The request-editor toolbar has the following actions (from left to right)</p>
		 <ul>
		 	<li><b>Submit</b> - submits the request to the specified endpoint</li>
		 	<li><b>Add to TestCase</b> - prompts to add the request to a TestCase, same as the request-menu action 
		 	described above</li>
		 	 <li><b>Add as MockResponse Step</b> (soapUI Pro only) - prompts to create a <a href="functional/mockresponse.html">MockResponse Step</a>  
		     this request in an existing or new TestCase as described above.</li>
		 	<li><b>Add to MockService</b> - prompts to add the requests operation to a MockService, same as the request-menu action 
		 	described above</li>
		 	<li><b>Recreate Request</b> - prompts to recreate the request xml from the operations input message definition. Also
		 	prompts if any values in the current request should be kept in the recreated request</li>
		 	<li><b>Create Empty</b> - prompts to create an empty soap-request with no soap-body</li>
		 	<li><b>Clone Request</b> - prompts to clone the request, same as the request-action described above. 
				 You will be prompted for a name for the new request and the new request will be placed after 
				 the cloned request.</li>
		 	<li><b>Cancel Request</b> - cancels an ongoing request (disabled if no request is running)</li>
		 	<li><b>Endpoint Combo</b> - a combo-box listing the endpoints available for this requests operations' interface. The
		 	combo box also contains the following options (as shown in the image):
		 	<ul>
		 		<li> <code>[edit current...]</code> option for changing the current new endpoint directly</li>
		 		<li> <code>[add new endpoint...]</code> option for adding a new endpoint directly</li>
		 		<li> <code>[delete current...]</code> option for deleting the current endpoint directly</li>
		 	</ul>
		 	
		 	</li>
		 	
		 	<li><b>Tab Layout</b> - toggles between the tab and split request editor layouts as described below</li>
		 	<li><b>Editor Orientation</b> - changes the orientation of the request/response editors between left/right and top/bottom</li>
		 	<li><b>Online Help</b> - Displays this page in an external browser</li>
		 </ul>
		 
		 </subsection>
		 <subsection name="Editor Layouts">
		 <p>The editor is available in 2 layout modes which can be toggled with the "Tab Layout" toolbar button (top right):</p>
		 <ul>
		 <li><b>Split Layout</b> (default, shown above) - the editor is divided into a left request-area and a right 
		 response-area; submitting the requests posts it to its endpoint and displays the result in the right area.
		 When moving focus to one of the editors, the dividing split pane will automatically be moved to give the 
		 focused editor a larger visible area, diminishing the requirement to resize the split pane manually when working
		 with request/response messages. This behavior will be disabled when manually dragging the split-pane to 
		 a desired position and re-enabled when changing the split pane orientation or when closing/re-opening the 
		 request-editor for the current request. It can also be turned off completely using the designated option in the
		 <a href="preferences.html#UI_Settings">UI Settings</a></li>
		 <columns><column><div><li><b>Tabbed Layout</b> - the editor displays the request or response areas in separate tabs available at 
		 the top of the editor window. Submitting a request automatically selects the response tab after the response
		 has been received.</li></div></column><column><img src="images/tab_layout.gif" alt="Tabbed layout in soapUI Pro"/></column></columns>
		 </ul>
		</subsection>
		
				 
		 <subsection name="Aut">
		 	<p>
		 	One important part of the Request editor is the Aut Inspector at the bottom of each message editor.
		 	</p>
		 	<p>
		 	This will let us use the WS-Security setting set in the WS-Security Tab in the Project viewer.</p>
		 	<p align="center"><img src="images/aut.gif" alt="Aut Headers in soapUI"/></p>
		 </subsection>
		
		<subsection name="HTTP Headers">
		<p>The HTTP Headers Inspector at the bottom of each message editor displays the configured/received HTTP headers for the 
		corresponding request/response message. For request message headers, buttons for adding/removing HTTP headers to be sent
		with the request are available from a toolbar below the table.</p>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/http_headers.gif" alt="HTTP Headers in soapUI"/></p>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="SSL Details">
		<p>The SSL Details inspector at the bottom of the response editor displays a list of certificates that were involved in 
		negotiating the current message exchange, the following screenshot shows this information for a default request to the
		PayPal API.</p>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/ssl_details.gif" alt="SSL Details in soapUI"/></p>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="WS-A Properties">
		<p>The WS-A Inspector displays properties used for adding WS-A headers to a Request/MockResponse 
		according to <a href="http://www.w3.org/Submission/ws-addressing/#_Toc77464322" target="_new">WS Addressing specification</a></p>
            <ul>
		<li>Enable WS-A Addressing</li>
		<li>Must understand indicates whether a header entry is mandatory or optional for the recipient to process.</li>
		<li>WS-A Version indicates ws addressing version to be used.</li>
		<li>Add default WS-A:Action indicates if by default generated action is to be added to request/mock response.</li>
		<li>Action - specifies the value of the Action property. If not specified, and 'Add default WS-A:Action is checked' , 
		default action from WSDL will be generated and added. Although Action property is mandatory by <a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/ws-addr-core/#msgaddrpropsinfoset" target="_new">WS-A core specification</a> 
		by checking previous check box and leaving this empty it is possible for action property to be left unspecified for testing purposes. </li>
		<li>Add default WS-A:To indicates if default To is to be added to request/mock response.</li>
		<li>To - OPTIONAL element specifies the value of the To property</li>
		<li>ReplyTo - OPTIONAL element specifies the value of the ReplyTo property. If not specified, and Anonymous property 
		is set to 'required', either on <a href="interfaces/index.html#Interface_Details_Tab">Interface</a> or 
		<a href="operations.html#Operation_Details_Tab">Operation</a> level , default value of 
		'http://www.w3.org/2005/08/addressing/anonymous' will be used (Operation level definition has priority if not 'optional').</li>
		<li>ReplyTo Reference Parameters - expected to be added in XML not text form and will be included in request exactly as specified</li>
		<li>Generate MessageID - indicates if messageId should be randomly generated</li>
		<li>MessageID - OPTIONAL element specifies the value of the MessageID property. If not specified, and previous check box is 
		checked , random MessageID will be generated for RequestResponse operation.</li>
		<li>From - OPTIONAL element specifies the value of the From property</li>
		<li>FaultTo - OPTIONAL element specifies the value of the FaultTo property</li>
		<li>FaultTo Reference Parameters - expected to be added in XML not text form and will be included in request exactly as specified</li>
		<li>RelatesTo- OPTIONAL element specifies the value of the RelatesTo property</li>
		<li>RelationshipType- OPTIONAL element specifies the value of the RelationshipType property</li>
         </ul>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/wsa_inspector.gif" alt="Viewing header properties in WS-A Inspector"/></p>
            <p>(note that all settings support property-expansion)</p>
		</subsection>

		<subsection name="XML Source Editor">	
		  <columns><column><div>
		  The request and response XML editors support syntax highlighting, undo or redo, copy and paste, etc. soapUI Pro also adds a
		  number of additional editor views to the default "XML"; <a href="outlineeditor.html">"Outline"</a> and 
		  <a href="formeditor.html">"Form"</a>, together with a number of <a href="messageinspectors.html">Message Inspectors</a>
		  shown below the request and response message
		  The following actions are available from the request and response editor right-button menus:	
		  <ul>
		  <li><b>Validate</b> - validates the editors' content against its message definition as described below</li>
		  <li><b>Format XML</b> - pretty-prints the xml in the editor</li>
		  <li><b>Add WSS-Username Token</b> - prompts to add a WSS-Username SOAP-Header to the request message using the 
		  username/password specified in the Request Details Tab</li>
		  <li><b>Add WS-Timestamp</b> - prompts to add a WS-Timestamp SOAP-Header to the request message</li>
		  <li><b>Outgoing WSS</b> - enabled only when there are <a href="projects\wss.html#Outgoing_WSS">Outgoing WSS Configurations</a> added
		  and applies or removes outgoing wss from request.</li>
		  <li><b>WS-A Headers</b> - enabled only when <a href="#WS-A_Inspector">WS Addressing is enabled</a> for the request and 
		  removes or adds WS-A Headers from the request as configured in the inspector</li>
		  <li><b>Undo/Redo/Copy/Cut/Paste/Find/Replace</b> - standard editing functions</li>
		  <li><b>Go To Line</b> - prompts for a line to move to</li>
		  <li><b>Show Line Numbers</b> - toggles line-number visibility</li>
		  <li><b>Save as</b> - prompts to save the editors content to a local file</li>
		  <li><b>Load from</b> - prompts to load the editors content to a local file</li>
		  <li><b>Get data..</b> - a soapUI Pro specific popup that allows you to select a property accessible from the
          request for generating the corresponding property-expansion at the current caret-position.</li>
		  </ul>
		  Also, a number of custom keyboard actions are available to make your "everyday-soapui-editing" easier:
		 <ul>
		 <li>Alt-Enter : submits the request to the specified endpoint</li>
		 <li>Alt-X : cancels a running submit</li>
		 <li>Alt-left/right arrow : moves between element values</li>
		 <li>Shift-Tab : moves focus between request/response areas</li>
		 </ul>
		 </div>
		 </column></columns>
		 </subsection>

		 
		 <subsection name="Submitting requests">
		 <p>When submitting a request using either the submit toolbar button or the Alt-Enter editor action, 
		 the request message is sent to the selected endpoint using the specified encoding and local Bind Address. 
		 Submittal is done in a background thread so any number of requests can be running simultaneously
		 (an animated icon in the navigator shows that they are running).</p>
		
		 <p>During submittal, the request/response editors are made read-only and all actions except the cancel button in the
		 toolbar are disabled. One can cancel an ongoing request either by the "Cancel" toolbar button or by pressing Alt-X in 
		 one of the editors. If you choose to close the editor window while a request is running, you will be prompted if you first
		 want to cancel the ongoing request. Depending on the state of the request, its thread may actually continue in the 
		 background even though soapUI shows it as canceled, but from a usability point-of-view, you should never notice.</p>
		 
		 <p>Once a response has been received, it will be displayed in the response area and a log message will be displayed 
		 in the soapUI log view and the request editors status bar showing the time taken and size of the received response.
		 If you choose to close the request editor without canceling an ongoing request, the response will be shown
		 in the response area when the request editor is made visible again.</p>
		 <p>A HTTP Proxy can either be set by using the <code>http.proxyHost</code> and <code>http.proxyPort</code>
		 system properties or through the soapUI <a href="preferences.html#Proxy_Settings">Proxy Preferences</a> dialog. 
		 If both are available, the system properties take precedence.</p>
		 </subsection>

		 <subsection name="Authentication">
		  <p>If the service requires authentication, soapUI will attempt to authenticate using the
		 specified username, password, or domain values specified either at the endpoint level via the 
		 <a href="interfaces/endpoints.html#Service_Endpoints">Service Endpoints</a> or those specified in the Request Details 
		 Tab (or a combination of both). Currently supported authentication 
		 types are those supported by HttpClient, i.e. Basic, Digest and NTLM authentication. SSL should work (=not tested!) 
		 if you use <code>https</code> urls and <a target="_new" href="http://java.sun.com/products/jsse/doc/guide/API_users_guide.html#Installation">install JSSE</a> 
		 accordingly.</p>
		 <p>If one of the WSS-Password Type options or the WSS-TimeToLive has been set in the Request Details Tab, soapUI will 
		 automatically add the corresponding WS-Security headers to the outgoing message, as can be seen in the 
		 HTTP log;</p>
		 <p align="center"><img src="images/wss_password.gif" alt="Viewing WS-Security headers in the HTTP log"/></p>
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection name="Message Validation">
		  <columns><column><div>
		  When pressing Alt-V in the request or the response area, the contained message is validated against the 
		  operations message definition;
		  <ol>
		  <li>The message body is validated against its schema definition</li>
		  <li>The SOAP envelope and structure is validated in accordance with the WSDL and SOAP schemas</li>
		  <li>If the message sends MIME attachments, their presence is validated in the 
		  <a href="attachments.html#The_Attachments_Tab">Attachments Tab</a></li>
		  </ol>
		  <p>Validation errors are shown in a list-box displayed under the editor. Double clicking
		  an error will move the corresponding editor caret to the line of the error (if possible).</p>
		  <p>If the message is valid the error list is hidden and an Ok-message is displayed.</p>
		  <p>Validation is currently only supported for literal-encoded messages (both rpc and document), 
		  SOAP-encoded messages are <i>not</i> supported.</p></div>
		  </column><column>
		  <img src="images/request_validation.gif" alt="Logs from Message Validation"/>
		  </column></columns>
		  
		 <columns><column><div>
		 The response message editor has a similar popup menu to the request-editor containing a "Check WS-I Compliance" 
		 option. Selecting this option (if the WS-I validation tools have been configured correctly) will validate 
		 the current request or response message as configured and display a WS-I Compliance report in a separate window as described under 
		 <a href="interfaces/wsi.html">WS-I Integrations</a>.
		 </div></column></columns>
		  
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection name="Copy Requests">
		 <p>soapUI Pro includes this action to simplify bulk updates of TestRequests with new content. The displayed
		 dialog is as follows:</p>
		 <p align="center"><img src="images/copy_request_to_testrequests.gif" alt="Copying Test Requests"/></p>
		 <p>The options are:</p>
		 <ul>
		 <li><b>Mode</b> - the copy mode, see below</li>
		 <li><b>TestRequests</b> - the TestRequests to copy or merge to</li>
		 <li><b>Create Backups</b> - creates disabled backup TestRequest steps with existing request content</li>
		 <li><b>Open Requests</b> - opens a list of modified TestRequests for manual post processing</li>
		 </ul>
		 <p>When selecting ok, the existing request will be copied or merged as configured:</p>
		 <ul>
		 <li><b>Copy</b> : Overwrites the target TestRequest(s)</li>
		 <li><b>Update</b> : Merges values from the source Request into the target TestRequest without overwriting</li>
		 <li><b>Keep Existing</b> : Overwrites the target TestRequest after merging existing TestRequest values into 
		 the source Request</li>
		 </ul>
		 <p>Please note that the merging currently requires empty elements to merge into, it will not merge at the 
		 element level, only at the value level</p>
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <p><hr size="1"/>Next: <a href="formeditor.html">Form Editor</a></p>
		</section>
    </body>
</document>

