<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>USing soapUI workspaces</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
		<section name="Workspaces">
		 
		 <p>In soapUI a Workspace is a collection of Projects, just like in, for example, eclipse:</p>
		 <ul>
		 <li>Default workspace information is maintained in the <code>${user.home}/default-soapui-workspace.xml</code> file.
		 Switch workspaces using the New or Switch Workspace actions described below, if switching to another workspace, soapUI 
		 will remember this until the next session and use that workspace instead.</li>
		 <li>Any number of projects can be added to the workspace</li>
		 <li>Any number of workspaces can be created</li>
		 </ul>
		  <columns><column><div>At startup soapUI loads all project files contained in the last used workspace and
		  opens them if they were not previously closed (see below). If a project file is for some reason not available 
		  it will be grayed out and displayed as disabled, with right-click options to either remove it from the 
		 workspace or reload it (optionally from a new location).</div>
		 <p>Projects can be imported and created and removed from the workspace using the Menu Choices on the Workspace or in the Project popup menus.</p></column>
		 </columns>		 
		 <p>When exiting, soapUI will automatically save all project files in the workspace, except for those that 
		 still have running tests. A prompt will ask to ignore these or abort the exit. If soapUI detects that
		 a project file has been modified externally since it was last loaded, based on modification date, it will
		 first prompt if to overwrite the file or leave it as it is.</p>
		 
		 <subsection name="Open or Close Projects">
		 <p>Projects can be closed/opened as desired using corresponding popup-menu actions; closed projects are displayed with 
		 a grey icon and can easily be opened by either double-clicking them or using the corresponding right-button menu option.
		 Closed projects are not read into memory which will greatly improve startup time and memory consumption and  
		 A projects open or close state is remembered in the workspace when restarting or switching workspaces and a global UI Setting 
		 is available (see <a href="preferences.html#UI_Settings">Preferences</a>) for always closing all projects when loading 
		 a new workspace.</p>
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection name="soapUI Workspace Actions">
		 
		<p>
            The following actions are available from the workspace nodes right-button
		 menu (and from the main "File" menu):
		 <ul>
		 <li><b>New SoapUI Project</b> : Prompts to create a new <a href="projects/index.html">SoapUI Project</a>.</li>
		 <li><b>Import Project</b> : Prompts for a filename for an existing soapUI project. The project will be added to
		 the current workspace. If the project-file is read only it can still be added but no changes will be saved and 
		 a warning will be shown in the soapUI log.</li>
		 <li><b>Import Remote Project</b> : Prompts for a URL to an existing remote soapUI project. The project will be added to
		 the current workspace in read only mode (read more on <a href="projects/index.html#Remote_Test_Projects">Remote Projects</a>).</li>
		 <li><b>Save All Projects</b> - Saves all projects</li>
		 <li><b>Open All Closed Projects</b> - Opens all closed projects.</li>
		 <li><b>Close All Open Projects</b> - Prompts to close all opened projects.</li>
		 <li><b>Rename</b> - Renames the Workspace, the name is shown as the label for the root node in the Navigator</li>
		 <li><b>New Workspace</b> - Prompts to create a new empty workspace.</li>
		 <li><b>Switch Workspace</b> - Prompts for an existing workspace file to switch to (all current projects will 
		 be saved before making the actual switch).</li>
		 <li><b>Online Help</b> - Displays this page in an external browser</li>
		 </ul></p>
		</subsection>
		<subsection name="soapUI Workspace Details Tab">
		  <p>
              The "Details" tab shown in the bottom left shows the following values when the workspace node is selected in
		 the navigation tree
		 <ul>
		 <li><b>Name</b> : the name of the current workspace</li>
	     <li><b>Description</b> : an arbitrary description of the current workspace, displayed as a tooltip over the 
		   workspace node in the Navigator.</li>
		 <li><b>File</b> (read-only): the current workspace file used</li>
          <li><b>Project Root</b> : the root folder to user for projects</li>
		 </ul>
		 </p>
	    
		 </subsection>
		 <p><hr size="1"/>Next: <a href="projects/index.html">Web Service Test Projects</a></p>
		</section>
    </body>
</document>

