<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
	<properties>
		<title>userguide - soapUI Pro Reporting</title>
	</properties>
	<body>
		<section name="Reporting in soapUI Pro">
			<p>soapUI Pro 3.0 introduces extensive reporting functionality:
				creating reports on different levels (project, testsuite, testcase,
				etc), different formats( pdf, cvs, xls, xml, etc), easy
				customization and more. Creating reports can be, also, done from pro
				command line runners and from maven pro plugin and that way automate
				testing web service and creating various reports for better testing
				documentation, testing analytics, etc. </p>
			<p>
			<p>The reporting functionality provides three basic types of reports:</p>
			<ol>
			<li><a href="jasperreports.html">Printable Reports</a> - based on JasperReports, with full customization possibilities both on 
			the global and project level allows you to basically create any kind of report you would like. Generated
			reports can be printed or saved as PDF, HTML, Word, RTF, etc.</li>
			<li><a href="dataexports.html">Data Export</a> - allows for export of underlying report-data in XML and csv format. This is usefull if you 
			want to import report-data into other tools for custom reporting/integrations.</li>
			<li><a href="junit.html">JUnit-Style HTML Reports</a> - as were available in previous versions of soapUI Pro, give a simplified 
			overview of functional test results</li>
			</ol>
			<p>Both the Printable and Data Export Reports allow export of custom data via the new SubReport DataSink, which
			allows one to include any desired data in generated reports.</p>
			<subsection name="Report Creation">
			<p>All of the above are available via the Create Report button available in Project, TestSuite, TestCase and LoadTest
			window toolbars. The button will open a dialog which shows available reports in a drop-down, selecting a report shows 
			further configuration options if applicable;</p>
			<p align="center"><img src="images/create-report-action.png"/></p>
			<p>Here the three default TestSuite-level reports are seen, selecting one and pressing the OK button will generate
			and display the corresponding report as described in the following pages.</p>
			</subsection>
				<hr size="1" />
				Next:
				<a href="jasperreports.html">Main Reports</a>
			</p>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>