<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>WS-ReliableMessaging Tutorial</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
		<section name="Testing WS-RelibleMessaging Services Using SoapUI">
		<p>For the purposes of this tutorial, we will be using Axis2 v1.5 and Sandesha2 v1.3, although the steps should remain the same for other versions.</p>
		<p>In order to get the Axis2 server set up with Sandesha2 for testing, you will need to perform the following steps.</p>
		<ol>
            <li>Download <a href="http://ws.apache.org/axis2/">Axis2</a> and <a href="http://ws.apache.org/sandesha/sandesha2/index.html">Sandesha2</a>  from the Apache site. </li>
            <li>Unzip Axis2 to the directory of your choice. The directory will be reffered to as AXIS2_HOME from here on. You will also need to create an environment variable with the same name and set it to the directory.</li> 
            <li>Unzip the Sandesha2 file</li>
            <li><p>Read through the Sandesha2 <a href="http://ws.apache.org/sandesha/sandesha2/userGuide.html#install">install instructions</a></p>
            	<ol>
            		<li>You will need to copy all the jar files to the lib folder</li>
            		<li>The phases already include the RMPhase entries in Axis2.xml in the 1.5 version, although you might need to add them if you are using another version</li>
            		<li>c.	For the purposes of this tutorial, there is no need to build the war file, just copy the files to the correct places</li>
            	</ol>
            </li>
            <li>You will find the RMSampleService in the folder you unzipped the Sandesha2 files to under samples/services. Simply copy the RMSampleService.aar file to the repository/modules directory in AXIS2_HOME</li>
            <li>Start the server by running axis2server.bat or axis2server.sh in the AXIS2_HOME/bin directory</li>
        </ol>
        <p>Now that you have set up the Axis2/Sandesha2 combination, you are ready to connect to it using SoapUI</p>
        <ol>
            <li>If you have not changed any of the settings, the wsdl for the service should be at http://localhost:8080/axis2/services/RMSampleService?wsdl. Create a new project in SoapUI using this WSDL.</li>
            <li><p>Go to the RMSampleServiceSoap11Binding, we will be using the echoString operation for the rest of this tutorial. There will be a request (Request 1), that was already created with the project. 
            You will need to replace the contents of the request with the following (the wsdl does not seem to reflect the structure that the RMSampleService really expects):</p>
            <pre>
&lt;soapenv:Envelope xmlns:soapenv="http://schemas.xmlsoap.org/soap/envelope/" xmlns:user="http://userguide.samples.sandesha2"&gt;
	&lt;soapenv:Header/&gt;
	&lt;soapenv:Body&gt;
		&lt;user:echoString xmlns:temp="http://tempuri.org/"&gt;
	        &lt;temp:Text>Hello World!&lt;/temp:Text&gt;
			&lt;temp:Sequence>sequence&lt;/temp:Sequence&gt;
	    &lt;/user:echoString&gt;
	&lt;/soapenv:Body&gt;
&lt;/soapenv:Envelope&gt;
            </pre></li>
            <li><p>In the request properties on the lower left, set the Skip SOAP action property to true.</p>
            <p align="center"><img src="images/Request.jpg" alt="The Request properties"/></p></li>
            <li><p>Enable WSA under the WSA tab, disable the Add Default WSA action checkbox, and set the action name to echoString. Either turn on Randomly Generate MessageID, or enter a MessageID in the box below.</p>
            <p align="center"><img src="images/WSA.jpg" alt="The WSA Properties tab"/></p></li>
            <li><p>In the WS-ReliableMessaging Tab, activate reliable messaging, and set it to use version 1.1 in the dropdown below.</p>
            <p align="center"><img src="images/WS-RM_tab.jpg" alt="The WSRM Properties tab"/></p></li>
            <li>You can now run the request, which will execute the request as a sequence</li>
		</ol>
		<p>You can see the WSRM feedback in the WSRM log</p>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/WS-RM_log.jpg" alt="The WSRM Log"/></p>
		<p><hr size="1"/>Next: <a href="../tools/index.html">Web Service Code Tool Integrations</a></p>
		</section>
    </body>
</document>

