<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Data Driven Web Service Testing - DataSinks</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
		<section name="soapUI Pro DataSink Step">
		<p>Often you want save the data when doing Web Service testing. This can be in to take a response and 
		use it in later Requests, save info for logging purposes or even to actually populate a business database.</p>
		
		<p>This can be done in soapUI by writing a Groovy script, but is simplified in soapUI Pro.</p>
		
			<table class="relatedInfo" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0">
                <tr class="a">
                    <td width="75" style="padding-top:5px">
                        <img src="../../images/where_do_i_start.jpg" alt="Start soapUI Testing"
                             longdesc="http://www.soapui.org"></img>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                        <table class="relatedInner">
                            <tr>
                                <td>
                                    <span class="relatedInfoHeader">Did you know?</span>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td>
                                    <div>
                                         <p>soapUI Pro has functionality for saving data from your tests easily - for example to data bases or Excel- easily.</p>
                                        <p>The Data Source Steps soapUI pro will improve your productivity and make Web Service Testing fun.</p>
                                     </div>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr align="right">
                                <td>
                                    <span class="relatedLinks">
                                        <a href="http://www.eviware.com/component/option,com_wrapper/Itemid,41/"
                                           title="try soapUI Pro"
                                           onclick="javascript:urchinTracker:('/downloadPro');">
                                            <img src="images/try_pro_100.png" alt="Try soapUI pro to soap test"
                                                 width="101" height="20" longdesc="http://www.eviware.com"/>
                                        </a>
                                    </span>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                        </table>
                    </td>
                </tr>
           </table>
	
		<p>soapUI Pro includes a specialized DataSink TestStep that greatly eases the task of saving of data collected during 
		a test to an external storage. The following DataSink types are supported:</p>
		<ul>
		<li><a href="#soapUI_Pro_JDBC_DataSink">JDBC DataSink</a> - writes data to a JDBC datasource</li>
		<li><a href="#soapUI_Pro_Excel_DataSink">Excel DataSink</a> - writes data to an Excel (xls) file</li>
		<li><a href="#soapUI_Pro_File_DataSink">File DataSink</a> - writes data to a columnar data file</li>
		<li><a href="#soapUI_Pro_Groovy_DataSink">Groovy DataSink</a> - calls a Groovy Script for each set of data</li>
        <li><a href="#soapUI_Pro_Property_DataSink">Property DataSink</a> - aggregates values to a property</li>
		</ul>
		
		<subsection name="The soapUI Pro DataSink Editor">
		<p>The DataSink editor is divided into 4 parts;</p>
		<ul>
		<li>A list of properties to the left containing the values to be saved.</li>
		<li>A toolbar to the top right for selecting a DataSink and setting properties and options</li>
		<li>A DataSink specific configuration panel to the right</li>
		<li>A Data Log inspector at the bottom for displaying rows processed by the DataSink</li>
		</ul>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/datasink_editor.gif" alt="The soapUI Pro DataSink Editor"/></p>
		<p>The list of Properties should contain those properties that will be passed to the configured Datasink, they 
		are added/removed using the Add/Remove toolbar buttons. The DataSink dropdown selects the DataSink to use</p>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="soapUI Pro DataSink Options" >
		<p>The DataSink Options dialog is as follows:</p>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/datasink_options.gif" alt="The soapUI Pro DataSink Editor Options"/></p>
		<p>The following settings are available:</p>
		<ul>
		<li><b>Shared</b> - controls whether this DataSink should be shared between threads in a LoadTest (see below)</li>
		</ul>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="soapUI Pro DataSink Execution">
		<p>Every time the TestCase execution flow passes the DataSink Step it will call the configured DataSink with
		the current property values. Values should have been previously set by either a Groovy script or a property transfer,
		or can alternatively contain a PropertyExpansion syntax.</p>
		<p>It is possible to drag properties from the Navigator tree into the Properties table to either add new a new 
		property containing a PropertyExpansion for the dragged property, or if dragged onto an existing propertys' value; 
		to create a PropertyExpansion there instead.</p>
		<p>The "Shared" option in the toolbar controls if the DataSink should be shared between threads during a LoadTest, 
		meaning	that all running threads will write (synchronized) to the same DataSink instead of each creating their own.</p>
		</subsection>

		<subsection name="soapUI Pro JDBC DataSink">
		<p>The JDBC DataSink has the following configuration panel:</p>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/jdbc_datasink_config_panel.gif" alt="The soapUI Pro JDBC DataSink configuration panel"/></p>
		<p>The 4 available options are pretty straight forward:</p>
		<ul>
		<li><b>Driver</b> - the JDBC Driver to load and use for this DataSink. Must be available in the soapUI classpath 
		either by placing it in a soapui/bin/ext directory, the jre/lib/ext directory or by directly modifying the 
		soapui.bat/.sh files to include the required jar files</li>
		<li><b>Connection String</b> - the connection string to use</li>
		<li><b>SQL Update</b> - the update statement to issue for the created connection, using Prepared Statement syntax 
		(ie ? is used as value placeholder).</li> 
		<li><b>Stored Procedure</b> - select if the SQL statement calls a stored procedure</li>
		</ul>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="soapUI Pro Excel DataSink">
		<p>The Excel DataSink has the following configuration panel:</p>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/excel_datasink.gif" alt="The soapUI Pro Excel DataSink configuration panel"/></p>
		<p>The 4 available options are pretty straight-forward:</p>
		<ul>
		<li><b>File</b> - the source excel file to use as a template for adding data</li>
		<li><b>Out File</b> - the target excel file to write. If not specified the data is written to the source file</li>
		<li><b>Worksheet</b> the worksheet to which the data should be added</li>
		<li><b>Start at Cell</b> - the top-left cell to start at when writing data.</li> 
		</ul>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="soapUI Pro File DataSink">
		<p>The File DataSink has the following configuration panel:</p>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/file_datasink_config_panel.gif" alt="The soapUI Pro File DataSink configuration panel"/></p>
		<p>Files will be written in a simple row format, using the specified separator. The available options are:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>File - the file to write to</li>
		<li>Separator - the separator for the columns in each row</li>
		<li>Trim Values - values will be trimmed before writing</li>
		<li>Append Values - values will be appended to an existing file instead of creating a new one when the TestCase starts</li>
		</ul>
		</subsection>

		<subsection name="soapUI Pro Groovy DataSink">
		<p>The Groovy DataSink has the following configuration panel:</p>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/groovy_datasink_config_panel.gif" alt="The soapUI Pro Groovy DataSink configuration panel"/></p>
		<p>This step allows any kind of DataSink to be created for a DataSink Step. Available context variables are:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>"context" - the current TestRunContext for storing context-specific values</li>
		<li>"properties" - a Map containing the current property values</li>
		<li>"testRunner" - the current TestRunner object</li>
		<li>"log" - a log for logging</li>
		</ul> 
		</subsection>

            <subsection name="soapUI Pro Property DataSink">
		<p>The Property DataSink has the following configuration panel:</p>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/property_datasink_config_panel.gif" alt="The soapUI Pro Property DataSink configuration panel"/></p>
		<p>This step allows for aggregation of values into a property that can be used elsewhere:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>Result Property - the target property in this TestStep to write to (must be defined!)</li>
		<li>Prefix - the prefix for the property value</li>
		<li>Content - the content to add for each time the DataSink is executed</li>
		<li>Suffix - the suffix for the property value</li>
		</ul>
         <p>As seen in the example screenshot, property-expansion is supported in these fields. The example will
         continously "build" an XML list of items which can for example be used in a later request by referring to
         the DataSinks "test" property.</p>
		</subsection>

		 <p><hr size="1"/>Next: <a href="datagenstep.html">DataGen TestStep</a></p>
		</section>
    </body>
</document>
