<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Data Driven Testing - soapUI Pro Data Source loop step</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
		<section name="soapUI Pro DataSourceLoop Step">
		<p>
		Data Driven Web Service Testing is one on soapUIs' strengths. In soapUI this can be done by Groovy scripting, but in soapUI
		Pro this is simplified. 
		</p>
		
			<table class="relatedInfo" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0">
                <tr class="a">
                    <td width="75" style="padding-top:5px">
                        <img src="../../images/where_do_i_start.jpg" alt="Start soapUI Testing"
                             longdesc="http://www.soapui.org"></img>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                        <table class="relatedInner">
                            <tr>
                                <td>
                                    <span class="relatedInfoHeader">Did you know?</span>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td>
                                    <div>
                                    	<p>soapUI Pro has functionality for creating data driven tests -for example from data bases or Excel- easily.</p>
                                    	<p>The Data Source Steps soapUI pro will improve your productivity and make Web Service Testing fun.</p>
                                    </div>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr align="right">
                                <td>
                                    <span class="relatedLinks">
                                        <a href="http://www.eviware.com/component/option,com_wrapper/Itemid,41/"
                                           title="try soapUI Pro"
                                           onclick="javascript:urchinTracker:('/downloadPro');">
                                            <img src="images/try_pro_100.png" alt="Try soapUI pro to soap test"
                                                 width="101" height="20" longdesc="http://www.eviware.com"/>
                                        </a>
                                    </span>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                        </table>
                    </td>
                </tr>
            </table>
            
		<p>The DataSourceLoop Step is used together with the DataSource Step to create a sequence of steps that 
		should be executed for each row of data. It must be placed after its corresponding DataSource step and
		is configured by either double-clicking or selecting "Configure" from its popup menu, which displays the 
		following dialog:</p>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/datasource_loop.gif" alt="DataSOurce Loop Configuration Panel"/></p>
		<p>The dialog contains 2 options:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>DataSource Step - selects the DataSource Step to check for more data</li>
		<li>Target Step - selects the Step to loop to if more data is available</li>
		</ul>
		<p>For example, if a DataSource step is used to read data from an external file and the followed by 
		a request using that data, a DataSource Loop should be added after the request specifying the DataSource Step
		and the Request step as its target step... (i.e. loop back to the request if more data is available).</p>
		 <p><hr size="1"/>Next: <a href="datasinkstep.html">soapUI Pro DataSink Step</a></p>
		</section>
    </body>
</document>

