<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
  ~ soapUI, copyright (C) 2004-2008 eviware.com
  ~
  ~ soapUI is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it under the
  ~ terms of version 2.1 of the GNU Lesser General Public License as published by
  ~ the Free Software Foundation.
  ~
  ~ soapUI is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without
  ~ even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.
  ~ See the GNU Lesser General Public License for more details at gnu.org.
  -->


<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Web Service Functional Testing - TestRequests</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
		<section name="HTTP Request Steps">

            <p>HTTP Request Steps are standalone HTTP requests that can be used to call any HTTP service. They are added
                via the  TestCase Editors popup menu with the "Insert Step -&gt; HTTP Request" option.</p>

                     <subsection name="HTTP Test Request Details Tab">
                      <p>
                    The "Details" tab shown in the bottom-left shows the same properties when a TestRequest node is selected in
                    the navigation tree as for a standard request (
                    see the <a href="../rest/requests.html#Request_Details_Tab">Request Details Tab</a> for more detailed information)
                    and adds two read-only properties:
                    <ul>
                    <li><b>Path</b> : the endpoint ULR for this HTTP Request</li>
                    </ul>

                    </p>
                    </subsection>

                             <subsection name="The HTTP Test Request Editor">
                     <p>Double-clicking a HTTP Test Request in either the navigator or the TestCase Editor Pane opens the requests
                     editor which is a copy of the standard REST Request Editor with the following exception:</p>
                     <ul>
                         <li>The second toolbar button "Add to Testcase" has been replaced with "Add Assertion" which prompts
                         to add an assertion to the REST TestRequest</li>
                         <li>The endpoint drop-down has been replaced by a text field (since there is no service associated with
                         the HTTP Request).</li>
                         <li>The second toolbar has been removed.</li>
                                                  </ul>
                                     <p align="center"><img src="images/http-request-step-toolbar.gif"></img></p>

                                 <ul>
                         <li>The clone action now clones the TestRequest and appends the cloned request to the containing TestCase</li>
                         <li>Under the request/response panes there is a now a tabbed pane containing 2 tabs; the "Assertions" tab and
                         the "Request Log" tab as described in the <a href="testrequests.html">Test Requests Overview</a>.</li>
                     </ul>
                    <p>All other editing, submittal, validation functionality is the same as in the REST Request editor</p>
                    </subsection>

		 <p><hr size="1"/>Next: <a href="response-assertions.html">Assertions</a></p>
		</section>
    </body>
</document>
