<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>functional Web Service testing</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
		<section name="Functional Testing of Web Services">
		<p>
		You create a test from a WSDL by right-clicking the request and choosing "Add to TestCase". Once you you have this in a TestCase the 
		next natural step is doing functional test of it.
		</p>
						
		<p>soapUI supports functional testing of Web Services by providing a TestCase metaphor where a number
		 of TestSteps can be executed in sequence. There are currently eleven types of TestSteps available providing 
		 for rich testing possibilities. TestCases are further organized into TestSuites of which an arbitrary 
		 number can be created within each project.</p>
		 <p>Functional Web Service testing in soapUI can be used for a variety of purposes:</p>
		 <ul>
		 <li>Unit testing : validate that each Web Service operation functions as stated</li>
		 <li>Compliance testing : validate that the Web Service returns results compliant with its definition</li>
		 <li>Process testing : validate that a sequence of web service invocations fulfill a required 
		 business process</li>
		 <li>Data Driven testing : validate that any of the above works as required with data input from external 
		 sources (for example a database or another web service).</li>
		 </ul>
		 
		 				
				<table class="relatedInfo" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0">
	<tr class="a">
    	<td width="75" style="padding-top:5px">
        	<img src="../../images/where_do_i_start.jpg" alt="Start soapUI Testing" longdesc="http://www.soapui.org"></img>
        </td>
        <td>
            <table class="relatedInner">
              <tr>
                <td>
                	<span class="relatedInfoHeader">Did you know?</span>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>
                    <div>
						<p>
						<b><i>soapUI Pro</i></b> 2 makes data driven testing much more easy by adding the DataSource TestStep.
						</p>
						<p>
						<b><i>soapUI Pro</i></b> contains productivity enhancements as well as offers Professional World Class support. contains productivity enhancements as well as offers Professional World Class support.
						</p>
                    </div>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr align="right">
              	<td>
                	<span class="relatedLinks"><a href="http://www.eviware.com/component/option,com_wrapper/Itemid,41/" title="try soapUI Pro" onclick="javascript:urchinTracker:('/downloadTrial');">
                                               <img src="../../images/try_pro_100.png" alt="Try soapUI pro to soap test" width="101" height="20" longdesc="http://www.eviware.com"/></a></span>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </table>
		</td>
	</tr>
</table>
		 

		 <p><hr size="1"/>Next: <a href="getting_started.html">Getting Started with Functional Testing</a></p>
		</section>
    </body>
</document>

