<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Parameters in Web Service Testing- soapUI properties step</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
		<section name="Properties Step">
		<p>The Properties Step allows you to define an arbitrary number of properties that can be 
		used from PropertyTransfer and GroovyScript steps. The properties can optionally be read from/written to 
		a properties-file upon execution, for example if you want to specify some properties external 
		(passwords, endpoints, etc) or want to write some results to a file for later reporting..</p>

		<subsection name="Properties Editor">
		<p>The Property Step Editor is straightforward:</p>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/properties_editor.gif" alt="Parameters in Web Service Testing in the Property Step editor"/></p>
		<p>The toolbar at the top contains the following (left to right):</p>
		<ul>
		<li><b>Add Property</b> : prompts to add a new property</li>
		<li><b>Remove Property</b> : prompts to remove the selected property</li>
		<li><b>Load from</b> : optional field containing a file/URL/system-property that contains the 
		source of the properties. The specified file or URL will be read as a standard properties file and 
		contained property values will be assigned to the steps properties. If the field is set to the 
		name of a system property, this property must in turn specify a file or URL that will be subsequently 
		read as described</li>
		<li><b>Select Properties Source</b> : allows selection of a local file containing the properties to be
		read. The selected file will read and the contained properties values will be assigned to matching properties
		in the Properties Step (you will be prompted if unavailable properties are to be created)</li>
		<li><b>Save to</b> : optional field containing a file or system property that contains the 
		target name of properties file. The specified file will be created as a standard properties file and 
		contained property values will be written to it. If the field is set to the name of a system property, 
		this property must in turn specify a file that will be subsequently created as described</li>
		<li><b>Select Properties Target</b> : allows selection of a local file to which the properties should be written</li>
		</ul>
		<p>The table displayed under the toolbar displays the currently defined properties and their values, values and
		names can be changed by standard editing.</p>
		</subsection>
	
		<subsection name="Property Details Tab">
			The Properties Step Details Tab (bottom left) contains the following:
			<ul>
			<li><b>Name</b>: The name of the Properties step</li>
			<li><b>Description</b> : an arbitrary description for the Properties step</li>
			<li><b>Create Missing on Load</b> - creates properties from source property files that are not currently defined</li>
			<li><b>Save before Load</b> - specifies to save existing properties before loading new ones to/from the specified source
			and target property files</li>
			<li><b>Discard Values on Save</b> : clears all property values when project is saved</li>
			</ul>
		</subsection>

		<subsection name="Step Execution">
		<p>When a Properties Step is executed during a TestCase, the following actions are taken:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>The properties are read or written from a source if specified as described above (depending on "Save before
		Load" option)</li>
		<li>The properties are written or read to a target if specified as described above (depending on "Save before
		Load" option)</li>
		<li>The properties are all copied to the current TestRunContexts properties so they are available for 
		<a href="../properties.html#Property_Expansion_in_soapUI">Property Expansion</a></li>
		</ul>
		</subsection>

		<p><hr size="1"/>Next: <a href="delaystep.html">Web Service Test Timing: Delay TestStep</a></p>
		</section>
    </body>
</document>
