<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
  ~ soapUI, copyright (C) 2004-2008 eviware.com
  ~
  ~ soapUI is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it under the
  ~ terms of version 2.1 of the GNU Lesser General Public License as published by
  ~ the Free Software Foundation.
  ~
  ~ soapUI is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without
  ~ even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.
  ~ See the GNU Lesser General Public License for more details at gnu.org.
  -->

<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Web Service Functional Testing - TestRequests</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
		<section name="REST/HTTP Request Steps">
		 
            <p>There are two types of HTTP Request steps available:</p>
            <ol>
                <li>REST Requests are linked to a REST Resource defined in the project and use that resources service for
                validations, etc.</li>
                <li>HTTP Requests are standalone requests not linked to any other item.</li>
            </ol>

            <subsection name="REST Request Steps">

            <p>REST Request Steps are either created from REST requests using their "Add to Testcase" action or from the
                TestCase Editors popup menu with the "Insert Step -&gt; REST Request" option which will prompt for which
                REST Resource in the project that the request should be created for.</p>

                    <p>REST/HTTP TestRequests are submitted either manually through their editors submit actions or when running
                    the TestCase containing the request. The requests response is validated against a requests assertions and the
                    requests icon changes to reflect the result of the validations; green means that all validations were ok, red means that some validations
                    failed. A grey background icon indicates that the request has not yet been submitted for validation, a white
                    background indicates that the TestRequest lacks assertions</p>
                     </subsection>

                     <subsection name="REST Test Request Details Tab">
                      <p>
                    The "Details" tab shown in the bottom-left shows the same properties when a HTTP TestRequest node is selected in
                    the navigation tree as for a standard REST Request (see the <a href="../rest/requests.html#Request_Details_Tab">Request Details Tab</a>
                    for more detailed information) and adds two read-only properties:
                    <ul>
                    <li><b>Service</b> : the name of the Service for this TestRequest</li>
                    <li><b>Resource</b> : the path of the Resource for this TestRequest</li>
                    </ul>

                    </p>
                    </subsection>

                             <subsection name="The REST Test Request Editor">
                     <p>Double-clicking a REST Test Request in either the navigator or the TestCase Editor Pane opens the requests
                     editor which is more or less a copy of the standard REST Request Editor with the following exceptions:</p>
                     <ul>
                         <li>The second toolbar button "Add to Testcase" has been replaced with "Add Assertion" which prompts
                         to add an assertion to the REST TestRequest</li>
                         <li>The second toolbar contains a drop-down for selecting which REST Resource this REST Test Request should
                         be linked to.</li>
                         </ul>

                                     <p align="center"><img src="images/rest-request-step-toolbar.gif"></img></p>

                                 <ul>
                         <li>The clone action now clones the TestRequest and appends the cloned request to the containing TestCase</li>
                         <li>Under the request/response panes there is a now a tabbed pane containing 2 tabs; the "Assertions" tab and
                         the "Request Log" tab as described in the <a href="testrequests.html">Test Requests Overview</a>.</li>
                     </ul>
                    <p>All other editing, submittal, validation functionality is the same as in the REST Request editor</p>
                    </subsection>

		 <p><hr size="1"/>Next: <a href="http-requests.html">HTTP Requests</a></p>
		</section>
    </body>
</document>
