<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Running a test from another test - soapUI Run TestCase TestStep</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
		<section name="Run TestCase Step">
		<p>The Run TestCase step allows you to run another TestCase from within the current one, optionally setting and 
		retrieving TestCase properties to or from the target TestCase.
		</p>
		<p>
		This can be useful for breaking down complex TestCases 
		into smaller parts or sharing some common test functionality between TestCases.</p>
		<p>After selecting the "Run TestCase" type when creating a new TestStep, the following dialog will be shown:</p>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/runtestcase_options.gif" alt="Running a test from another test - soapUI Run TestCase TestStep Dialog"/></p>
		<p>Select the desired TestSuite and TestCase in the top combo boxes. The "Return Properties" list contains the TestCase
		properties defined for the selected target TestCase, select those properties whose values should be copied back to the 
		Run TestCase step after execution.</p>
		
		<subsection name="The Run TestCase Editor">
		<p>Once created, the Run TestCase editor will be opened, containing (top to bottom)</p>
		<ul>
		<li>A toolbar with actions to run, cancel, configure and open the target TestCase</li>
		<li>A table containing the same properties as the target TestCase. Only the property values are editable</li>
		<li>A TestCase Log inspector showing the output of the last run</li>
		</ul>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/runtestcase_1.gif" alt="The Run TestCase Editor"/></p>
		
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="Execution">
		<p>When running the TestStep, the following happens:</p>
		<ol>
		<li>The properties containing values and not marked as return properties are copied to the target TestCase</li>
		<li>The target TestCase is run</li>
		<li>The properties marked as return properties are copied back from the target TestCase to the Run TestCase step</li>
		<li>If the target TestCase failed, so will the Run TestCase step.</li>
		</ol>
		
		<p>The property handling in step 1 and 3 can be seen as input/output arguments for the target TestCase, allowing you
		to run it with different values. This could be combined with a surrounding DataSource for executing an entire TestCase 
		with a range of input values.</p>
		<p>After running, the TestCase log should contain the same output as would be seen in the TestCase log for the 
		target TestCase:</p>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/runtestcase_2.gif" alt="Run TestCase with Log"/></p>
		</subsection>

		   <p><hr size="1"/>Next: <a href="mockresponse.html">Web Service Simulation - MockResponse Step</a></p>
		</section>
    </body>
</document>
