<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
  ~ soapUI, copyright (C) 2004-2008 eviware.com
  ~
  ~ soapUI is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it under the
  ~ terms of version 2.1 of the GNU Lesser General Public License as published by
  ~ the Free Software Foundation.
  ~
  ~ soapUI is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without
  ~ even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.
  ~ See the GNU Lesser General Public License for more details at gnu.org.
  -->

<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Web Service Functional Testing - TestRequests</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
    @TODO@change the whole page appropriately
		<section name="SOAP Requests">
		 
		 <columns><column><div>
		TestRequests are one of the main features you work with in soapUI. It extends standard requests with the possibility to 
		add any number of Assertions that will be applied to the response received for the request. That is, you check that the reponse contains 
		what you expect it to contain.		 
		 <p> TestRequests are either created from standard requests using their "Add to Testcase" action or from the TestCase Editors popup 
		 menu with the "Insert Step -&gt; Test Request" option (shown to the right), which will prompt for which Interface or Operation
		  the request should be create for.</p>
		  
		  <p>When you creat A TestCase A dialog will prompt to add certain standard assertions in order to make you Web Service Testing more Rapid</p></div>
		  </column><column>
			<img src="images/add_request_to_testcase.gif" alt="Add Request to TestCase dialog containing Standard Assertions"/>
			</column></columns>
		 <p>TestRequests are submitted either manually through their editors submit actions or when running 
		 the TestCase containing the request. The requests response is validated against a requests assertions and the
		 requests icon changes to reflect the result of the validations; green means that all validations were ok, red means that some validations 
		 failed. A grey background icon indicates that the request has not yet been submitted for validation, a white 
		 background indicates that the TestRequest lacks assertions</p>

		  <subsection name="TestRequest Actions">
		   <columns><column><div>
		  The following actions are available from the test-request nodes' right-button menu:	
		  <ul>
		  <li><b>Open Editor</b> - opens the associated TestStep editor (if available)</li>
		  		<li><b>Disable/Enable TestStep</b> - disables/enables the TestStep for execution</li>
		  		<li><b>Insert Step -&gt;</b> - shows a list of insertable test-steps at the current position</li>
		  		
		  		<li><b>Rename</b> - prompts to rename the selected step</li>
		  		<li><b>Delete</b> - prompts to delete the selected step</li>
		  		<li><b>Clone TestStep</b> - prompts to clone the selected step (see below)</li>
		  		
		  		<li><b>Move Step Up</b> - moves the selected step up one position in the list
		  		(this can also be performed with Ctrl-Up)</li>
		  		<li><b>Move Step Down</b> - moves the selected step down one position in the list 
		  		(this can also be performed with Ctrl-Down)</li>
		  		
		  		<li><b>Change Operation</b> - prompts to change the operation for this TestRequest (see below)</li>
		  		<li><b>Select Operation</b> - selects this TestRequests operation in the Navigator</li>
		  		<li><b>Clone Assertions (soapUI Pro only)</b> - prompts to clone assertions from this TestRequest to 
		  		other TestRequests (see below)</li>
		  		<li><b>Online Help</b> - displays this page in a browser</li>
 		  </ul></div>
		  </column><column>
			<img src="images/testrequest_actions.gif" border="0" alt="Menu alternatives for TestRequests"/>
			</column></columns>
		 </subsection>
		 
		 	 
		  <subsection name="TestRequest Details Tab">
		   <columns><column><div>
		 The "Details" tab shown in the bottom-left shows the same properties when a TestRequest node is selected in 
		 the navigation tree as for a standard request ( 
		 see the <a href="../requests.html#Request_Details_Tab">Request Details Tab</a> for more detailed information) 
		 and adds two read-only properties:
		 <ul>
		 <li><b>Interface</b> : the name of the Interface for this TestRequest</li>
		 <li><b>Operation</b> : the name of the Operation for this TestRequest</li>
		 </ul>
		 
		 </div>
		 </column><column>
			<img src="images/test_request_details_tab.gif" border="0" alt="TestRequest Details showing Interface and Operation"/>
			</column></columns>
		 </subsection>
		 
		  <subsection name="Change Operation">
		 <p>Selecting to change the operation for a TestRequest opens the following dialog:</p>
		 <p align="center"><img src="images/change_operation.gif"/></p>
		 <p>The list of Interfaces displays those available in the current project, the list of Operations
		 is updated accordingly.</p>
		 </subsection>
		 
		  <subsection name="The TestRequest Editor">
		  <p>Double-clicking a TestRequest in either the navigator or the TestCase Editor Pane opens the requests
		  editor which is more or less a copy of the standard Request Editor with the following exception:</p>
		  <ul>
		  	<li>The second toolbar button "Add to Testcase" has been replaced with "Add Assertion" which prompts
		  	to add an assertion to the TestRequest</li>
		  	<li>The clone action now clones the TestRequest and appends the cloned request to the containing TestCase</li>
		  	<li>Under the request/response panes there is a now a tabbed pane containing 2 tabs; the "Assertions" tab and
		  	the "Request Log" tab (both described below).</li>
		  </ul>
		 <p>All other editing, submittal, validation functionality is the same as in the request editor</p>
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection name="The Assertions Tab">
		 <p>The Assertions tab lists the assertions that have been configured for the TestRequest. Double clicking an
		  assertion in the list opens that assertions' configuration dialog (if available). Any number of assertions
		  can be added, often it may be relevant to add the same type of assertion multiple times with different 
		  configurations.</p>
		  <p>A colored circle next to the  assertion indicates the status of the assertion in regard to the last
		  received response; red = assertion failed together with error messages, green = assertion ok, 
		  grey = assertion has not been performed.</p>
		 <columns><column><div>
		  The following actions are available from the assertion lists right-button menu:	
		  <ul>
			  <li><b>Add Assertion</b> - prompts to add a new assertion to the list.</li>
			  <li><b>Configure</b> (if possible) - opens the selected assertions' configuration dialog.</li>
			  <li><b>Clone</b> (if possible) - prompts to clone the select assertion.</li>
			  <li><b>Rename</b> - prompts to rename the selected assertion.</li>
			  <li><b>Remove</b> - prompts to remove the selected assertion.</li>
		  </ul></div>
		  </column><column>
			<img src="images/testrequest_assertions_tab.gif" border="0" alt="Assertion Tab easy adding of assertion"/>
			</column></columns>
			<p>The toolbar contains corresponding actions and a "Clone Assertions" action for cloning a number
			of assertions to other TestRequests (see below)</p>
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection name="Clone Assertions">
		 <p>soapUI Pro contains a right-button or assertion toolbar action for cloning an arbitrary number of
		 assertions to other TestRequests. The dialog shown is as follows:</p>
		 <p align="center"><img src="images/clone_assertions.gif" alt="Clone Assertions for Agile Web Service Testing"/></p>
		 <p>The options top-to-bottom are:</p>
		 <ul>
		 <li><b>Assertions</b> - select the assertions to be cloned</li>
		 <li><b>Target TestSteps</b> - select the TestRequests to clone to</li>
		 <li><b>Target TestCase</b> - the target TestCase</li>
		 <li><b>Target TestSuite</b> - the target TestSuite</li>
		 <li><b>Target Project</b> - the target Project</li>
		 <li><b>Overwrite</b> - overwrites existing singular assertions (ie those assertions that can only 
		 exist once, for example SoapFault, SchemaCompliance, etc). If not selected and the corresponding
		 assertions exist in the target TestStep(s), they will be ignored.</li>
		 <li><b>Open List</b> - opens a separate window after the update containing a list of all Requests/TestRequests
		 that have been modified during the clone procedure (useful for manual post processing).</li>
		 </ul>
		 <p>Setting the desired options and selecting OK will clone as configured.</p>
         </subsection>

		 <subsection name="The Request Log Tab">
		  <columns><column><div>
		  The Request Log tab simply shows a history of submit/response times and response-sizes for the TestRequest.
		  This can come in handy if you want to manually compare response times or sizes over time.	</div>
		  </column><column>
			<img src="images/testrequest_log_tab.gif" border="0" alt="The Request Log Tab for Logging Web Service Tests"/>
			</column></columns>
		 </subsection>
		   <subsection name="Request Result Viewer">
		  <p>When executing a Request Step from within a TestCase (or associated LoadTest) the actual request/result 
		  and associated properties for that request can be viewed by opening a "Request Result Viewer" either 
		  from the TestCase editors log list or from a LoadTest editors log by double-clicking the associated log entry. 
		  Sent or Received attachments are currently not saved to preserve memory.
		  </p>
		  <p> 
		  The viewer shows 3 tabs:
		  </p>
		  <ul>
		  <li><b>Request Properties</b> - shows request and reponse properties for the request</li>
		  <li><b>Request Message</b> - shows the actual request message sent, including expanded properties, 
		  inline files and MTOM/XOP Includes..</li>
		  <li><b>Response Message</b> - shows the response message received</li>
		  </ul>
		  <p align="center"><img src="images/testrequest_result_viewer.gif" border="0" alt="Viewing a A Web Service response"/></p>
		 </subsection>
		 <p><hr size="1"/>Next: <a href="rest-requests.html">REST Requests</a></p>
		</section>
    </body>
</document>
