<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Web Service Functional Testing - TestRequests</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
		<section name="Test Requests">
		<p>soapUI defines three types of Request Steps:</p>
            <ol>
                <li>SOAP Test Requests - calls a WSDL Operation defined in the project</li>
                <li>REST Test Requests - calls a REST REsource defined in the project</li>
               <li>HTTP Test Request - calls an arbitrary HTTP service</li>
            </ol>

            <p>The first two of these are internally linked to and dependant on their corresponding operations/resource
                and therefore also indirectly dependant on their containing services, which they need for validation,
                request generation, etc. Removing the service will also remove the corresponding Test Requests (a future
                feature will be to convert them to HTTP Test Requests).
                </p>

            <p>Common for all these is that they add an Assertion possibility for validating the response received
            from the target service.</p>

             <subsection name="The Assertions Tab">
		 <p>The Assertions tab lists the assertions that have been configured for the TestRequest. Double clicking an
		  assertion in the list opens that assertions' configuration dialog (if available). Any number of assertions
		  can be added, often it may be relevant to add the same type of assertion multiple times with different
		  configurations.</p>
		  <p>A colored circle next to the  assertion indicates the status of the assertion in regard to the last
		  received response; red = assertion failed together with error messages, green = assertion ok,
		  grey = assertion has not been performed.</p>
		<p align="center">	<img src="images/testrequest_assertions_tab.gif" border="0" alt="Assertion Tab easy adding of assertion"/>
			</p>
			<p>The toolbar contains corresponding actions and a "Clone Assertions" action for cloning a number
			of assertions to other TestRequests (see below)</p>
             <p>
              The following actions are available from the assertion lists right-button menu:
              <ul>
                  <li><b>Add Assertion</b> - prompts to add a new assertion to the list.</li>
                  <li><b>Configure</b> (if possible) - opens the selected assertions' configuration dialog.</li>
                  <li><b>Clone</b> (if possible) - prompts to clone the select assertion.</li>
                  <li><b>Rename</b> - prompts to rename the selected assertion.</li>
                  <li><b>Remove</b> - prompts to remove the selected assertion.</li>
              </ul></p>
		 </subsection>


		 <subsection name="The Request Log Tab">
		  <p>
		  The Request Log tab simply shows a history of submit/response times and response-sizes for the TestRequest.
		  This can come in handy if you want to manually compare response times or sizes over time.
		  </p>
			<p align="center"><img src="images/testrequest_log_tab.gif" border="0" alt="The Request Log Tab for Logging Web Service Tests"/>
                </p>

		 </subsection>
		   <subsection name="Request Result Viewer">
		  <p>When executing a Request Step from within a TestCase (or associated LoadTest) the actual request/result
		  and associated properties for that request can be viewed by opening a "Request Result Viewer" either
		  from the TestCase editors log list or from a LoadTest editors log by double-clicking the associated log entry.
		  Sent or Received attachments are currently not saved to preserve memory.
		  </p>
		  <p>
		  The viewer shows 3 tabs:
		  </p>
		  <ul>
		  <li><b>Request Properties</b> - shows request and reponse properties for the request</li>
		  <li><b>Request Message</b> - shows the actual request message sent, including expanded properties,
		  inline files and MTOM/XOP Includes..</li>
		  <li><b>Response Message</b> - shows the response message received</li>
		  </ul>
		  <p align="center"><img src="images/testrequest_result_viewer.gif" border="0" alt="Viewing a A Web Service response"/></p>
		 </subsection>

            <subsection name="Clone Assertions">
                    <p>For SOAP Requests, soapUI Pro contains a right-button or assertion toolbar action for cloning an arbitrary number of
                    assertions to other TestRequests. The dialog shown is as follows:</p>
                    <p align="center"><img src="images/clone_assertions.gif" alt="Clone Assertions for Agile Web Service Testing"/></p>
                    <p>The options top-to-bottom are:</p>
                    <ul>
                    <li><b>Assertions</b> - select the assertions to be cloned</li>
                    <li><b>Target TestSteps</b> - select the TestRequests to clone to</li>
                    <li><b>Target TestCase</b> - the target TestCase</li>
                    <li><b>Target TestSuite</b> - the target TestSuite</li>
                    <li><b>Target Project</b> - the target Project</li>
                    <li><b>Overwrite</b> - overwrites existing singular assertions (ie those assertions that can only
                    exist once, for example SoapFault, SchemaCompliance, etc). If not selected and the corresponding
                    assertions exist in the target TestStep(s), they will be ignored.</li>
                    <li><b>Open List</b> - opens a separate window after the update containing a list of all Requests/TestRequests
                    that have been modified during the clone procedure (useful for manual post processing).</li>
                    </ul>
                    <p>Setting the desired options and selecting OK will clone as configured, alternatively use the
                        "Apply" option to execute the current Dialog settings without closing it.</p>
                    </subsection>
            


		 <p><hr size="1"/>Next: <a href="soap-requests.html">SOAP Requests</a></p>
		</section>
    </body>
</document>
