<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>testcase_details_tab.gif
    <properties>
        <title>Functional Testing of Web Services - TestCase</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
		<section name="soapUI TestCases">
		 
		 <p>
		 soapUI supports functional testing of web services by providing a TestCase metaphor where a number
		 of TestSteps can be executed in sequence. Also, an arbitrary number of LoadTests can be associated
		 with a TestCase for running the TestCase under different load scenarios.
		 </p>
		 
		
		 
		 
		 
		  <subsection name="TestCase Actions">
		   <columns><column><div>
		  The following actions are available from the TestCase nodes' right-button menu:	
		  <ul>
		  <li><b>Show TestCase Editor</b> - opens the TestCase Editor described below</li>
		  <li><b>Disable/Enable TestCase</b> - disables or enables the TestCase</li>
		  <li><b>Options</b> - show the TestCase Options dialog described below</li>
		  <li><b>Add Step -></b> - adds a new TestStep to the TestCase</li>
		  <li><b>New LoadTest</b> - prompts to create a new LoadTest for the TestCase</li>
		  <li><b>Clone TestCase (see below)</b> - prompts to clone the entire TestCase, optionally into another TestSuite</li>
		  <li><b>Clone TestSteps (soapUI Pro only, see below)</b> - prompts to clone a number of TestSteps, 
		  	optionally into another TestSuite</li>
		  <li><b>Clear</b> - prompts to remove all TestSteps from the TestCase</li>
		  
		  <li><b>Rename</b> - prompts to rename the TestCase</li>
		  <li><b>Remove</b> - prompts to remove the TestCase from its TestSuite</li>

     	  <li><b>Launch Runner</b> - open the Launch dialog for the soapUI TestCaseRunner</li>
		  
		  <li><b>Move TestCase Up</b> - moves the current TestCase up in the list of TestCases</li>
		  <li><b>Move TestCase Down</b> - moves the current TestCase down in the list of TestCases</li>
		  
		  <li><b>Export</b> - prompts for file where to export Test Case</li>
		  
		  <li><b>Online Help</b> - Displays this page in an external browser</li>
		  </ul>
		</div>
		</column></columns>
		 
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection name="TestCase Details Tab">
			 The "Details" tab shown in the bottom-left shows the following values when the TestCase node is selected in 
			 the navigation tree
			 <ul>
			 <li><b>Name</b> : the name of the current TestCase</li>
			 </ul>
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection name="Clone TestCase">
		 <p>Selecting to clone a TestCase from the TestCase menu displays the following dialog:</p>
		 <p align="center"><img src="images/clone_testcase.gif" alt="Clone TestCase dialog in soapUI for Functional Testing"/></p>
		 <p>If selecting to clone to another project, soapUI will prompt to clone required interfaces to that
		 project as well.</p>
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection name="Clone TestSteps">
		 <p>Selecting to clone TestSteps from the TestCase menu displays the following dialog:</p>
		 <p>The selected steps will maintain references to each-other (for example via property-transfers) after
		 the clone, but be sure that the target TestCase(s) contains no TestSteps that have names same as those
		 being cloned (in which case the cloned steps will be prompted to be renamed).</p>
		 <p>If selecting to clone to another project, soapUI will prompt to clone required interfaces to that
		 project as well.</p>
          
		 <p align="center"><img src="images/clone_teststeps.gif"  alt="Clone TestStep dialog in soapUI Pro for Functional Testing"/></p>

         <p>Use the "Apply" option to execute the current Dialog settings without closing it.</p>
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection name="The TestCase Editor">
		 <columns><column>
		 <p>
		 Doubleclicking a TestCase node in the navigator or selecting its <b>Open TestCase Editor</b> menu option
		  	opens the TestCase editor, which let's you edit and run TestCases. If the TestCase is currently being load tested the editor 
		  	will be mostly disabled.</p>
		  	<p>The editor is divided into the following 4 parts (from top to bottom):</p>	
		  	<ul>
		  	<li>A toolbar for running or cancelling and setting options</li>
		  	<li>A progress bar showing TestCase status and progress</li>
		  	<li>A number of tabs for the TestCase; 
		  	<ul>
		  		<li><a href="#The_TestStep_List">TestSteps</a> - the list of TestSteps in the TestCase</li>
		  		<li><a href="#TestCase_Coverage">TestCase Coverage</a> - Coverage Panel for this TestCase</li>
		  		<li><a href="#TestCase_Requirements">TestCase Requirements</a> - Requirements for this TestCase</li>
		  	</ul>
		  	 </li>
		  	 <li>A number of Inspectors for the TestCase (left to right):
		  	 <ul>
		  	 <li>Description : an arbitrary description for the TestCase</li>
		  	 <li>Properties : TestCase properties</li>
		  	 <li>Setup Script : A Groovy script to run when the TestCase is run</li>
		  	 <li>TearDown Script : A Groovy script to run when the TestCase finishes</li>
		  	 </ul>
		  	 </li>
		  	<li>The TestCase Log for viewing/exporting results: the following entries are displayed:
		  	<ul>
		  	<li>When the TestCase started</li>
		  		<li>An entry for each executed TestStep specifying how long it took</li>
		  		<li>Optional errors and/or messages reported by each TestStep</li>
		  		<li>How long the TestCase took</li>
		  	</ul>
		  	</li>
		  	</ul>
		  	</column><column><img src="images/testcase_editor.gif" border="0" alt="The TestCase Editor after a Functional Web Service Test with log"/></column></columns>
		  	
		  </subsection>
		  <subsection name="The TestCase Editor Toolbar">	
			<p>The main toolbar contains the following actions (left to right)</p>
		  	
		  	<ul>
		  		<li><b>Run TestCase</b> - runs the TestCase (see below)</li>
		  		<li><b>Cancel TestCase</b> - cancels a running TestCase</li>
		  		<li><b>Run Continuously </b> - toggles if the TestCase is to be run continuously  When selected, the 
		  		TestCase will run repeatedly until cancelled with the Cancel TestCase button</li>
		  		<li><b>TestCase Credentials</b> - prompts to set the credentials to be used by all requests in the TestCase. This is 
		  		useful if you want to run your tests with different credentials</li>
		  		<li><b>TestCase Endpoint</b> - prompts to set the endpoint to be used by all requests in the TestCase. This is 
		  		useful if you want to run your tests against different servers, etc. The available URL's are collected
		  		from the test requests' operations' interfaces. The selected endpoint is assigned to each request in the 
		  		TestCase</li>
		  		<li><b>New LoadTest</b> - creates a new LoadTest for this TestCase</li>
		  		<li><b>TestCase Options</b> - opens the TestCase Options dialog described below</li>
		  		<li><b>Create Report (soapUI Pro only)</b> : Exports a HTML Report for the last TestSuite run (see below)</li>
		  		 <li><b>Online Help</b> - Displays this page in an external browser</li>
		  	</ul>
		  	</subsection>
		  	
		  	<subsection name="The TestStep List">
		  	 <columns><column>
		  	<p>The TestSteps tab contains a list of the currently configured TestSteps for this TestCase.
		  	Double-clicking a TestStep in the list opens that items editor view. Right-clicking a TestStep shows a popup-menu
		  	with the following actions:</p>
		  	<ul>
		  		<li><b>Open Editor</b> - opens the associated TestStep editor (if available)</li>
		  		<li><b>Disable/Enable TestStep</b> - disables or enables the TestStep for execution</li>
		  		<li><b>Insert Step -&gt;</b> - shows a list of insertable test-steps at the current position</li>
		  		
		  		<li><b>Rename</b> - prompts to rename the selected step</li>
		  		<li><b>Delete</b> - prompts to delete the selected step</li>
		  		<li><b>Clone TestStep</b> - prompts to clone the selected step (see below)</li>
		  		
		  		<li><b>Move Step Up</b> - moves the selected step up one position in the list
		  		(this can also be performed with Ctrl-Up)</li>
		  		<li><b>Move Step Down</b> - moves the selected step down one position in the list 
		  		(this can also be performed with Ctrl-Down)</li>
		  		
		  		<li><b>Step specific actions</b> - depends on which type of TestStep that is selected</li>
		  		<li><b>Online Help</b> - displays this page in a browser</li>
		  	</ul>
		  	
		  	<p>Double clicking a TestSteps' entry in the log opens a TestStep result viewer for that step 
		  	if available and as described on each TestStep documentation page 
		  	(for example the <a href="testrequests.html#Request_Result_Viewer">Request Result Viewer</a>).</p>
		  </column></columns>
		  	
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection name="TestCase Options">
		 <p>Selecting TestCase Options from either a TestCase nodes popup menu in the navigator or from the TestCase
		 Editors toolbar opens a dialog with the following options.</p>
		 
		 <ul>
		 <li><b>Search Properties</b> : When looking for property values without step specifications 
		 (see <a href="../properties.html#Property_Expansion_in_soapUI">Property Expansion</a>), check all steps
		 before the current one for the named property.</li>
		 <li><b>Session</b> : Controls if a HTTP Session is to maintained for all requests
		in the TestCase. Selecting this will reuse cookies, authentication headers, etc</li>
		<li><b>Abort on error</b> : Controls if the TestCase is to be canceled when a TestStep fails with an error, 
		(for example if a contained RequestStep has failed assertions)</li>
		<li><b>Fail TestCase on Error</b> : Controls if the TestCase is to fail if it the "Fail on error" option
		is not selected and the TestCase ends with one or more TestStep.</li>
		<li><b>Discard OK Results</b> : Long Running TestCases will eventually consume substantial amount of memory
		since all TestStep results are internally cached for later viewing/reporting. Checking this option will make
		soapUI only save non successful TestStep results which will save substantial amounts of memory.</li>
		<li><b>Socket timeout</b> : The timeout (in milliseconds) to be used for all requests in the TestCase</li>
		<li><b>TestCase timeout</b> : The timeout (in milliseconds) to wait before canceling or failing a running TestCase</li>
		<li><b>Max results</b> : The maximum number of TestStep Results to keep in memory during the execution of a TestCase</li>
		
		</ul>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/testcase_options.gif" alt="Setting options for a Functional Testing of Web Services in TestCase Options"/></p>
		 </subsection>

		 <subsection name="Clone TestStep">
		 <p>Selecting to clone a TestStep from a TestSteps menu displays the following dialog:</p>
		 <p align="center"><img src="images/clone_teststep.gif" alt="Clone TestStep Dialog"/></p>
		 <p>If selecting to clone to another project, soapUI will prompt to clone the required interface to that
		 project as well if not available.</p>
		 </subsection>
		 
		  <subsection name="Generating Test Reports">
		   <p>soapUI Pro supports the generation of reports from within the TestCase editor. The reports show a summary
		 of all the executed TestCase and diagnostic information for failed assertions.</p>
		 <p>Selecting the "Create Report" button in toolbar opens the following dialog for exporting the last results
		 to an HTML report:</p>
		 <p align="center"><img src="images/createreport.gif" alt="Dialog for Creating a Web Service test report"/></p>
		 <p>After specifying the output folder and format, the report will be created and opened in an external browser:</p>
		 <p align="center"><img src="images/sampletestcasereport.gif"  alt="A Web Service test report in soapUI"/></p>
		 </subsection>
		
		<subsection name="TestCase Coverage">
		<p>
		TestCase Coverage is an Unique Functionality for soapUI (soapUI Pro only) that allows you to see how much of the Web Services 
		are being covered by you tests. In everyday work this let's you improve your test by adding assertions for uncovered elements 
		as well as shows which elements are unused in your test cases.
		</p>
		<p>The TestCase Coverage tab contains the same Coverage information as available in the TestSuite and Project 
		Coverage Panels. Enabling Coverage and running the TestCase will dynamically calculate/update the messages 
		exchanged during the tests and add their Coverage information to the Coverage Panel. See the 
		<a href="../projects/coverage.html">Project Coverage</a> document for details.</p>
		 <p align="center"><img src="images/testcase_coverage.gif" alt="Test Coverage in soapUI Pro"/></p>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="TestCase Requirements">
		<p>The TestCase Requirements tab contains the same Requirements Panel as seen on the Project Viewer, but only 
		those Requirements that are dependant on this TestCase.</p>
		 <p align="center"><img src="images/testcase_requirements.gif" alt="Test Case Requirements in soapUI Pro"/></p>
		<p> Adding a new Requirement will automatically add the 
		current TestCase to that requirements TestCase List. Also, a specialized "Link TestCase" option is available from
		the Requirements Toolbar for linking the TestCase to existing Requirements:</p>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/link_testcase_to_requirements.gif" alt="Linking a Case Requirements to a test in soapUI Pro"/></p>
		</subsection>
		 
		   <p><hr size="1"/>Next: <a href="teststeps.html">Web Service functional Testing- Working with Test Steps</a></p>
		</section>
    </body>
</document>
