<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Test Web Services - TestSuites</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
		<section name="Web Service TestSuites">
		 
		 <p>A TestSuite serves as container for an arbitrary number of TestCases. When running a TestSuite the 
		 contained TestCases can be executed either in sequence or in parallel as described below.</p>
		 
		  <subsection name="Generating TestSuites">
		 <p>
		  Selecting the "Generate TestSuite" option from the Interface menu prompts to generate a complete 
		  TestSuite for the selected interface. The dialog contains the following options;</p>
		  
		   <p align="center"><img src="images/generate_testsuite.gif" border="0" alt="Generate TestSuite in soapUI"/></p>
		  <ul>
		  <li><b>TestSuite</b> - select if to generate into an existing TestSuite or create a new one</li>
		  
		  <li><b>Style</b> - there are 2 different styles:
		  <ol>
		  <li>One TestCase for each Operation - creates a TestSuite with one TestCase for each operation</li>
		  <li>Single TestCase with one Request for each Operation - create just that!</li>
		  </ol>
		  </li>
		  
		  <li><b>Request Content</b> - there are 2 alternatives:
		  <ol>
		  <li>Use existing Requests in Interface - uses the existing requests as TestRequests</li>
		  <li>Create new Empty Requests - creates new empty requests with optional content in the created TestRequests</li>
		  </ol>
		  </li>
		  
		  <li><b>Operations</b> - Select those operations you want to generate for</li>
		  <li><b>Generate LoadTest</b> - Creates a default LoadTest for each generated TestCase</li>
		  </ul>
		  
		 
		 </subsection>
		 
		 
		 				
				<table class="relatedInfo" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0">
	<tr class="a">
    	<td width="75" style="padding-top:5px">
        	<img src="../../images/where_do_i_start.jpg" alt="Start soapUI Testing" longdesc="http://www.soapui.org"></img>
        </td>
        <td>
            <table class="relatedInner">
              <tr>
                <td>
                	<span class="relatedInfoHeader">Did you know?</span>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>
                    <div>
						<p>
						In <b><i>soapUI Pro</i></b> you can see how well your TestSuites tests your Web Services. soapUI Pro is the the only tool around using TestSuite Coverage.
						</p>
						<p>
						If test quality matters, try <b><i>soapUI Pro</i></b>.
						</p>
                    </div>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr align="right">
              	<td>
                	<span class="relatedLinks"><a href="http://www.eviware.com/component/option,com_wrapper/Itemid,41/" title="try soapUI Pro" onclick="javascript:urchinTracker:('/downloadTrial');">
                                               <img src="../../images/try_pro_100.png" alt="Try soapUI pro to soap test" width="101" height="20" longdesc="http://www.eviware.com"/></a></span>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </table>
		</td>
	</tr>
</table>
		 

		 
		 <subsection name="TestSuite Actions">
          <columns><column><div>
		  The following actions are available from the TestSuite nodes' right-button menu:	
		  <ul>
  		  <li><b>Open TestSuite Editor</b> - Opens the TestSuite Runner described below</li>
  		  <li><b>Disable/Enable TestSuite</b> - Disables/Enables the TestSuite</li>
		  <li><b>New TestCase</b> - prompts to create a new TestCase in the TestSuite</li>
		  <li><b>Clone TestSuite</b> - prompts to clone the entire TestSuite, including all TestCases/TestSteps</li>
		  <li><b>Launch TestRunner</b> - opens the dialog for launching the 
  		   <a href="../commandline/functional.html#Launch_Dialog">command-line TestRunner</a></li>
		  <li><b>Rename</b> - prompts to rename the TestSuite</li>
		  <li><b>Remove</b> - prompts to remove the TestSuite from its project. All contained TestCases 
		  will be removed also.</li>
		  <li><b>Export</b> - export this TestSuite</li>
		  <li><b>Import Test Case</b> - prompts for Test Case to import to this TestSuite</li>
		  <li><b>Online Help</b> - Displays this page in an external browser</li>
		  
		  </ul>
		  </div>
		  </column></columns>
		 </subsection>
		 
		  <subsection name="TestSuite Details Tab">
				 The "Details" tab shown in the bottom-left shows the following values when the TestSuite node is selected in 
				 the navigation tree
				 <ul>
				 <li><b>Name</b> : the name of the current TestSuite</li>
				 </ul>
		 </subsection>
		 
		  <subsection name="TestSuite Runner">
		 <columns><column><div>
		  Double Clicking a TestSuite in the navigator opens the TestSuite Runner containing a list of the contained
		  TestCases and a toolbar. A Progress Bar is displayed for each TestCase, double-clicking a TestCase opens 
		  the associated TestCase editor.  If a TestCase is currently being load tested its Progress Bar displays this 
		  and the TestCase will not be run during TestSuite execution.
		  <p>The available toolbar buttons left to right are:</p>
		  <ul>
		  <li><b>Run</b> : Runs selected TestCases</li>
		  <li><b>Cancel</b> : Cancels ongoing runs</li>
		  <li><b>New TestCase</b> : Prompts to create a new TestCase in this TestSuite</li>	
		  <li><b>Run in Sequence</b> : Toggles if the TestCases should be run in sequence</li>
		  <li><b>Run in Parallel</b> : Toggles if the TestCases should be run in parallel</li>
		  <li><b>Create Report (soapUI Pro only)</b> : Exports a HTML Report for the last TestSuite run (see below)</li>
		  </ul>
		  <p>The run in sequence/parallel state is preserved and also applied when running a TestSuite using one
		  of the command line tools or the maven plugin.</p>
		
		  <p>After the progress bar the comes a List of the contained TestCases follows by a number of Inspectors for 
		  the TestCase (left to right):</p>
		  	 <ul>
		  	 <li>Description : an arbitrary description for the TestSuite</li>
		  	 <li>Properties : TestCase properties</li>
		  	 <li>Setup Script : A Groovy script to run when the TestSuite is run</li>
		  	 <li>TearDown Script : A Groovy script to run when the TestSuite finishes</li>
		  	 </ul>
		  	 
		  	 <p>The TestSuite log window at the bottom shows all step/run results for the last TestSuite run</p>
		
		 </div>
		  </column><column>
			<img src="images/testsuite_runner.gif" border="0" alt="Running a number of TestCases in a TestSuite"/>
			</column></columns>
		 
		 </subsection>
		 
		 <subsection name="Generating Reports">
		 <p>soapUI Pro supports the generation of reports from within the TestSuite editor. The reports show a summary
		 of all executed TestCases and diagnostic information for failed assertions.</p>
		 <p>Selecting the "Create Report" button in toolbar opens the following dialog for exporting the last results
		 to an HTML report:</p>
		 <p align="center"><img src="images/createreport.gif" alt="Create a Report Dialog"/></p>
		 <p>After specifying the output folder and format, the report will be created and opened in an external browser:</p>
		 <p align="center"><img src="images/sampletestsuitereport.gif" alt="'Report from running a Functional Test Suite"/></p>
		 </subsection>
		
		<subsection name="TestSuite Coverage">
		<p>
		TestSuit Coverage is an Unique Functionality for soapUI (soapUI Pro only) that allows you to see how much of the Web Services 
		are being covered by you tests. In everyday work this let's you improve your test by adding assertions for uncovered elements 
		as well as shows which elements are unused in your test suites.
		</p>
		<p>The TestSuite Coverage tab contains the same Coverage information as available in the Project 
		Coverage Panel. Enabling Coverage and running the TestSuite will dynamically calculate/update the messages 
		exchanged during the tests and add their Coverage information to the Coverage Panel. See the 
		<a href="../projects/coverage.html">Project Coverage</a> document for details.</p>
		 <p align="center"><img src="images/testsuite_coverage.gif" alt="TestSuite Coverage Report"/></p>
		</subsection>		
		   <p><hr size="1"/>Next: <a href="testcases.html">Functional Web Service Testing - TestCases</a></p>
		</section>
    </body>
</document>
