<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Automatic Form Editor from WSDL - soapUI Pro</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
		<section name="Auto Generated Form Editor in soapUI Pro">
		
		      <table class="relatedInfo" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0">
                <tr class="a">
                    <td width="75" style="padding-top:5px">
                        <img src="../images/where_do_i_start.jpg" alt="Start soapUI Testing"
                             longdesc="http://www.soapui.org"></img>
                    </td>
                    <td>
                        <table class="relatedInner">
                            <tr>
                                <td>
                                    <span class="relatedInfoHeader">Did you know?</span>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr>
                                <td>
                                    <div>
                                        <p>soapUI Pro allows you to view your requests as forms. No more XML! This makes your work easier and faster.</p>
                                        <p>The different editors in soapUI pro will improve your productivity and make Web Service Testing fun.</p>
                                    </div>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                            <tr align="right">
                                <td>
                                    <span class="relatedLinks">
                                        <a href="http://www.eviware.com/component/option,com_wrapper/Itemid,41/"
                                           title="try soapUI Pro"
                                           onclick="javascript:urchinTracker:('/downloadPro');">
                                            <img src="images/try_pro_100.png" alt="Try soapUI pro to soap test"
                                                 width="101" height="20" longdesc="http://www.eviware.com"/>
                                        </a>
                                    </span>
                                </td>
                            </tr>
                        </table>
                    </td>
                </tr>
            </table>
		
		<p>The form editor attempts to dynamically build a user friendly input form from the underlying XML Schema 
		definition for the current request message. The following screenshot shows the form created for one of
		the PayPal API calls;</p>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/formeditor_overview.gif" alt="Form created from XML Schema automatically"/></p>
		
		<p>The toolbar contains buttons to Validate and Clear the current form. Clear will recreate an 
		empty underlying request contain only required elements. Validating will show a 
		clickable list of errors below the editor that can be used to move focus to the corresponding field that
		caused the error:</p>
		
		<p align="center"><img src="images/validate_form_editor.gif" alt="Form validations of input data for SOAP Request"/></p>
		
		<p>By default, the editor creates fields for all elements and attributes in the underlying schema for those
		structures that are available in the underlying message, which can both be useful for inspection purposes
		but also annoying for testing purposes. Therefore, the toolbar contains a "View Type" combo which offers
		the following options:</p>
		<ul>
		<li><b>All</b> - will display all fields (default)</li>
		<li><b>Mandatory</b> - will display only mandatory fields</li>
		<li><b>Data</b> - will display only fields that contain any data. This can come in handy during
		testing when preparing a request and wanting to hide remaining fields</li>
		<li><b>Mandatory and Data</b> - will display all fields containing data and those that are mandatory</li> 
		</ul>
		<p>For example the following shows the above request with the "Data" value selected</p>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/formeditor_dataonly.gif" alt="Schema Generated form showing only elements containing data"/></p>
		<p>This setting will be remembered between editing sessions.</p>
		
		<subsection name="Data type Support">
		<p>The Form Editor uses validating editors for all native XML Schema data types and
		provides popup dialogs for easy entry of dates, durations, etc.</p>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/formeditor_input.gif" alt="Example of DateTime support for Web Service Forms"/></p>
		
		
		<p> The editors will discard values not allowed 
		by the schema, if it is still required to enter "invalid" values the right-button menu for these fields contains
		a "Set Value" action for entering any text into the field:</p>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/formeditor_setvalue.gif" alt="Bypassing Data Type Support in soapUI Pro"/></p>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="Schema Support">
		<p>The soapUI Pro Form Editor supports most commons XML Schema constructs but may have trouble displaying,
            editing, or validating more
		complex schemas. Therefore, it is advisable to initially double check the XML generated by the editor in
		one of the other editors. Since it is our ambition to fully support XML Schema, please let us know if you have
		schema constructs that are giving you or the editor trouble...</p>
		<p>The following constructs should currently work fine:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>Standard elements; if maxOccurs is more than 1 a listbox with add,edit, or remove buttons will be shown</li>
		<li>Enumerations or Booleans will be displayed as combo-boxes</li>
		<li>Binary fields are linked to the attachment support, a "Browse..." button will be displayed next to the
		input field allowing browsing and automatic associated of a file with a binary field</li>
		<li>Attributes are displayed with a @ before the field name</li>
		<li>Standard Sequence, Choice and All complex types - Choice will be displayed with a combo-box in the section header 
		from which the desired choice should be selected.</li>
		<li>Multiple occurrences of an complex element will be displayed as a list with add or remove buttons in the top right.
		Each entry in the list will be displayed with a list index next to the section name, for example in the last 
		screenshot above, the MassPayItem section can contain 1-250 MassPayItems, currently it contains only one (seen 
		with an index of [0]).</li>
		<li>AbstractTypes will display a drop-down of global derived types from the schema, allowing selection of 
		which derived type to use</li>
		</ul>
		</subsection>
		<p>A '*' after a field name denotes that it is required. All fields can show a small green question-mark 
		which will show documentation information from the associated type in a tooltip.</p>
		
		 <p><hr size="1"/>Next: <a href="overviewview.html">Overview View for Understandable SOAP Viewing</a></p>
		</section>
    </body>
</document>