<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>userguide - requests - message inspectors</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
		<section name="soapUI Pro Message Inspectors">
		<p>soapUI Pro adds a number of WSDL Context sensitive message inspectors that are available
		for both the standard XML Source editor and the Outline Editor displaying context 
		sensitive details for the currently selected content element.</p>
		
		<p>The following inspectors are currently available:</p>
		<ul>
		<li><b><a href="#XSD_XML_Schema_Inspector">XSD</a></b> - displays XML Schema information for the selected node</li>
		<li><b><a href="#Table_Layout_Inspector">Table</a></b> - displays a tabular view of the current nodes' siblings and children</li>
		<li><b><a href="#XML_-_XML_Fragment_XPath_Inspector">XML</a></b> - displays XML fragment and XPath information for the current node</li>
		<li><b><a href="#Doc_-_XML_Schema_Documentation_Inspector">Doc</a></b> - displays schema documentation annotations if available</li>
		<li><b><a href="#Coverage_Inspector">Coverage</a></b> - displays Message Coverage information for the selected node</li>
		</ul>
		<p>Each tab is enabled or disabled if corresponding content is available.</p>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/message_inspectors.gif" alt="A view of the different Message Inspectors in soapUI"/></p>
		
		<subsection name="Coverage Inspector">
		<p>When enabled via its toolbar, the coverage inspector continuously displays <a href="coverage.html">Message Coverage</a> information for the current request
		or response message.</p>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/coverage_inspector.gif"  alt="Well Testedness with the Message Inspector"/></p>
		<p>In the image above, the inspector shows red for the search string element since it contains a default value ('?'), 
		checking the "Default Values" checkbox in the toolbar would allow this and show the entire message as covered.</p>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="XSD/XML Schema Inspector">
		<p>The XML Schema Inspector displays the current nodes corresponding XML Schema definition if possible. For simple
		types (for example in a sequence), the containing complex type is displayed instead. The tab title will contain
		the name of the current type if available. The following screenshot 
		shows schema information for the selected RequesterCredentials SOAP Header in a request to the PayPal API</p>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/schema_inspector_1.gif" alt="Detailed Element information in soapUI Schema Inspector"/></p>
		<p>Note that the inspector requires the message to comply with the currently imported WSDL file, for example if a
		received response has an updated namespace, the inspector will not be able to display schema information.</p>
		</subsection>

		<subsection name="Table Layout Inspector">
		<p>The Table Inspector builds a tabular view of the current selected node and its siblings and children;</p>
		<ul>
		<li>siblings correspond to rows in the table</li>
		<li>children correspond to columns. For each sibling the same children that are available for the selected node are
		displayed</li>
		</ul>
		<p>Once selected, it is possible to navigate "both ways", i.e. clicking in a new row in the table moves focus in the 
		current editor to the corresponding node. The tab title displays the currently number of available rows.</p>
		<p>The following screenshot shows a tabular view of the items found in a Amazon search result;</p>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/table_inspector_1.gif" alt="Viewing Message Structure in Table Layout Inspector"/></p>
		</subsection>

		<subsection name="XML - XML Fragment/XPath Inspector">
		<p>The XML Fragment/XPath inspector shows the XML fragment for the currently selected node, which can be useful  
		when using the Outline Editor to navigate a message. It also displays the currently selected nodes XPath expression 
		which can be selected and copied to the clipboard with Ctrl-C. The following screenshot shows an XML fragment
		for a node in found in a Amazon search result;</p>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/xml_inspector_1.gif" alt="Zooming in on ZML Fragment in the XML Fragment Inspector"/></p>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="Doc - XML Schema Documentation Inspector">
		<p>The Doc inspector displays any schema annotations for the currently selected type. These are also available as
		tooltips in the Outline Editor but can be useful in the Source Editor as shown in the following screenshot for a 
		PayPal API request;</p>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/doc_inspector_1.gif" alt="Viewing Schema Annotations in the XML Schema Documentation Inspector"/></p>
		</subsection>

		 <p><hr size="1"/>Next: <a href="attachments.html">Working with Web Service Attachments and Inline Files</a></p>
		</section>
    </body>
</document>