<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>web service testing - soapUI 3.0</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="SoapUI 3.0 new features">
            <p>Welcome to soapUI 3.0- The Reporting Release!</p>
            <p>
                <i>As always, make backups of your project files before switching and let us know if you have any
                    issues! Also please note that projects with REST testing saved in 3.0 beta may not be usable in 2.5.x!
                </i>
            </p>
            <table class="webstartlinkstable">
                <tr>
                    <td align="center" bgcolor="white">
                        <span class="webstartheader">soapUI 3.0.1</span><br/>
                        <div>
                            <a href="http://www.soapui.org/jnlp/3.0.1/soapui.jnlp"
                               urchinTracker="/jnlp/soapui/3_0_1">
                                <img class="webstart" src="images/webstart_green.png" border="0" alt="SoapUI WebStart"/>
                            </a>
                        </div>
                       [<a target="_new"
                            href="https://sourceforge.net/projects/soapui/files/soapui/3.0.1">
                        Download</a>]
                    </td>
                    <td align="center" bgcolor="white">
                        <span class="webstartheader">soapUI Pro 3.0.1</span><br/>
                        <div>
                            <a href="http://www.eviware.com/jnlp/3.0.1/soapui-pro.jnlp"
                               urchinTracker="/jnlp/soapui/3_0_1">
                                <img class="webstart" src="images/webstart_orange.png" border="0"
                                     alt="SoapUI Pro WebStart"/>
                            </a>
                        </div>
                     [<a target="_new" href="http://www.eviware.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=blogsection&amp;id=12&amp;Itemid=58">Download</a>]
                 
                    </td>

                </tr>
            </table>
         <p>(webstart and more plugins will be released soon)</p>
         
          <p>Many initial/minor issues fixed in the nightly builds, don't hesitate to use them instead; 
		 <a href="http://www.eviware.com/nightly-builds">http://www.eviware.com/nightly-builds</a></p>

		<subsection name="3.0.1 Release">
		<p>This is mostly a bug-fix release, the following has been handled:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>Updated installers for Mac, Linux and 64-bit Windows (without JRE)</li>
		<li>Updated components/libraries: JXBrowser 1.3 + hotfixes, Groovy 1.6.4, WSS4j 1.5.8, XML-Sec 1.4.3, Bouncycastle 1.43, JTidy r820</li>
		<li>Fixed Java 1.5 compatibility</li>
		<li>Database configuration, password-handling and encryption fixed (Pro-only)</li>
		<li>JasperReport-template adjustments (Pro-only)</li>
		<li>Updated Launch-dialogs to support all current command-line options</li>
		<li>Null-pointer fixes in WS-Security handling</li>
		<li>Fixed sorting of properties</li>
		<li>Fixes related to names containing leading/trailing spaces</li>
		<li>WSDL-loading-related fixes (redirects and schema overrides)</li>
		<li>REST-related fixes and improvements</li>
		<li>New: Possibility to insert file as base64 encoded string (Thank you Cory!)</li>
		<li>New: Groovy scripts are now run in seperate thread when running in TestStep editor (Thank you Piotr!)</li>
		<li>New: MockServices now don't require SOAP Action by default (Thank you azl!)</li>
		<li>New and experimental: Deploy as WAR (from Project menu), packages the project as a WAR file for running 
		MockServices inside an existing servlet container.</li>
		<li>and many more fixes..</li>
		</ul>
		<p>Who can we thank more than our customers and users? no-one! Thank you everyone for your patience and support!</p>
		<p>/the-eviware-soapui-team</p>
		
		</subsection>

            <subsection name="Final Release">
             <p>The final release includes many more minor fixes and some minor improvements:</p>
                <ul>
                    <li>Global interval for garbage collection to improve memory handling</li>
                    <li>Improved handling of linked TestCases to Requirements</li>
                    <li>Many improvements to the default Jasper-based reports, now also including Coverage information</li>
                    <li>Updated Browser component and related fixes</li>
                    <li>WebStart distribution</li>
                    <li>Updated documentation on new and old features</li>
                    <li>etc..</li>
                </ul>
                <p>As always thank you to all of our users that have reported issues and annoyances, we owe you :-)</p>
            </subsection>

		 <subsection name="Updates..">
		 <ul>
		 <li>2009-06-10 : beta2 release! Mainly bug fixes and minor improvements, but also some new features, including:
		 <ul>
		 <li>A powerful <a href="userguide/projects/eventhandlers.html">Event Handler</a> functionality for customizing test-behaviour (*)</li>
		 <li>A Forum-search field in the main window toolbar!</li>
		 <li>JDBC Connection passwords are now held in separate field and displayed masked in the UI</li>
		 <li>Collapse/Expand right-button menu in Navigator when clicking outside the label of an item</li>
		 </ul>
		 </li>
		 <li>2009-05-27 : maven 1 and maven 2 plugins available from maven repositories, use version 3.0-beta-1</li>
		 </ul>
		 </subsection>

         <subsection name="Major New Features">
         <p>(* = SoapUI Pro only)</p>
         <ul>
         <li><p><b>Reporting *</b> - SoapUI Pro 3.0 adds an extensive framework for creating reports from
         project and test result data. The framework comes with a number of pre-configured reports for your 
         tests which allows you to save test results and test metrics. Reports can be saved as
         <ul>
         <li>PDF, HTML, WORD, Excel through JasperReports</li>
         <li>XML or CSV Data Export</li>
         <li>JUnit Style reports as previously available</li>
         </ul>
         <a href="userguide/projects/reporting/index.html">[Read More...]</a></p>
         </li>
		 <li><p><b>REST Improvements</b> - We build on the success of 2.5 -the REST Release by improving as follows:
		 <ul>
		 <li>Inferred schemas - For schema-less services soapUI can automatically generate an XML Schema for you from gathered
		 response content (including non-xml responses that are converted to xml by soapUI, for example JSON).
		  <a href="userguide/rest/inference.html">[Read More...]</a>, <a href="userguide/rest/tutorial.html">[Tutorial]</a></li>
		 <li>Improved REST model - soapUI now models REST methods as separate items in the soapUI Object Model (old projects
		 are automatically converted to new ones), <a href="userguide/rest/methods.html">[Read More...]</a></li>
		 <li>WADL Spec update - WADL support has been updated to be in line with the latest specification draft</li>
		 <li>WADL Coverage * - WSDL Coverage calculation has now been extended to also support WADL; get coverage information 
		 for your REST resources, methods, parameters and XML representations.</li>
		 <li>Added support for OPTIONS and TRACE methods</li> 
		 <li>HTML Response viewer for viewing HTML, images, flash-movies, etc inside soapUI</li>
		 </ul></p>
		 </li>
         <li><p><b>JDBC Connection handling *</b> : JDBC connections can now be managed at the project level and reused in related
         DataSource and DataSink steps. A number of wizards have been added to create valid connection strings for all
         common JDBC drivers, and for generating SQL Select and Update statements  
         <a href="userguide/projects/jdbcConnections.html">[Read More...]</a></p>
         </li>
         <li><p><b>JavaScript Support</b> - it is now possible to use JavaScript (via the Rhino engine) as a scripting language
         in all scripts inside a project (script language is changed on the project level).</p></li> 
         <li><p><b>WS-ReliableMessaging</b> - soapUI now support WS-ReliableMessaging (versions 1.0, 1.1 and 1.2) both on a request and TestCase level</p></li> 
         <li><p><b>WS-I Tools Bundling</b> - Tools for performing WS-I Basic Profile compliance tests are now bundled
         with soapUI, no separate download or installation is required. This will make Interoperability testing easier.</p></li> 
         <li><p><b>Mac and Linux Installers</b> - He have added native installers for Mac OS X and Linux and updated the Windows Installer. On Mac OS X soapUI is now installed as a proper .app</p></li> 
         <li><p><b>Project Runner</b> - It is now possible to run and reorder TestSuites from within soapUI (in the Project Window),
         including setup/tearDown scripts on the Project Level</p></li>
         <li><p><b>Fixed Rate Strategy *</b> - Load Strategy for sending requests or TestCases in a fixed rate, regardless of how long
         the corresponding execution takes.</p></li>
         <li><p><b>Improved Browser Component</b> - soapUI now bundles a much improved XULRrunner based browser component, 
         allowing much improved integrated viewing of HTML and REST responses, including Flash, SVG, Images, and more</p></li> 
         </ul>
         </subsection>
         <subsection name="And lots of minor goodies..">
         <p>A huge list of minor improvements, including</p>
         <ul>
         <li>Assertions: <a href="userguide/functional/testrequests.html#The_Assertions_Tab">Possibility to rearrange assertions</a></li>
         <li>Command Line: SaveAfterRun Option (useful with DataGen) *</li>
         <li>Datagen: DataGen Number property improvement *</li>
         <li>Datagen: DataGen window shows last value *</li>
         <li>Editors: Validation expands content in xml</li>
         <li>Editors: TextArea in contains-assertion</li>
         <li>Memory: Memory improvements for long-running tests</li>
         <li>Misc: Option to Keep SOAP Headers when updating interface</li>
         <li>Misc: Improved Prefix-handling for default namespaces</li>
         <li>SOAP: Improved MTOM Encoding</li>
         <li>HTTP: Improved Chunked Encoding handling</li>
         <li>HTTP: <a href="userguide/preferences.html#HTTP_Settings">Added global option to enable Expect-Continue handshakes</a></li>  
         <li>Misc: Possibility to launch soapUI with URL; if WSDL soapUI will start new project wizard, 
         if WADL soapUI will create new project and launch new rest service wizard</li>
         <li>Misc: Import project remembers last folder</li>
         <li>Mocking: Ability to specify local host to bind to</li>
         <li>Mocking: Ability to control compression to use for a MockResponse</li>
         <li>Mocking: Multithreaded onResponse/afterRequest MockService scripts</li>
         <li>Mocking: Mock supports messages without body/parts</li>
         <li>Mocking: Menu option to restart a MockService</li>
         <li>Project: Generate project name from WSDL/WADL file name</li>
         <li>Test Management: Change description when cloning 
         	<a href="userguide/functional/testcases.html#Clone_TestCase">TestCases</a> and 
         	<a href="userguide/functional/testsuites.html#Clone_TestSuite">TestSuites</a></li>
         <li>Test Management: <a href="userguide/functional/teststeps.html#Clone_TestStep">Option to open TestStep on clone</a></li>
         <li>Test Management: <a href="userguide/functional/teststeps.html#MultiDelete_of_TestSteps">Multi-actions; delete TestStep</a></li>
         <li>Test Properties: <a href="userguide/properties.html#Property Editors">Save properties table</a></li>
         <li>Test Properties: <a href="userguide/properties.html#Property Editors">Improved Load Properties from file</a></li>
         <li>Test Properties: Action to reload global properties from file</li>
         <li>Wizards: <a href="userguide/functional/response-wizards.html#Add_Script_Assertion_Wizard">Add Script Assertion wizard *</a></li>
         <li>Load Testing: Added "Runs per Thread" limit</li>
         <li>Load Testing: Error-ration column</li>
         <li>etc..</li>
         </ul>  
         
         </subsection>
         <subsection name="Updated Libraries">
         <ul>
         <li><a target="_new" href="http://groovy.codehaus.org/">Groovy</a> 1.6.3 (1.5.7)</li>
         <li><a target="_new" href="http://ws.apache.org/wss4j/">WSS4J</a> 1.5.7 (1.5.5)</li>
         <li><a target="_new" href="http://commons.apache.org/logging/">Commons Logging</a> 1.1.1 (1.1)</li>
         <li><a target="_new" href="http://www.mortbay.org/jetty/">Jetty</a> 6.1.15 (6.1.14)</li>
         <li><a target="_new" href="http://jexcelapi.sourceforge.net/">JExcelApi</a> updated to 2.6.10</li>
         <li><a target="_new" href="http://www.saxonica.com/">Saxon XPath/XQuery processor</a> updated to 9.1.0.6</li>
         <li>Bundled JRE updated to 1.6.0_13</li>
         </ul>
         </subsection>
         <subsection name="Major Bugs Fixed">
         <p>A large number of bugs have been fixed, including</p>
         <ul>
         <li>Burst Strategy now works</li>
         <li>Soap monitor now works better</li>
         <li>Removed http version 0.9</li>
         <li>Fixed Enable-UI command line option in pro runners</li>
         <li>Fixed moving of TestCases with properties</li>
         <li>Removed ProjectRoot setting from project file</li>
         <li>Fixed closing of message-exchange panels</li>
         <li>Many composite-project related fixes</li>
         <li>etc...</li>
         </ul>
         
         </subsection>

         <subsection name="API Changes">
         <p>There have been some major refactoring to the testrunner-related classes and listeners, mostly backwards
         compatible, but if you run into issues let us know and we'll see if we can provide a solution</p>
         <p>Notable changes are:</p>
         <ul>
         <li>New TestSuiteRunListener and ProjectRunListener interfaces for listening to related events</li>
         <li>Possibility to set attachment content from script (FileAttachment.setData( byte [] data )</li>
         <li>testRunner.runTestStepByName( ... ) runs the specified TestStep directly and logs its results</li>
         <li>etc...</li>
         </ul>
         </subsection>


            <p>
                <hr size="1"/>
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>

