<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Project encryption</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
		<section name="Project Encryption">
		<p>To protect sensitive data in projects files <b>Project Password</b> property is added. Setting this 
		property, typing a password, will cause that project file will be encrypted when saved. Aslo, this will 
		be marked in <b>Navigator</b>.</p>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/non-encrypted-project.gif" alt="non encrypted opened project"/>
		<img src="images/encrypted-project.gif" alt="encrypted open project"/></p>
		<p>Project <b>can not</b> be composite and encrypted at same time. If you set password for composite project composite
		property will set to false and error message will be prompted. Same goes if yoo try to set composite propety true
		on encrypted project.
		<p align="center"><img src="images/password-composite.gif" alt="project settings"/></p>
        </p>
        <subsection name="Working with encrypted project">
        <p>When start SoapUI you will not be promted for password for encrypted projects. You need to open them and than you
        will be prompted for password:
        <p align="center"><img src="images/password-dialog.gif" alt="project password dialog"/></p>
        If password is correct project will be opened, if password is wrong it stays closed. 
        </p>
        </subsection>
        <subsection name="Encryption in global settings">
        <p>If you need to protect data that are stored in global settings there is global password setting:
        <p align="center"><img src="images/global-password.gif" alt="Global password setting"/></p>
        Setting global password will encrypt soapui-settings.xml where SoapUI global settigns are stored. When starting
        SoapUI with encrypted soapui-settings.xml you will be asked for password first:
        <p align="center"><img src="images/global-password2.gif" alt="Global password setting dialog"/></p>
        If correct SoapUI will restore all your settings with workspace and projects. If not you'll see:
        <p align="center"><img src="images/bad-global-password.gif" alt="Global password - bad password"/></p>
        Old soapui-settings will be saved in backup file and default settings will replace your old settings.
        </p>
        </subsection>
		 <p><hr size="1"/>Next: <a href=" "> </a></p>
		</section>
    </body>
</document>