<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>userguide - soapUI Event Handlers</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
		<section name="Event Handlers">
		<p>soapUI 3.0 Pro introduces powerful event-handling functionality which makes it easy to attach 
		custom scripts to test-execution-related events in soapUI. Possible usage scenarios are:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>Modification of outgoing requests (changing namespaces, adding security tokens, etc..)</li>
		<li>Filtering of requests handled by the SOAP Monitor (adding/changing content, etc)</li>
		<li>Custom logging of results during loadtests, testsuites, etc</li>
		<li>Custom handling of requests to mockServices, etc..</li>
		</ul>
		<p>The Event Handlers tab in the Project Window is as follows:</p>
		
		<p align="center"><img src="images/eventhandlerstab.png"/></p>

		<p>The table at the top lists all handlers and contains a toolbar for adding/removing new handlers. The columns in the table are:
		</p>
		<ul>
		<li>Name : an arbitrary name for the handler</li>
		<li>Event : for which event the handler will be triggered</li>
		<li>Target : an regex filter expression that will be applied for the corresponding target object when the event is triggered. 
		Use this to narrow down invocations. This field can also contain property-expansions (see more below)</li>
		<li>Disabled : option to temporarily disable an event handler</li>
		</ul>
         <p>Selecting an entry will enable the script editor at the bottom allowing you to enter the desired script</p>
         <subsection name="Event Filtering">
		<p>As mentioned above, the target column can be used to filter out which target items a script should be applied to, for
		example for a TestRunListener.afterTestStep script, you could enter "Request.*" to narrow the script down to all steps
		beginning with the letter "Request".</p>
		<p>The target also support property-expansion, and if this returns a boolean string "true" or "false", this value will be used 
		(true will apply the filter, false will not). When using this with the script-property-expansion feature, you can for example
		enter as follows in an TestRunListener.afterTestStep target:</p>
		<source>${=testStepResult.timeTaken > 50}</source>
		<p>This would evaluate the script and return "true" for those teststeps having taken more than 50 ms, thus applying the script
		only to them.</p>.
         </subsection>
         
         <subsection name="Available Events">
		 <p>When adding a new handler, you will be prompted for which event to handle:</p>
		 <p align="center"><img src="images/addeventhandler.png"/></p>
		 
		 <p>Getting to know the available events is basically knowledge of the soapUI API, the following Listeners are currently
		 exposed with their corresponding methods:</p>
		 <ul>
		 <li><a target="_new" href="http://www.soapui.org/apidocs/com/eviware/soapui/model/iface/SubmitListener.html">SubmitListener</a> : events related to submittal of a request (both SOAP and REST)</li>
		 <li><a target="_new" href="http://www.soapui.org/apidocs/com/eviware/soapui/impl/wsdl/submit/RequestFilter.html">RequestFilter</a> : events related to sending a request (both SOAP and REST)</li>
		 <li><a target="_new" href="http://www.soapui.org/apidocs/com/eviware/soapui/model/testsuite/ProjectRunListener.html">ProjectRunListener</a> : events related to running tests at the Project level</li>
		 <li><a target="_new" href="http://www.soapui.org/apidocs/com/eviware/soapui/model/testsuite/TestSuiteRunListener.html">TestSuiteRunListener</a> : events related to running tests at the TestSuite level</li>
		 <li><a target="_new" href="http://www.soapui.org/apidocs/com/eviware/soapui/model/testsuite/TestRunListener.html">TestRunListener</a> : events related to running tests at the TestCase level</li>
		 <li><a target="_new" href="http://www.soapui.org/apidocs/com/eviware/soapui/model/testsuite/LoadTestRunListener.html">LoadTestRunListener</a> : events related to running LoadTests</li>
		 <li><a target="_new" href="http://www.soapui.org/apidocs/com/eviware/soapui/model/mock/MockRunListener.html">MockRunListener</a> : events related to a MockService and its dispatching</li>
		 <li><a target="_new" href="http://www.soapui.org/apidocs/com/eviware/soapui/impl/wsdl/monitor/MonitorListener.html">MonitorListener</a> : events related to handling of messages via the SOAP Monitor</li>
		 </ul>
         </subsection>
         
		 <p><hr size="1"/>Next: <a href="composite-projects.html">Composite Projects</a></p>
		</section>
    </body>
</document>
