<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Web Service Project Requirements</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
		<section name="Web Service Project Requirements">
		<p>
		Project Requirements (soapUI Pro only) is an editor handling the requirements of the project.
		A short explanation of the functionality is that in general you can add, remove, edit, import and export requirements. 
		</p>

				<table class="relatedInfo" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0">
	<tr class="a">
    	<td width="75" style="padding-top:5px">
        	<img src="../../images/where_do_i_start.jpg" alt="Start soapUI Testing" longdesc="http://www.soapui.org"></img>
        </td>
        <td>
            <table class="relatedInner">
              <tr>
                <td>
                	<span class="relatedInfoHeader">Did you know?</span>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr>
                <td>
                    <div>
						<p>
						There is a commercial version of soapUI available; <b><i>soapUI Pro</i></b>.
						</p>
						<p>
						<b><i>soapUI Pro</i></b> contains productivity enhancements as well as offers Professional World Class support.
						</p>
                    </div>
                </td>
              </tr>
              <tr align="right">
              	<td>
                	<span class="relatedLinks"><a href="http://www.eviware.com/component/option,com_wrapper/Itemid,41/" title="try soapUI Pro" onclick="javascript:urchinTracker:('/downloadTrial');">
                                               <img src="../images/try_pro_100.png" alt="Try soapUI pro to soap test" width="101" height="20" longdesc="http://www.eviware.com"/></a></span>
                </td>
              </tr>
            </table>
		</td>
	</tr>
</table>

		<p>
		The requirement can then be connected to the TestCases fulfilling the requirements, linked to important information or documented. 
		</p>
		
		<p align="center"><img src="images/project_requirements.gif" border="0" alt="Project Requirements Editor Main View"/></p>
		
		 <subsection name="Project Requirements Menu Bar">
		 	<p>The Project Requirements contains the following menu bar items:</p>
		 	
		 	<p>
		 	<ul>
		 	<li><b>Add Requirement</b>. Add a Requirement</li>
		 	<li><b>Remove Requirement</b> Remove a Requirement</li>
		 	<li><b>Import Requirements</b> Import Requirements from a text file. See format below.</li>
		 	<li><b>Export Requirements</b> Export Requirements to a text file. See format below.</li>
		 	</ul>
		 	</p>
		 	
		 	</subsection>
		 	
		 	<subsection name="Import File Format">
		 	<p>
		 	The file format for importing and exporting is quite simple, the fields are comma separated and in quotes. Only the main fields; 
		 	ID, Name, Short Description and Status are supported.
		 	
		 	Example:
		 	</p>
		 	
		 	<source>
"TST-049","User Name Length","User Name must exceed 6 chars and be case sensitive","In Scope"
"EVI-020","Cu No SQL Injection Test","Test SQL Injection","Out of Scope"
"EVI-021","Loadtest Purchase","We must make sure that Purchase withstand a buying storm","Out of Scope"
		 	</source>
		 </subsection>
		 <subsection name="Web Service Requirements List">
		 	<p>
		 	The data in the requirements list is the following:
		 	<ul>
		 	<li><b>ID</b> This is the ID for the Requirement. Generally the idea is that ID should be imported from 
		 	a Test Management system or Project Management system, but it works perfectly well as a stand alone ID. ID does not need to be unique.</li>
		 	<li><b>Name</b> Name if the Requirement.</li>
		 	<li><b>Short Description</b>Short Description for the Requirement. Long description should be entered in the description the description Inspector.</li>
		 	<li><b>Status</b> Status of the Requirement. There are two in built values signifying whether the Requirement should be tested or not, but you can manually enter any Status.</li>
		 	<li><b>TestCases</b> This shows the number of TestCases added in the TestCases Inspector.</li>
		 	</ul>
		 	</p>
		 	<p align="center"><img src="images/Requirement_list.gif" border="0" alt="A list of Web Service Requirements"/></p>
		 	
		 </subsection>
		 	 
		 <subsection name="Requirements Inspectors">
		 	<p>
		 	There are three Requirements Inspectors:
		 	<ul>
		 	<li><b>TestCases</b> This is the functionality for connecting a Requirement to a TestCase in soapUI. You can double click any TestCase and run it.</li>
		 	<li><b>Links</b> Link to useful references or actual Requirements in a Project management system.</li>
		 	<li><b>Description</b>Long description of the TestCase.</li>
		 	</ul>
		 	</p>

		 </subsection>
		

		 <p><hr size="1"/><a href="wss.html"> Next: WS-Security</a></p>
		</section>
    </body>
</document>
