<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>JBossWS Plugin</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
  
		<section name="JBossWS Plugin">
		
    	<subsection name="Discontinued">
		<p><b>2007-14-11 : We have decided to discontinue JBoss WS IDE.</b></p>
		<p>2007-14-11 : JBoss WS IDE is as of the 14:th of November 2007 discontinued. This does not mean 
		our support for JBoss WS has ended, we have only chosen to stop producing within JBoss. soapUI will continue its
		strong support for JBoss, just not <b>as</b> JBoss, rather as a independent Open Source software producer.</p>
		<p>Look at our <a href="../userguide/tools/index.html">tools Pages</a> for more info. </p>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="Intro">
		<p>The JBossWS Plugin is a specialized Eclipse plugin for working with the formidable 
		<a target="_new" href="http://labs.jboss.org/portal/jbossws">JBossWS Web Service stack</a> together 
		with <a target="_new" href="http://labs.jboss.org/portal/jbosside">JBossIDE</a> or standalone.
		Apart from the standard <a href="../eclipse/index.html">soapUI Eclipse Plugin</a> features, 
		the JBossWS Plugin currently has initial functionality that supports:</p>
		<ul>
		<li><a href="bottomup.html">Publishing</a> POJO's/EJB's as JBossWS Web Services</li>
		<li><a href="consume.html">Consuming</a> an existing Web Service with JBossWS</li>
		<li><a href="topdown.html">Implementing</a> an existing WSDL contract with JBossWS</li>
		<li>Adding JSR-181 Web Service <a href="annotations.html">Annotations</a> to an existing Java class</li>
		</ul>
		<p>The following improvements are planned to be available for the final JBossIDE 2.0.0 release:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>Improved support for implementing Web Services from an existing WSDL contract</li>
		<li>Improved support for consuming Web Services from an EJB or Servlet</li>
		<li>Improved support for adding Web Service annotations on a method level</li>
		<li>Wizards for security configurations</li>
		<li>Project/File templates for JBossWS projects and related artifacts</li>
		<li>Tighter integration with the Eclipse Web Tools Projects Web Service support</li>
		<li>Integrated Help</li>
		</ul>
		
		<p>Please submit questions and discuss issues on the 
		<a target="_new" href="http://www.jboss.com/index.html?module=bb&amp;op=viewforum&amp;f=201">JBoss Eclipse IDE User Forum</a>, 
		and report bugs/requests/etc in <a target="_new" href="http://jira.jboss.org/jira/browse/JBIDE">JBossIDE JIRA</a> under
		the "Web Services Plugin" component!</p>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="Latest News">
		<p><b>2006-10-12 : JBossIDE 2.0.0 beta2</b><div>- first "public" release of JBossWS plugin for
		eclipse / JBossIDE [<a href="newandnoteworthy-2.0.0-beta2.html">Read more</a>]</div></p>
		</subsection>
				
		<subsection name="Installation">
		<p>The plugin is distributed together with <a target="_new" href="http://labs.jboss.org/portal/jbosside">JBossIDE 2.0.0 beta2</a>.</p>
		<p>Currently, the plugin requires you to install JBossWS separately (download from 
		<a target="_new" href="http://labs.jboss.com/portal/jbossws/downloads">http://labs.jboss.com/portal/jbossws/downloads</a>), 
		but it will be bundled in the final jbosside 2.0.0 version</p>
		<p>Once you have installed the plugin, start by setting the path to the
		JBossWS WSTools script in the "JBossIDE / JBossWS / Integrated Tools" preferences page:</p>
		<p align="center"><img src="images/integrated_tools.gif" alt="installation JBossWs"/></p>
		<p>(The JAXB/XmlBeans tools are not required for JBossWS support)</p>
		</subsection>
		
		<p><hr size="1"/>Next: <a href="gettingstarted.html">Getting Started with JBossWS</a></p>
		</section>
    </body>
</document>
