<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
          ~ Copyright 2004-2014 SmartBear Software
          ~
          ~ Licensed under the EUPL, Version 1.1 or - as soon as they will be approved by the European Commission - subsequent
          ~ versions of the EUPL (the "Licence");
          ~ You may not use this work except in compliance with the Licence.
          ~ You may obtain a copy of the Licence at:
          ~
          ~ http://ec.europa.eu/idabc/eupl
          ~
          ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software distributed under the Licence is
          ~ distributed on an "AS IS" basis, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either
          ~ express or implied. See the Licence for the specific language governing permissions and limitations
          ~ under the Licence.
-->

<document>
    <properties>
        <title>userguide - soapUI REST Methods</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
		<section name="REST Methods in soapUI">
		<p>A REST Method in soapUI correspond roughly to a Method in WADL and is contained as a child to a REST Resource. 
		It defines which HTTP Method, Parameters, Representations, etc are available to a child Request.
        Methods are created from the "New Method" Resource popup which prompts for an initial name, HTTP Method and
        if to open the method editor:</p>
            <p align="center"><img src="images/new-rest-method.gif"></img></p>

        <p>soapUI has built in support for visualizing both JSON and XML responses, and also internally converts HTML and JSON
        responses to XML so they can be used in functional tests together with other related features (property-transfers,
        xpath assertions, etc).</p>    
        
            <subsection name="REST Method Viewer">
                <p>The REST Method View is as follows:</p>
                <p align="center"><img src="images/method-editor.gif"></img></p>
                <p>The toolbar at the top contains an action to create a new request for this Method together
                with a combo box to edit the HTTP method of the Method. The "Method Parameters" tab contains
                all parameters for this Method and the "Representations" tab contains all representations, 
                both as described in <a href="params.html">Parameters and Representations</a></p>
            </subsection>
            
            <subsection name="Properties and Actions">
             <p>The following properties are available at the bottom left for a REST Method:</p>
             <ul>
                 <li>Name : the name of the method</li>
                 <li>Description : a short description</li>
                 <li>HTTP Method : the HTTP Method to use by child requests</li>
             </ul>
             <p>Right-clicking a resource shows a popup with the following actions:</p>
             <ul>
                 <li>Show Method Viewer - opens the Method Viewer (see below)</li>
                 <li>New Request - prompts to create a new Request for this Method</li>
                 <li>Clone Method - prompts to clone this Method including all children</li>
                 <li>Rename - prompts to rename the Method</li>
                 <li>Delete - prompts to delete the Method</li>
                 <li>Online Help - shows this page in a browser</li>
             </ul>
         </subsection>

		 <p><hr size="1"/>Next: <a href="requests.html">REST Requests</a></p>
		</section>
    </body>
</document>
