<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
          ~ Copyright 2004-2014 SmartBear Software
          ~
          ~ Licensed under the EUPL, Version 1.1 or - as soon as they will be approved by the European Commission - subsequent
          ~ versions of the EUPL (the "Licence");
          ~ You may not use this work except in compliance with the Licence.
          ~ You may obtain a copy of the Licence at:
          ~
          ~ http://ec.europa.eu/idabc/eupl
          ~
          ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software distributed under the Licence is
          ~ distributed on an "AS IS" basis, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either
          ~ express or implied. See the Licence for the specific language governing permissions and limitations
          ~ under the Licence.
-->


<document>
	<properties>
		<title>Getting started with the JDBC TestStep</title>
	</properties>
	<body>
		<section name="Getting started with the JDBC TestStep">

			<subsection name="Introduction">
				<p>
					soapUI 3.5 introduces a new TestStep for retrieving data from a
					database using JDBC. The result is formatted as XML and can be asserted or processed 
					in the standard
					way (see
					<a href="../../userguide/functional/response-assertions.html">Test Request Assertions</a>
					).
				</p>

			</subsection>
			<subsection name="TestStep Properties Configuration">
				<p>
					For using the JDBC TestStep you will need to add a JDBC driver to
					soapui_home/bin/ext folder and restart the application
				</p>
				<p>
					The Open source version of JDBC TestStep has fields for manually setting the
					connection settings as well as the SQL query
					and an option for checking if
					query is a stored procedure call. The query result
					can be viewed only as plain	XML.
				</p>
				<p align="center">
					<img src="images/jdbc_teststep_core.gif" alt="JDBC TestStep panel - open source version" />
				</p>
				<p>
				The Pro version has option of using a connection configured at the project level and a graphical wizard
				for building the SQL query.
				</p>
				<p align="center">
					<img src="images/jdbc_teststep_pro.gif" alt="JdbcRequest Test Step panel - pro version" />
				</p>
				<p>
					There are two ways of supplying the JDBC connection settings:
					<ul>
						<li>
							Use a <a href="../../userguide/projects/jdbcConnections.html">project level JDBC Connection 
							</a> - in this case the driver/connection string/password properties will be populated with 
							configured values for the selected JDBC Connection (but the fields will be disabled and read-only).
						</li>
						<li>
							Use text field values for driver/connection string/password - in this case the Database Connection is set to 
							"None".
						</li>
					</ul>
					The specified settings (i.e. JDBC Connection or driver/connection string/password) will be used when 
					building the query and running the TestStep.
				</p>
				<p>
					<ol>
					The JDBC panel consists of the following components:
						<li>Query properties - number of properties can be added for replacement in query through PreparedStatement.
							Properties need to be specified in the query as ":propertyName" and will by replaced by exact names.</li>
						<li>JDBC Connection selection with options
							<ul>
							<li>Create-new - adds a new JDBC Connection to project and preselects it here</li>
							<li>None - do not use a JDBC Connection, but use driver/connection string/password values instead</li>
							<li>Existing project-level JDBC Connection</li>
							</ul>
						</li>
						<li>Button for <a href="#Configuring_DatabaseConnection">configuring the selected JDBC Connection</a> - enabled only 
						if a connection is selected (this will apply to the connection settings at project level)</li>
						<li>Driver</li>
						<li>Connection string</li>
						<li>Password</li>
						<li>Button for <a href="#Configuring_DatabaseConnection">configuring connection properties</a> - enabled only 
						if a connection is not selected, but plain connection properties are used</li>
						<li>Button for testing connection</li>
						<li>SQL Query</li>
						<li>Indicator if query is a stored procedure call</li>
						<li>Button for <a href="#Configuring_SQL_Query">building the SQL query</a> (soapUI Pro only)</li>
						Result can be displayed in 
						<li>XML view</li>
						<li>Outline view (soapUI Pro only)</li>
					</ol>
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Configuring DatabaseConnection">
				<p>Based on the driver selected from the list of configured <a>JDBC Drivers Properties</a> you get the list of properties to fill/change
				in order to configure the connection. Configuration changes will take immediate affect on the project level as well.
				</p>
				<p align="center">
					<img src="images/database_connection_configuration.gif" alt="DatabaseConnection configuration" />
				</p>
			</subsection>
			<subsection name="Configuring the SQL Query">
				<p>There are two options for configuring the SQL query to be used:
				<ul>
				<li>A plain listing of stored procedures along with available output parameters - launched when the stored procedure check box is selected</li>
				<p align="center">
					<img src="images/sp_call_query_panel.gif" alt="Stored Procedure call configuration" />
				</p>
				<li>A powerful visual query builder for creating complex SQL queries with unions and sub-queries - launched when stored procedure 
				check box is not selected</li>
				<p align="center">
					<img src="images/build_query_panel.gif" alt="Complex SQL query configuration" />
				</p>
				</ul>
				</p>
				<p>For the visual query builder there are two preview tabs at the bottom part of the window: 
				<ul>
				<li>SQL preview - where you can view the SQL query you've visually created and add properties to be used in the query</li>
				<li>Result preview - Displays current query results in form of a plain table with no additional options. 
				This preview should be used just to verify the SQL result before including the query in a TestStep.</li>
				</ul>
				<p align="center">
					<img src="images/result_preview.gif" alt="SQL result preview" />
				</p>
				There are a large number of possibilities when building your query visually, including</p>
				<ul>
				<li>Adding objects to the query - you can simply double click an object in the right tree or drag it to the query area</li>
				<li>By right clicking on the query area	you can choose to add unions and derived tables also, along with existing objects.</li> 
				<p align="center">
					<img src="images/add_to_query.gif" alt="SQL result preview" />
				</p>
				
				<li>Joining tables - When two objects referenced with a foreign key relationship are added to the query 
				they become joined automatically with an INNER JOIN clause. To join them manually, you should select the field by 
				which you want to link the object with another and drag it to the corresponding field of the other object. 
				To define join type you may right click the link and select	the Properties item from the context popup menu or 
				double-click it to open the Link Properties dialog.</li>
				<p align="center">
					<img src="images/link_properties.gif" alt="SQL result preview" />
				</p>
				<li>Setting object aliases</li>
				<li>Selecting output fields</li>
				<li>Sorting</li>
				<li>Defining criteria</li>
				<li>Grouping output fields</li>
				<li>Working with sub queries - You may add a sub-query as part of the expression or condition in the Columns Pane while editing text in a cell. To add a sub-query, right 
				click at the text position for a new sub-query and select the Insert Sub-query item from context popup menu
				<p align="center">
					<img src="images/insert_subquery.gif" alt="SQL result preview" />
				</p></li>
				<p>
					Happy testing, and please don't hesitate to give us your feedback!
				</p>
				</ul>
			</subsection>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>

