<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>integrating soapUI with other software</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
		<section name="Integrating soapUI">
		<p>Many of the classes in soapUI can be used directly in other programs, for example if you want to 
		set up requests and/or TestCases manually.</p>
		<p>The following code is taken from the WsdlRequestTestCase
		and illustrates how to create a project, import a WSDL, create a request and submit it:</p>
		<source>// create new project
WsdlProject project = new WsdlProject();

// import amazon wsdl
WsdlInterface iface = project.importWsdl( "http://localhost:8082/soapui-tests/test1/TestService.wsdl", true )[0];

// get "GetPage" operation
WsdlOperation operation = (WsdlOperation) iface.getOperationByName( "GetPage" );

// create a new empty request for that operation
WsdlRequest request = operation.addNewRequest( "My request" );

// generate the request content from the schema
request.setRequestContent( operation.createRequest( true ) );

// submit the request
WsdlSubmit submit = (WsdlSubmit) request.submit( new WsdlSubmitContext(), false );

// wait for the response
Response response = submit.getResponse();

//	print the response
String content = response.getContentAsString();
System.out.println( content );
assertNotNull( content );
assertTrue( content.indexOf( "404 Not Found" ) > 0  );</source>
         <p>For this to work you will need the same dependencies as the soapUI maven plugin, download the source and
         have a look at the dependencies in src/maven-soapui-plugin/project.xml.</p>
         
         <subsection name="Regarding the LGPL License">
         <p>The LGPL license allows you to do the following things with soapUI:</p>
         <ul>
         <li>Use soapUI as a component of your development process in any way you wish</li>        
         <li>Make unlimited copies of soapUI without payment of royalties or license fees.</li>
         <li>Distribute copies of soapUI, although it would be much easier to refer anyone who wants copies 
         directly to our web site</li>
         <li>Make changes to soapUI if you need to do so for use within your own company. The LGPL license does 
         not require you to share those internal changes with the rest of the community.</li>
         <li>Distribute changed versions of soapUI to others, but if you distribute 
         such changed versions you are required to share those changes with the rest of the community 
         by publishing that changed source code under the LGPL.</li>
         </ul>
         </subsection>
         
		</section>
    </body>
</document>
