<?xml version="1.0"  encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<rss version="2.0"  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>News from soapUI.org</title>
    <link>http://www.soapui.org</link>
	<copyright>Copyright 2005-2008 eviware software ab</copyright>
    <description>RSS News Feed from soapUI.org</description>
    <language>en-us</language>
	<atom:link href="http://www.soapui.org/news.rss" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />

		<item>	
			<title>soapUI 2.5.1</title>
			<link>http://www.soapui.org/new_and_noteworthy_2_5.html</link>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">2.5.1</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 02 Feb 2009 09:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<description>soapUI 2.5.1, an update to 2.5 The REST Release, is out. 2.5.1 Contains bugfixes and performance improvements.</description> 	  
		</item>


		<item>	
			<title>soapUI 2.5</title>
			<link>http://www.soapui.org/new_and_noteworthy_2_5.html</link>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">2.5 final</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2008 15:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<description>soapUI 2.5, The REST Release, is out. This release contains not only -as the first testing tool available- complete support for REST Testing but is full of additional features.</description> 	  
		</item>

		<item>	
			<title>soapUI 2.5 beta 1</title>
			<link>http://www.soapui.org/new_and_noteworthy_2_5.html</link>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">2.5 beta1</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2008 13:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<description>soapUI 2.5, The REST Release, betat 1 is out. This release contains not only complete support for REST Testing but is full of additional features.</description> 	  
		</item>

		<item>	
			<title>soapUI 2.0.2</title>
			<link>http://www.soapui.org/new_and_noteworthy_2.html</link>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">2.0.2 release</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 28 Jan 2008 14:46:12 +0100</pubDate>
			<description>Mostly bug fixes and Plug in updates</description> 
		</item>
		 
		<item>
			<title>soapUI 2.0.1</title>
			<link>http://www.soapui.org/new_and_noteworthy_2.html</link>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">2.0.1 release</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 15 Jan 2008 08:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<description>Mostly bug-fixes and minor updates</description> 
		</item>

		<item>
			<title>soapUI 2.0 Final</title>
			<link>http://www.soapui.org/news-report.html</link>
			<guid>http://www.soapui.org/new_and_noteworthy_2.html</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 12 Dec 2007 08:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<description>soapUI 2.0 Final of the Coverage Release</description>
		</item>



		<item>
			<title>soapUI 2.0 beta2</title>
			<link>http://www.soapui.org/news-report.html</link>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">2.0 beta 2</guid>
			<pubDate>Sun, 02 Dec 2007 08:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<description>Improved WS-Security, Raw message viewer and more...</description>
		</item>

		<item>
			<title>SNAPSHOT Update and 2.0 beta1</title> 
			<link>http://www.soapui.org/news-report.html</link>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">2.0 beta 1 snapshot</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 20 Nov 2007 08:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<description>Releases of the IDE plugins. LoadTest statistics logging, minor updates and bugfixes...</description>
		</item>

		<item>
			<title>soapUI 2.0 beta1</title>
			<link>http://www.soapui.org/news-report.html</link>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">2.0 beta 1</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 14 Nov 2007 08:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<description>Major release filled with functionality such as Message Capture, WS-Security and more...</description>
		</item>

		<item>
			<title>soapUI 1.7.6 release</title>
			<link>http://www.soapui.org/new_and_noteworthy_176.html</link>
			<guid>http://www.soapui.org/new_and_noteworthy_176.html</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 26 Sep 2007 08:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<description>Intermediate release with a bunch of fixes and improvements...</description>
		</item>

		<item>
			<title>SNAPSHOT Update</title>
			<link>http://www.soapui.org/news-report.html</link>
			<guid>http://www.soapui.org/new_and_noteworthy_176.html#snap</guid>
			<pubDate>Wed, 29 Aug 2007 08:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<description>Some important bug-fixes and a large number of improvements...</description>
		</item>

		<item>
			<title>soapUI 1.7.5 Final</title>
			<link>http://www.soapui.org/new_and_noteworthy_175.html</link>
			<guid>http://www.soapui.org/new_and_noteworthy_175.html</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 06 Aug 2007 08:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<description>The "Community Release" goes final...</description>
		</item>

		<item>
			<title>soapUI in the news.</title>
			<link>http://www.soapui.org/news-report.html</link>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">soapUI in the news</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 11 May 2007 08:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<description>soapUI gets "9/10 - Excellent" score in InfoWorld round-up.</description>
		</item>

		<item>
			<title>1.7.1</title>
			<link>http://www.soapui.org/news-report.html</link>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1.7.1 Release</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 07 May 2007 08:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<description>A Bug-Fix release including a much-improved NetBeans plugin and some goodies for soapUI Pro users, Read More</description>
		</item>

		<item>
			<title>1.7 final</title>
			<link>http://www.soapui.org/new_and_noteworthy_17.html</link>
			<guid>http://www.soapui.org/new_and_noteworthy_17.html</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2007 08:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<description>We are extremely happy to finally release soapUI 1.7, which you can read everything about here, download as usual from sourceforge.net.

			As always huge thanks to all those that patiently have provided feedback and encouragement during the last months!
			</description>
		</item>

		<item>
			<title>1.6 final</title>
			<link>http://www.soapui.org/new_and_noteworthy_16.html</link>
			<guid>http://www.soapui.org/new_and_noteworthy_16.html</guid>
			<pubDate>Sun, 12 Nov 2006 08:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<description>We are extremely happy to finally release soapUI 1.6, which you can read everything about here, download as usual from sourceforge.net.

			Another huge thanks to all those that patiently have provided feedback and encouragement during the last months!
			</description>
		</item>

		<item>
			<title>1.6 beta2</title>
			<link>http://www.soapui.org/news-report.html</link>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1.6 beta 2</guid>
			<pubDate>Tue, 12 Sep 2006 08:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<description>We are extremely happy to finally release the second beta of soapUI 1.6, which you can read everything about here, download as usual from sourceforge.net.

			Another huge thanks to all those that patiently have provided feedback and encouragement during the last months! Keep it coming!
			</description>
		</item>

		<item>
			<title>1.6 beta1</title>
			<link>http://www.soapui.org/news-report.html</link>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1.6 beta 1</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 14 Jul 2006 08:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<description>We are extremely happy to announce the first beta of soapUI 1.6, which you can read everything about here, download as usual from sourceforge.net.

			A huge thanks to all those that have provided feedback and encouragement during the last months!
			</description>
		</item>

		<item>
			<title>SNAPSHOT release and eclipse-plugin</title>
			<link>http://www.soapui.org/news-report.html</link>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1.5 snapshot</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 11 May 2006 08:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<description>After a month of refactorings and testing we are finally releasing a new snapshot and a sneak-peak of the upcoming eclipse-plugin. The SNAPSHOT includes a fair number of bug-fixes, initial support for SOAP 1.2 and WS-Security and includes integrations with 9 web-service toolkits for generating artifacts from WSDLs and generating WSDLs themselves.

			The eclipse-plugin sneak-peak currently has limited functionality but shows our committment to complement the already excellent eclipse platform with extensive SOAP testing functionality as available in soapUI.
			</description>
		</item>


		<item>
			<title>1.5 final release</title>
			<link>http://www.soapui.org/new_and_noteworthy_15.html</link>
			<guid>http://www.soapui.org/new_and_noteworthy_15.html</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 06 Apr 2006 08:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<description>We are happy to announce the final release of soapUI 1.5, Read a summary of the new features here. Compared to the last beta, the final release includes a small number of bug fixes 
			improvements to the website (see site udaptes) a windows installer including the required JRE for those that dont have java installed and/or want start-menu icons and an uninstaller. 
			The release is as always available from sourceforge.net.

			Again a huge thanks to all those that have provided feedback and encouragement!
			</description>
		</item>

		<item>
			<title>1.5 beta2 release</title>
			<link>http://www.soapui.org/new_and_noteworthy_15.html</link>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1.5 beta 2</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2006 08:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<description>This is the second beta for soapUI 1.5, it introduces no new major functionality but: fixes a large number of internal issues and adds some improvements in the area of LoadTest timings, etc. 
			includes most of the updated documentation both on the site and in the distributions 
			includes the first 1.5 beta of the maven-plugin 
			As always huge thanks for all feedback and encouragement! Keep it coming :-)
			</description>
		</item>

		<item>
			<title>1.5 beta1 release</title>
			<link>http://www.soapui.org/new_and_noteworthy_15.html#b1</link>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1.5 beta 1</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 27 Feb 2006 08:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<description>This is the first beta for soapUI 1.5, read all about it here!.</description>
		</item>

		<item>
			<title>1.0.3 maintenance release</title>
			<link>http://www.soapui.org/news-report.html</link>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1.0.3 Release</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 24 Nov 2005 08:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<description>This release fixes the following issues:

			Fixed inclusion of relative xsds in sub wsdls, see bug 1362652 
			Fixed lockup on failed authentication, see bug 1362888 
			Fixed handling of overloaded operations, see bug 1362929 
			Fixed handling of wsdls containing multiple inline schemas in the types element 
			And adds a small number of improvements:

			Added "Show Editor" menu options to relevant popup menus in navigator 
			Added possibility to move test-steps in the testcase editor with Ctrl-Up/Down 
			Added possibility to open test-step editors by selecting their step in the TestCase editor and pressing Enter 
			Added a "Clone TestCase" option to the TestCase popup menu allowing cloning of an entire testCase including all its test steps. 
			Related site/doc updates 
			Thanks to all that have helped in reporting/suggesting/confirming the above issues!
			</description>
		</item>

		<item>
			<title>1.0.2 maintenance release</title>
			<link>http://www.soapui.org/news-report.html</link>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1.0.2 Release</guid>
			<pubDate>Sun, 20 Nov 2005 08:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<description>This release fixes the following issues:

			Fixed inclusion of schemas when adding WSDL from the file system; see bug 1350372 
			Fixed scrollbar-behaviour in xml-editors for long-lines; see discussion in forum. 
			Fixed pick-up of proxy-settings from standard system properties; see feature request 1346544 
			Fixed source-distribution so that it compiles... (duh!), see Compiling soapUI in the technical overview 
			And adds a number of improvements:

			Two new test-step types: 
			a Conditional Goto Step step allowing XPath-based conditions to trigger jumping to any other test step opening for conditional test steps, monitoring, restarts, etc. 
			a Delay Step allowing a pause of xx milliseconds 
			Improvements to ValueTransfers; see request on the mail list and the updated user guide. 
			Possibility to select values from the previous steps request message (instead of response) or one of its endpoint, domain, username or password properties. 
			Possibility to assign the source value to one of the following steps endpoint, domain, username or password properties. 
			Improved logging in TestCase desktop panel to show info on performed value transfers and goto conditions 
			Improved WSDL importing to handle WSDLs with invalid XSDs. A warning will be shown and request-generation/ schema-validation will not work. 
			Upgraded to xmlbeans 2.1.0 
			Improved keyboard navigation in navigator so selected items can be opened by pressing enter 
			Improved endpoint combobox in request editors to include an option for adding a new endpoint 
			Added a number of unit tests for wsdl importing and valuetransfer test steps 
			Numerous minor adjustments/improvements (icons, messages, etc.) 
			Added documentation on how to integrate soapUI in other projects 
			Related site/doc updates 
			Thanks to all that have helped in reporting/suggesting/confirming the above issues!
			</description>
		</item>

		<item>
			<title>1.0.1 maintenance release</title>
			<link>http://www.soapui.org/news-report.html</link>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1.0.1 Release</guid>
			<pubDate>Sun, 30 Oct 2005 08:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<description>This release fixes a small number of issues:
			Fixed naming of value transfers; see bug 1342557 
			Fixed capitalization of Content-type; see bug 1328568 
			Fixed closing of dependant panels when removing model objects; see bug 1342555 
			Minor improvements to documentation (added PDF) 
			Thanks to all reports / comments! Focus is now on the first 1.1 beta containing load-test functionality, scheduled for mid-november.
			</description>
		</item>

		<item>
			<title>1.0 final release</title>
			<link>http://www.soapui.org/news-report.html</link>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1.0 Release</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 17 Oct 2005 08:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<description>After 4 weeks of testing and >2000 downloads, the final release is ready. The following bugs have been fixed;

			Fixed setting of empty SOAP Action header; see bug 1314885 
			Fixed schema validation of SOAP Faults 
			Fixed ValueTransfer editor related exception; see bug 1312942 
			Updated to commons-httpclient-3.0rc4 
			Minor refactorings and updates to the documentation 
			Thanks to all reports / comments so far! Focus is now on fixing any new bugs and on the next version [read more...].
			</description>
		</item>

		<item>
			<title>1.0 beta2 release</title>
			<link>http://www.soapui.org/news-report.html</link>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1.0 beta 2 Release</guid>
			<pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2005 08:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<description>This is beta2, which contains the following fixes/improvements;

			Improved "Update Definition" functionality; fixed bug 1296190 and added the possibility to choose a new binding if the old one has been renamed 
			Added the possibility to set username/password/domain for all requests in a testcase via a "Set Credentials" button in the TestCase Panel 
			Added username/password/domain properties to the maven plugin to allow overriding of these during CI test runs 
			Improved and added documentation for the CommandLine TestRunner 
			Added a SimpleNotContainsAssertions checking that a specified token is missing from the response 
			Fixed bug 1305583 which reused authentication credentials 
			Fixed bug 1304913 which did not terminate soapUI correctly under webstart runtime 
			Modified splitpane behaviour so that dragged splitpanes do not automatically resize themselves (see "bug" 1304920) 
			Added a sample-project to the offline distribution containing some tests, assertions, etc. 
			Improved Service Endpoints management 
			Fixed problems when importing WSDLs containing REST-style bindings 
			Added a sample project containing 2 interfaces and a small number of tests for getting started. 
			Related and additional updates to the documentation 
			Thanks to Jesper Brandt for suggesting/helping out with several of the above issues!

			Although soapUI has been downloaded/webstarted over 1000 times since its beta release, I have heard almost nothing from its users. Please let me know how/if soapUI is working for you; if there are any problems or if you have some suggestions to make your everyday soaping easier. Thanks!

			Final release is planned to be in 2 weeks.
			</description>
		</item>

		<item>
			<title>1.0 beta1 release</title>
			<link>http://www.soapui.org/news-report.html</link>
			<guid isPermaLink="false">1.0 beta 1 Release</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2005 08:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
			<description>This is the first "public" version of soapUI so please have patience and understanding with any problems related to WSDL importing, XML Validation, etc. (soapUI has been tested rather extensively only with doc/literal services in a J2EE environment and running under WinXP). post bug-reports on sourceforge including wsdls, soap requests, etc anything that could be needed to recreate your problems. Thanks!</description>
		</item>

  </channel>
</rss>