<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Testing Web Services - the soapUI snapshot</title>
    </properties>
    <body>
		<section name="soapUI SNAPSHOT release">
		<columns><column>
		<p>The soapUI SNAPSHOT release will be updated frequently to mirror the current code base and fix critical
		bugs. It will primarily be available through Java WebStart and as a zip binary without the JRE or any documentation.</p>
		<p>SourceForge release and related plugins will <i>not</i> be made available unless somehow required.</p>
		<p><b>Please be sure to make backup-copies of your projects before testing a new snapshot!</b></p>
		</column>
		<column align="center" width="200">
			       <div>
				<a href="http://www.soapui.org/jnlp/SNAPSHOT/soapui.jnlp" urchinTracker="/jnlp/soapui/snapshot"><img src="images/webstart_green.png" alt="" border="0"/></a>
			 <br/>[<a urchinTracker="/download/soapui/snapshot" href="download/soapui-SNAPSHOT-bin.zip">Download</a>]</div>
		<p>Updated 2007-11-20</p>
		</column></columns>
		
		<subsection name="SNAPSHOT 2007-11-20">
		<p>This snapshot fixes some initial bugs in the 2.0 beta1 release and also adds some improvements:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>LoadTest Statistics can now be continuously logged to external files during the run of a LoadTest via the 
		following tab in the LoadTest Options dialog:
		<p align="center"><img src="images/loadteststatistics.gif" alt="soap test load test statistics"/></p>
		When specifying a folder, soapUI will there create one file for each TestStep and one for the TestCase total, 
		and then export	the corresponding statistics as configured and when the LoadTest ends</li>
		<li>A -b option has been added to the MockServiceRunner command line utility that will cause it not to read from stdin 
		when starting. This is required if you want to run your MockServices in the background with for example nohup</li>
		<li>WSDL Caching has been modified to now cache WSDL's as text and not XML, which will improve project load/save 
		times and stability, especially when working with large/many WSDL's/XSD's</li>
		<li>The TestRun log visible in the TestCase and TestSuite editors has been "brushed up" visually:
		<p align="center"><img src="images/testrunlog.gif" alt="test run log and TestSuite editors soap test"/></p></li>
		<li>a global ${projectDir} property is now available for accessing the projects directory</li>
		<li>etc..</li>
		</ul>
		
		<p>Bugs fixed:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>MockService Start/Stop menu actions now don't confuse the open editor</li>
		<li>Assign end point in the Service Endpoints dialog now also assigns authorization settings</li>
		<li>setPropertyValue now works correctly in Groovy scripts</li>
		<li>Fixed null-pointer in Maven LoadTestRunner when specifying user name, password or domain settings</li>
		<li>etc...</li>
		</ul>
		
		<p>Together with the SNAPSHOT release, we are also releasing the 2.0 beta1 version of the eclipse, Maven, IDEA and
		NetBeans plugins;</p>
		<ul>
		<li>The NetBeans plugin has been overhauled to now use the standard NetBeans project model instead of a soapUI 
		Navigator. Create new "soapUI" projects with New Project\SOA\Web Service Testing Project;
		<p align="center"><img src="images/netbeans_new_project.gif"/></p>
		Projects can then either be created or imported from an existing soapUI Project and are displayed in the 
		standard NetBeans project explorer:
		<p align="center"><img src="images/netbeans_explorer.gif"/></p></li>
		<li>The eclipse plugin is available from SourceForge and the update site</li>
		<li>The IDEA plugin is available through the IDEA plugin manager or from SourceForge</li>
		<li>The Maven plugins are available at SourceForge and our Maven repositories</li>
		</ul>
		
		<p>An associated <a target="_new" href="http://www.eviware.com/content/view/81/58/">soapUI Pro SNAPSHOT</a> is also available 
		which includes improved WSDL coverage calculations and some more soapUI-Pro specific improvements and bug-fixes.</p>
		
		<p>As always a huge thanks to those patiently reporting issues and constantly helping us improve our tools.</p>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="SNAPSHOT 2007-08-29">
		<p>This snapshot fixes some annoying bugs in the 1.7.5 release and adds a sleuth of UI-improvements:</p>
		<h4>Bugs (hopefully) fixed:</h4>
		<ul>
		<li>The very annoying bug that did not save changes to a TestCase and its contents if any TestCase in the same
		TestSuite had been moved within that TestSuite.</li>
		<li>Fixed correct progress display for in the TestSuite runner, see
		<a target="_new" href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1763706&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">Bug Report</a></li>
		<li>Fixed SOAP 1.2 action header, see
		<a target="_new" href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1771920&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">Bug Report</a></li>
		<li>Fixed correct HTTP status code for Fault MockResponse, see
		<a target="_new" href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1773056&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">Bug Report</a></li>
		<li>Fixed Generation of TestSuites to use existing Requests, see
		<a target="_new" href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1774508&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">Bug Report</a></li>
		<li>Fixed initialization of Horizontal Scroll bars in editors when using tabs, see
		<a target="_new" href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1775584&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">Bug Report</a></li>
		<li>Fixed Out-Of-Memory errors when creating backup-requests, see
		<a target="_new" href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1775593&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">Bug Report</a></li>
		<li>Fixed WSDL import problems with circular definition imports, see
		<a target="_new" href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1776788&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">Bug Report</a></li>
		<li>Fixed progress display for TestCases with disabled TestSteps, see
		<a target="_new" href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1783837&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">Bug Report</a></li>
		<li>Fixed renaming of Delay Steps, see
		<a target="_new" href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1783840&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">Bug Report</a></li>
		</ul>
		<h4>New Features:</h4>
		<ul>
		<li>Added option to clear Properties when saving a Project, see 
		<a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1767300&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737766">Feature Request</a></li>
		<li>Added line-numbers in all Groovy/XML editors (Alt-L) and also a "Go To Line" action (Ctrl-Alt-L), see 
		<a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1728250&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737766">Feature Request</a></li>
		<li>Added Excel-file support to DataSource TestStep (soapUI Pro only)</li>
		<li>Added range-support to DataSource TestStep (soapUI Pro only)</li>
		<li>Added XQuery assertion and XQuery support to property-transfers</li>
		<li>Added "Recent" file menu for fast switching between workspaces, projects and editors</li>
		<li>Added Log to Property-Transfer editor to show recent transfers</li>
		<li>Fixed automatic creation of non-existent properties in Properties Steps when "Create on Load" option is selected</li>
		<li>Added dialogs for launching soapUI command-line TestRunner and LoadTestRunner tools</li>
		<li>Moved HTTP-Headers/Attachments/SSL-Info tabs in message editors to be inspectors</li>
		<li>Fixed Response assertions to be inspector instead with automatic show/hide on failed/passed state</li>
		<li>A large number of UI-Improvements: tool bars, inspectors, etc..</li>
		<li>And much more... </li>
		</ul>
		<p>As always, thanks to all our users for your feedback, reports and patience!</p>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="SNAPSHOT 2007-04-19">
		<p>This snapshot fixes the following:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>Fixed attachment-support in MockRequest dispatching, see
		<a target="_new" href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1702793&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">Bug Report</a></li>
		<li>Fixed setting of lastSavedDate when WSDL caching is disabled</li>
		<li>Improved focusing when opening/switching desktop windows</li>
		<li>Fixed Check-Box label and creation of TestRequests with default Not SOAP Fault assertion, see
		<a target="_new" href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1702798&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">Bug Report</a></li>
		<li>Fixed correct count and termination of LoadTestRunners, see
		<a target="_new" href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1702805&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">Bug Report</a></li>
		<li>Fixed TPS/BPS calculation with branched TestCases, see
		<a target="_new" href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1702802&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">Bug Report</a></li>
		<li>Updated to commons-logging 1.1</li>
		<li>And more internal fixes.. </li>
		</ul>
		<p>Also an update to the <a href="eclipse/index.html">eclipse-plugin</a> with version 1.7.0.02 has been publish 
		to our update-site with the above fixes and hopefully fixed focusing issues when running eclipse under Java 1.6.</p>
		
		<p>As always, thank you for all feedback, keep it coming!</p>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="SNAPSHOT 2007-03-29">
		<p>This snapshot fixes some more minor issues:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>Improved error reporting and dispatching for mock operations</li>
		<li>Added MockService option to require correct SOAP Version in requests</li>
		<li>Added XML Schema XSD to default XSD's when importing</li>
		<li>Added scroll bars to MockOperation dispatch script/XPath editors</li>
		<li>Fixed unsetting of OutputName when updating to a one-way operation</li>
		<li>Fixed check of MockService path before starting</li>
		<li>Fixed LoadTest runner not to start threads if limit has been passed</li>
		<li>Reverted to commons-ssl-0.3.4, awaiting bug fixes</li>
		<li>And more internal fixes.. </li>
		</ul>
		<p>This is hopefully the final snapshot before the final 1.7 release. Please let us know of any old/new
		issues as soon as possible. As always, thank you for all feedback, keep it coming!</p>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="SNAPSHOT 2007-03-25">
		<p>This snapshot fixes a number of minor issues:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>Added experimental support for 3rd-party libraries in "ext" folder relative to startup folder, normally soapUI/bin. 
		Place JDBC drivers and other libs required from Groovy scripts in this folder.</li>
		<li>Fixed correct validation and failures for one-way operation requests</li>
		<li>Added new "SOAP Response" assertion which validates that the response is a soap message as mandated by the WSDL. 
		The assertion is (optionally) added to all new Test Requests.</li>
		<li>Added internal check that fails empty responses for two-way operations</li>
		<li>Fixed correct display of message exchanges in load-test log</li>
		<li>Set character encoding to utf-8 in JUnit reports</li>
		<li>Fixed NPE's when running tests from command line</li>
		<li>Fixed closing of MockService-related desktop-panels</li>
		<li>Added right-click popup to all undoable text-areas with edit-actions</li>
		<li>Polished up XPath Match assertion dialog</li>
		<li>Added confirmation to creation of empty requests</li>
		<li>Fixed property-expansion in end points</li>
		<li>and some  more internal fixes.. </li>
		</ul>
		<p>As always, thank you for all feedback, keep it coming!</p>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="SNAPSHOT 2007-03-21">
		<p>This snapshot fixes a number of minor issues:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>Added support for excluded types in the WSDL Settings page. Types specified here will ignored when 
		generating requests, which can be handy if "overly complex" types are in the schema. By default the 
		schema@http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema is added to the list.</li>
		<li>Fixed error-line-numbers for RPC operations with simple types</li>
		<li>Fixed step result for test request to be OK if assertions pass</li>
		<li>Fixed spelling errors in UI Settings page</li>
		<li>and some  more internal fixes.. </li>
		</ul>
		<p>As always, thank you for all feedback, keep it coming!</p>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="SNAPSHOT 2007-03-20">
		<p>This snapshot fixes a number of minor issues:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>Fixed dispatching of mock response with Groovy script</li>
		<li>Added option to not disable Groovy log during LoadTest</li>
		<li>Added option to use WSDL Binding name for imported Interfaces (instead of portType)</li>
		<li>Fixed correct internal WSDL Context initialization when importing WSDL:s with multiple bindings</li>
		<li>Added output-folder setting to WS-I tools, for running wsi tools from command line runner</li>
		<li>Fixed failure of test from command line even if no assertions fail</li>
		<li>Downgrade Xalanan dependency back to 2.6.0 which is required by WSS</li>
		<li>And more internal stuff of course.. </li>
		</ul>
		<p>As always, thank you for all feedback, keep it coming!</p>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="SNAPSHOT 2007-02-25">
		<p>This snapshot fixes a number of minor issues:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>Added update frequency to both LoadTest graphs (for regular intervals..) and LoadTests themselves (in the 
		Options dialog), see 
		<a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1667522&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737766">Feature Request</a></li>
		<li>Fixed threading issues with Groovy scripts</li>
		<li>Fixed loading of SOAP 1.2 XSD</li>
		<li>Added option strip whitespaces from outgoing requests, see 
		<a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1667555&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737766">Feature Request</a></li>
		<li>Fixed case of wsdl2java axis2 script, see
		<a target="_new" href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1666462&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">Bug Report</a></li>
		<li>Hopefully fixed calculation of TPS/BPS when using "based on actual time passed" in load tests, see
		<a target="_new" href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1665700&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">Bug Report</a></li>
		<li>Added possibility to save project before removing, see
		<a target="_new" href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1664733&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">Bug Report</a></li>
		<li>Improved contentID handling for multi part attachments; the first attachment of a multipart attachment
		can have 2 space-separated contentIds, where the second will be used for the multipart attachment itself</li>
		<li>Added system-properties viewer to help menu</li>
		<li>More minor fixes and refactorings...</li>
		</ul>
		
		<p>Thanks again for all feedback, keep it coming!</p>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="SNAPSHOT 2007-02-19">
		<p>This snapshot fixes a number of minor issues:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>Fixed TestStep focus when moving TestSteps with the keyboard in the testcase editor</li>
		<li>Fixed check for 0 tabSize in Groovy/XML editors</li>
		<li>Update JRE requirement to 1.5+ for webstart</li>
		<li>Improved SOAP Fault error message when dispatch fails in MockService</li>
		<li>Added saveFirst and createMissing properties to PropertiesStep (default to true/false), see 
		<a target="_new" href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1661060&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">Bug Report</a></li>
		<li>Added PropertyTransfer setting "Transfer to all", which will transfer a single source property to all target selections 
		(when using XPath for target). Selecting this option and for example transferring a source property/value to
		<source>declare namespace ns1='http://www.webserviceX.NET/';
//ns1:ConversionRate/ns1:*/text()</source>
		would set the text of all child elements of ns1:ConversionRate</li>
		<li>Ongoing internal refactorings..</li>
		</ul>
		
		<p>Thanks again for all feedback, keep it coming!</p>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="SNAPSHOT 2007-02-14">
		<p>This snapshot fixes a number of minor issues:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>Added TestCase option to not fail if there were ignored TestStep failures</li>
		<li>Added display of TestStep status in TestStep log</li>
		<li>Improved handling of startup delay in LoadTests</li>
		<li>Removed modification of project file name when creating a new project</li>
		<li>Fixed all file dialogs to use same chooser and thus reuse last directory</li>
		<li>Hopefully fixed selection of content nodes when dispatching mock request to RPC operation</li>
		<li>Updated JBossWS JAX-WS tool to use "wsconsume" instead of "wsimport" (in alignment with their docs..)</li>
		<li>Let all context objects in Groovy scripts implement Map interface allowing for much simpler syntax when accessing
		these;
		<source>context["name"] = ... 
or
context.name = .. </source></li>
		</ul>
		<p>Thanks for all feedback, keep it coming!</p>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="SNAPSHOT 2006-12-18">
		<p>This snapshot hopefully fixes a number of bugs:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>Added "Export Attachment" button to response attachments panel, see 
		<a target="_new" href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1613123&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">Bug Report</a></li>
		<li>Fixed start-info value for MTOM attachments with SOAP 1.1 in accordance with spec, see 
		<a target="_new" href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1613885&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">Bug Report</a></li>
		<li>Fixed/Improved handling of Content-IDs with swaRef attachments, see 
		<a target="_new" href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1614285&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">Bug Report</a></li>
		<li>Fixed launching of commands under Linux, see 
		<a target="_new" href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1617319&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">Bug Report</a></li>
		<li>Fixed launching of GSoap tools under Linux, see 
		<a target="_new" href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1615756&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">Bug Report</a></li>
		<li>Fixed use of correct charset when reading responses, see 
		<a target="_new" href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1617488&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737766">Bug Report</a></li>
		<li>and some more internal fixes..</li>
		</ul>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="SNAPSHOT 2006-12-12">
		<p>This snapshot fixes a number of bugs:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>Added "Export Attachment" button to attachments panel, see 
		<a target="_new" href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1613123&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">Bug Report</a></li>
		<li>Updated to wsdl4j 1.6.2 for fixes with overloaded operations.. </li>
		<li>Fixed handling of missing encodingTypes attribute in bindings</li>
		<li>Fixed export of statistics to export correct data, see 
		<a target="_new" href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1610645&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">Bug Report</a></li>
		<li>Fixed collapsion of tree on renames and system preference updates, see 
		<a target="_new" href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1609172&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">Bug Report</a></li>
		<li>Fixed failure of testrequests on connection errors, see 
		<a target="_new" href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1604544&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">Bug Report</a></li>
		<li>More SSL fixes; removed trustStore settings since soapUI trusts everything anyway.. Huge
		thanks to Julius Davies for explaining and Thomas Arn for testing!</li>
		<li>Fixed scrollbar increment in XML/Groovy editors, see
		<a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1604562&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737766">Feature Request</a></li>
		<li>More internal improvements and bug fixes...</li>
		</ul>
		<p>Since we have updated a core library (wsdl4j) and are aiming for a 1.6.1 release before Christmas we kindly urge 
		you to report any new/more relevant issues! Thank you!</p>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="SNAPSHOT 2006-11-27">
		<p>This snapshot fixes a number of bugs:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>Copying a Property Transfer now copies source step/property/path correctly</li>
		<li>Requests are sent using multi part only when necessary</li>
		<li>Dependency error in command line runners</li>
		<li>Updated to commons-ssl-0.3.4, please report any SSL-related problems!</li>
		<li>Fixed file-choosers in dialog to allow selection of files..</li>
		<li>etc..</li>
		</ul>
		
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="SNAPSHOT 2006-11-23">
		<p>This snapshot fixes the following:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>Fixed problem when creating new TestCases in empty TestSuite, see 
		<a target="_new" href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1596907&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">Bug Report</a></li>
		<li>Fixed lockup when loading unavailable WSDL's, see 
		<a target="_new" href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1599211&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">Bug Report</a></li>
		<li>Fixed NPE when removing an Interface with associated test requests, see 
		<a target="_new" href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1599193&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">Bug Report</a></li>
		<li>Updated to commons-ssl-0.3.3 which fixes classcastexception and initializing SSL with system properties, see 
		<a target="_new" href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1597002&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">Bug Report</a></li>
		<li>Added SSL Preferences dialog allowing you to specify keyStore/trustStore from within soapUI without
		having to modify the bat/sh files. soapUI must be restarted for settings to take effect;
		<p align="center"><img src="images/ssl_settings_for_snapshot.gif"/></p></li>
		<li>Added support for "anonymous" attachments; attachments can be added to any request (regardless of 
		WSDL definition) and assigned the "anonymous" part in the Attachments table. The request will in this case 
		be sent as a multi part message and the attachment(s) will be added without reference from the root part. (see
		<a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1599266&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737766">Feature Request</a>)
		<p align="center"><img src="images/anonymous_attachments_for_snapshot.gif"/></p></li>
		<li>Added support for specifying request HTTP Headers and viewing response HTTP Headers in the request/response
		editor:(see
		<a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1596288&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737766">Feature Request</a>)<p align="center"><img src="images/http_headers_for_snapshot.gif"/></p></li>
		</ul>
		<p>As always.. all feedback is greatly appreciated..!</p>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="SNAPSHOT 2006-11-08">
		<p>This snapshot fixes the following:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>Added exclusion list to proxy settings (comma separated)</li>
		<li>Added support for shift ins/del (copy/cut) to XML editors</li>
		<li>Added 2 context properties available when load-testing:
		<ol>
		<li><b>ThreadIndex</b> - the index of the created thread.. this value will never change for a given TestCase during its run time.. 
		New threads will simply get an incremented index.. the mod of this value could for example be used as an index into a data-file 
		(to handle changes in number of threads) </li>
		<li><b>RunCount</b> - tells how many times the TestCase has been run by its thread (not in total) during the current LoadTest </li>
		</ol>
		</li>
		<li>Fixed correct popup in LoadTest log and similar errors in other tables, see 
		<a target="_new" href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1592156&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">Bug Report</a></li>
		<li>Improved error handling in LoadTest runner</li>
		<li>Added initial support for unzipping gzipped response messages, i.e. messages with a Content-Type or Content-Encoding ending with "gzip". 
		Thanks to Diego Banda.</li>
		</ul>
		<p>As always... all feedback is greatly appreciated...!</p>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="SNAPSHOT 2006-10-26">
		<p>This snapshot fixes the following:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>Fixes proxy-support for schema-loading, see 
		<a target="_new" href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1585239&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">Bug Report</a></li>
		<li>Fixes headless support for command-line runners, see
		<a target="_new" href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1585241&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">Bug Report</a></li>
		<li>Fixes Unix script arguments, see
		<a target="_new" href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1585240&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">Bug Report</a></li>
		<li>More internal fixes..</li>
		</ul>
		<p>As always.. all feedback is greatly appreciated..!</p>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="SNAPSHOT 2006-10-22">
		<p>This snapshot fixes the following:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>Added request-level property to inline attachment content in response editor (as in soapUI 1.5), see 
		<a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/forum/forum.php?thread_id=1594751&amp;forum_id=494205">forum discussion</a></li>
		<li>Improved saving of projects to not corrupt files on out-of-memory (saving now first saves to an in-memory buffer
		which is written to file if no errors occur..)</li>
		<li>Fixed export of definitions containing multiple files with same name, see 
		<a target="_new" href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1579756&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">Bug Report</a></li>
		<li>Fixed validation of derived types in XML editors</li>
		<li>Fixed load-test statistics to show correct values if a step is executed multiple times within one run</li>
		<li>Fixed automatic adding of TestStep Status assertion to newly created Load Tests, see
		<a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/forum/forum.php?thread_id=1595693&amp;forum_id=494205">forum discussion</a></li>
		<li>More internal fixes..</li>
		</ul>
		<p>As always.. all feedback is greatly appreciated..!</p>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="SNAPSHOT 2006-10-14">
		<p>This snapshot fixes the following:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>Added option to ignore case in Contains/NotContains assertions</li>
		<li>Improved support for automatic validation by adding an option to not send invalid requests (see
		<a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1570712&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737766">Feature Request</a>)</li>
		<li>Hopefully fixed the Content-ID related bug when receiving MIME-attachments (see 
		<a target="_new" href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1575529&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">Bug Report</a>)</li>
		<li>Added a global option to backup project-files before saving to avoid corruption of data when exiting after an 
		"Out of Memory" error (see <a target="_new" href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1543510&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">Bug Report</a>)</li>
		<li>Hopefully fixed bug of Property-Table values not being saved when moving focus away (see 
		<a target="_new" href="https://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1563155&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">Bug Report</a>)</li> 
		<li>Fixed a serious memory-leak in request-processor for MTOM/inline attachments and also modified memory-management 
		under testing to never discard timing results for individual TestSteps.</li>
		<li>More internal fixes..</li>
		</ul>
		<p>As always.. all feedback is greatly appreciated.. hopefully there are only 1-2 more snapshots before the final 1.6 release</p>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="SNAPSHOT 2006-10-09">
		<p>This snapshot fixes the following:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>Added support for automatic validation of request/response messages in editors (see
		<a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1570712&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737766">Feature Request</a>), 
		thanks to Michael Vorburger! ("Preferences / UI Settings / Validate Request / Response")</li>
		<li>Added support for generating RPC-parts for attachments ("Preferences / WSDL Settings / Attachment Parts")</li>
		<li>Improved Code-generation dialogs:
		<ul>
		<li>Added [Tools] button which open "Preferences / Integrated Tools" for setting tool paths</li>
		<li>All path/file parameters are now relative to soapUI-project directory</li>
		<li>Improved error messages</li>
		<li>Fixed bug in additional classes for XFire generation</li>
		</ul>
		</li>
		<li>General dialog improvements; Escape closes and F1 shows online help if available</li>
		<li>Fixed validation of SOAP mustUnderstand/encodingStyle attributes in entire messages, see 
		<a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/forum/forum.php?thread_id=1585783&amp;forum_id=494205">forum discussion</a></li>
		<li>Fixed handling of missing Content-ID header in response attachments, see 
		<a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/forum/forum.php?thread_id=1582325&amp;forum_id=494205">forum discussion</a></li>
		<li>Added possibility to edit response message and revalidate with Alt-V (including assertions), see 
		<a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/forum/forum.php?thread_id=1585341&amp;forum_id=494205">forum discussion</a></li>
		<li>Added possibility for custom background image in desktop. Just place a soapui-background.gif/jpg/png in the 
		soapUI bin directory (at last :-), Thanks to Roger Sundberg</li>
		<li>Added option to open TestCase editor when adding requests to a TestCase</li>
		<li>Updated to commons-ssl-0.3.0.jar</li>
		<li>Many more minor fixes..</li>
		</ul>
		<p>As always, we are greatly thankful for your help!</p>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="SNAPSHOT 2006-09-22">
		<p>This snapshot fixes the following:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>Fixed caching of attachments to now be saved in the soapUI project file (compressed).. this makes
		portability of soapUI projects with attachments much simpler.. The attachment-folder setting has been
		removed.</li>
		<li>Fixed importing/viewing of schemas starting with a comment</li>
		<li>Fixed property-expansion when running XPath assertions and property-transfers from within their
		editors.</li>
		<li>Fixed .sh script invocation on Unix platforms</li>
		<li>Fixed loading/caching of WSDL's/schemas on paths with spaces</li>
		<li>more minor fixes..</li>
		</ul>
		<p>As always, we are greatly thankful for your help!</p>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="SNAPSHOT 2006-09-13">
		<p>This snapshot fixes the following:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>Fix for the <a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1557534&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">bug</a> 
		when loading secured WSDL's.</li> 
		<li>Fix for the <a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1557534&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">bug</a> 
		with XPath assertions containing empty content.</li> 
		<li>Fixes password-input fields to be masked</li>
		<li>Added debug-output when launching TcpMon</li>
		</ul>
		<p>As always, we are greatly thankful for your help!</p>
		</subsection>

		<subsection name="SNAPSHOT 2006-09-03">
		<p>This release adds/fixes the following:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>Optimized the Groovy-TestStep for lower memory consumption and faster execution times</li> 
		<li>Initial fix for the <a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1546292&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">bug</a> 
		when validating doc-literal messages with mime-attachments.</li> 
		<li>Initial fix for the <a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1546280&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">bug</a> 
		when receiving response attachments.</li> 
		<li>Initial fix for the <a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1546278&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">bug</a> 
		when viewing response attachments.</li> 
		<li>Initial fix for the <a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1549544&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">bug</a> 
		when running WS-I analysis reports.</li> 
		<li>Initial fix for the <a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1546845&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">bug</a> 
		for keyboard accelerators on the mac.</li> 
		<li>Added a new "Transfer text content" option to Property Transfers for backwards compatibility reasons. When an XPath expression points at an element
		and this option is checked, the elements text-content will be transferred instead of the entire element. This option will be checked by default.</li>
		<li>Added a new "Set NULL on missing source" option to Property Transfers that sets the target property to null if the source property is not available (instead of failing) </li>
		<li>Added a new "Search Properties" option to TestCases that controls if property-references should look for all steps after the requested property or only
		the TestRunContext. Unchecked by default (for backwards compatibility), see 
		<a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/forum/forum.php?thread_id=1562227&amp;forum_id=494205">forum discussion</a></li>
		<li>Added the possibility to specify property expansions as <code>${&lt;TestStep Name&gt;#&lt;Property&gt;}</code> allowing specification 
		of which TestSteps property to use (instead of searching context and preceding TestSteps..).</li>
		<li>A large number of minor UI-improvements (icons, shadows, etc..)</li> 
		<li>Internal refactorings</li>
		</ul>
		<p>Thanks again for everyone´s feedback, as always very appreciated!</p>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="SNAPSHOT 2006-08-24">
		<p>This release adds/fixes the following:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>Fixed a number of critical issues in testrunner which resulted in outofmemory errors.. hopefully these are resolved now.</li> 
		<li>Added step numbers to the testcase log</li> 
		<li>Minor refactorings..</li>
		</ul>
		<p>Thanks again for everyone's feedback, as always very appreciated!</p>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="SNAPSHOT 2006-08-23">
		<p>This release adds/fixes the following:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>Changed support for external log4j.xml to soapui-log4j.xml in line with this <a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1541668&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737766">Feature Request</a></li> 
		<li>Improved schemaLocation handling for relative paths (see 
		<a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/forum/forum.php?thread_id=1558763&amp;forum_id=494205">forum discussion</a>)</li>
		<li>Improved memory conservation during test-cases and load-testing (see 
		<a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/forum/forum.php?thread_id=1554203&amp;forum_id=494205">forum discussion</a>)</li>
		<li>Added an option for property-transfers to transfer text content of source/target elements for backwards-compatibility reasons with 1.5, 
		(see <a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/forum/forum.php?thread_id=1556818&amp;forum_id=494205">forum discussion</a>)</li> 
		<li>A small number of internal refactorings and improvements..</li> 
		</ul>
		<p>Thanks again for everyone's feedback, as always very appreciated!</p>
		</subsection>
		
		
		<subsection name="SNAPSHOT 2006-08-22">
		<p>This release adds/fixes the following:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>Added support for external log4j.xml in line with this <a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1541668&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737766">Feature Request</a></li> 
		<li>Added a "description" tab to both TestCase and TestSuite editors for arbitrary TestSuite/TestCase documentation</li> 
		<li>Fixed teststep-listeners and added an option to transfer null on missing source properties (in line with 
		<a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/forum/forum.php?thread_id=1556818&amp;forum_id=494205">forum discussion</a>)</li>
		<li>Added missing library for unverified certificate support</li>
		<li>Fixed broken Preemptive Authentication support (see 
		<a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/forum/forum.php?thread_id=1555825&amp;forum_id=494205">forum discussion</a>)</li>
		<li>Improved schemaLocation handling for relative paths (see 
		<a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/forum/forum.php?thread_id=1558763&amp;forum_id=494205">forum discussion</a>)</li>
		<li>Improved memory conservation during load-testing (see 
		<a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/forum/forum.php?thread_id=1554203&amp;forum_id=494205">forum discussion</a>)</li>
		
		<li>A number of internal refactorings and improvements..</li> 
		</ul>
		<p>Thanks again for everyone's feedback, as always very appreciated!</p>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="SNAPSHOT 2006-08-09">
		<p>This release adds/fixes the following:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>Improved the Groovy editor in line with the <a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1534414&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737766">Feature Request</a> adding
		syntax highlighting, undo/redo, line-number information and caret-to-error positioning on parse/execution errors if possible</li> 
		<li>Improved the undo/redo functionality in line with the <a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1514430 &amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737766">feature request</a>
		and this <a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1529127&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">bug report</a></li> 
		<li>Fixed the <a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1536980&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">bug</a> 
		when importing a WSDL using the swaRef data type.</li> 
		<li>Hopefully fixed the <a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1529892&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">bug</a> 
		when trying to load an inaccessible WSDL.</li> 
		<li>Totally refactored the request/response editor internals and added line-number information and a possible tab-based layout (as in the eclipse-plugin) which can be
		toggled from the request editors toolbar.. Please let us know if you experience any new problems with the request/response editors</li>
		<li>"Downgraded" to jgoodies looks 2.0 due to user errors under win2000</li>
		<li>Updated to use commons-ssl for unverified certificate support</li>
		<li>A large number of internal refactorings and improvements..</li> 
		</ul>
		<p>Thanks again for everyone's feedback, as always very appreciated!</p>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="SNAPSHOT 2006-07-24">
		<p>This release adds/fixes the following:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>Added a "tools" log tab showing all tool output</li>
		<li>Added the <a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1526699&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737766">Exit without Save</a> 
		feature request, see <a href="userguide/overview.html#Main_Menu">Main Menu</a></li> 
		<li>Improved the <a href="userguide/shortcuts.html">Keyboard Shortcuts</a> in accordance with established standards
		(see <a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1476514&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737766">feature request</a>).</li> 
		<li>Improved the <a href="userguide/tools/topdown.html#XFire_1_X">XFire Code-Generation</a> to include new options for XFire 1.2</li>
		<li>Improved all integrated Code-Generation tools to optionally use the cached WSDL if available</li>
		<li>Improved the Dialog UI</li>
		</ul>
		<p>Thanks again for everyone's feedback, as always very appreciated!</p>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="SNAPSHOT 2006-07-20">
		<p>This release adds/fixes the following:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>Fixed the <a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1525860&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">bug</a> 
		when updating an interface and also added an option to create default requests for new methods.</li> 
		<li>Added a binary distribution (see above)</li>
		</ul>
		<p>Thanks again for everyone's feedback, as always very appreciated!</p>
		
		</subsection>
	
		<subsection name="SNAPSHOT 2006-07-19">
		<p>This release adds/fixes the following in the 1.6 beta1:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>An option to turn off automatic resizing of the request/response editors in the 
		<a href="userguide/preferences.html#UI_Settings">UI Settings</a></li>
		<li>An option to discard successful test results which will save memory when executing
		long-running TestCases (see <a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/forum/forum.php?thread_id=1537364&amp;forum_id=494205">forum discussion</a>), 
		available in the <a href="userguide/functional/testcases.html#TestCase_Options">TestCase Options</a> dialog.</li> 
		<li>Fixed the <a target="_new" href="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1524153&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">bug</a> when moving a testrequest step containing attachments</li> 
		<li>Options for including request/response times in global time-taken calculations in the <a href="userguide/preferences.html#HTTP_Settings">HTTP Settings</a></li>
		<li>Improved the <a href="userguide/requests.html#Request_Actions">"AddToTestCase" Request Action</a> to provide options to add new TestSuites / TestCases</li>
		<li>Improved the <a href="userguide/functional/testrequests.html#Request_Result_Viewer">Request Result Viewer</a> to show
		the actual request content sent, including expanded properties, inline files and MTOM/XOP Includes..</li>
		</ul>
		<p>Thanks again for everyone's feedback, as always very appreciated!</p>
		
		</subsection>
	
		<subsection name="SNAPSHOT 2006-05-11">
		<p>This release adds/fixes the following:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>Adds initial SOAP 1.2 support, selecting the corresponding SOAP Version from an Interfaces Details 
		panel will affect request generation and HTTP Headers accordingly. SOAP 1.2 documents are currently 
		validated as if they were SOAP 1.1 (in accordance with Basic Profile).</li>
		<li>Adds initial WS-Security support for UsernamePassword and Timestamp tokens. Both can be added directly
		in the request editor from its right-button menu, UsernamePassword tokens can also be added dynamically 
		at request time by selecting the appropriate WSS-Password Type in a requests Details panel</li>
		<li>Added a number of WSDL-related settings to the global Preferences dialog</li>
		<li>Integrated a number of WS-toolkits for direct invocation of "WSDL2Java" and "Java2WSDL" tools from 
		within soapUI.. <a href="userguide/tools/index.html">[Read More]</a></li>
		<li>A fair number of bug-fixes related to test-running, logging, etc..</li>
		</ul>
		<p>Thanks again for everyone's feedback, as always very appreciated!</p>
		
		</subsection>
	
		<subsection name="SNAPSHOT 2006-04-11">
		<p>This release hopefully fixes the following:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>Validation of soap encodingStyle and mustUnderstand wildcard attributes should work correctly
			(bug <a href="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1437988&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">1437988</a>)</li>
        <li>Improved pre-selection and feedback for TestCase "Set Endpoint" toolbar button</li>
        <li>Improved handling of invalid preference-values</li>
        <li>Fixed correct tree handling for imported projects</li>
        <li>Added HTTP-Preferences setting to limit maximum number of bytes to read from server, set this value (in bytes) if you want
        to guard yourself against too long results (which will consume large amounts of memory), leaving it at 0 will result
        in the entire response being read.</li>
		</ul>
		<p>Thanks again for everyone's feedback, as always very appreciated!</p>
		
		</subsection>
	
		<subsection name="SNAPSHOT 2006-03-14">
		<p>This release fixes the following:</p>
		<ul>
			<li>Cloning of TestSteps failed to update UI correctly for PropertyTransfers and ConditionalGotos 
			(bug <a href="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1448964&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">1448964</a>)</li>
			<li>Removed invalid possibility to rename a TestStep to an existing name
			(bug <a href="http://sourceforge.net/tracker/index.php?func=detail&amp;aid=1448967&amp;group_id=136013&amp;atid=737763">1448967</a>)</li>
			<li>Bug in PropertyTransfer Editor when renaming TestSteps</li>
			<li>Update 2: Bug when moving and renaming TestSteps</li>
			<li>Update 2: Fixed display of cancel/fail-reason in TestCase DesktopPanel</li>
		</ul>
		<p>Thanks for the reports!</p>
		</subsection>
		<subsection name="SNAPSHOT 2006-03-13">
		<p>This release is the same as 1.5 beta2</p>
		</subsection>
		<subsection name="SNAPSHOT 2006-03-08">
		<p>This release fixes numerous internal issues, including:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>Update of Load Test history graph on reset/restart</li>
		<li>Glitches in TestSuite runner</li>
		<li>etc...</li>
		</ul>
		</subsection>
		<subsection name="SNAPSHOT 2006-03-06">
		<p>This release fixes a number of internal issues, including:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>Correct rescaling and update of load Test graphs</li>
		<li>Correct test monitoring in cloned TestCases/TestSuites</li>
		</ul>
		</subsection>
		<subsection name="SNAPSHOT 2006-03-05">
		<p>This release fixes a number of internal issues, including:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>Synchronization of LoadTest Assertions with target TestSteps</li>
		<li>Correct test monitoring in newly created projects</li>
		<li>Extensive internal refactorings in accordance with Findbugs report</li>
		<li>Moved to JGoodies Looks 2.0</li>
		</ul>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="SNAPSHOT 2006-03-02">
		<p>This release fixes numerous minor issues with the 1.5 beta1 release, including:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>Errors when moving TestSteps</li>
		<li>Errors in Properties TestStep editor</li>
		<li>Timings of non-request teststeps</li>
		</ul>
		<p>And adds the following functionality:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>Possibility to control if request timing should contain send/read times in loadtest options dialog</li>
		<li>Undo/Redo in all text areas</li>
		<li>Groovy Scripts expose result property</li>
		<li>Internal timings are now using <code>System.nanoTime()</code></li>
		</ul>
		<p>Huge thanks to Jens Brillinger and Andreas Wickman for their feedback! Keep it coming!</p>
		</subsection>
		
		<subsection name="SNAPSHOT 2006-02-27">
		<p>This release is the same as 1.5 beta1</p>
		</subsection>
		 
		</section>
    </body>
</document>
