<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
          ~ Copyright 2004-2014 SmartBear Software
          ~
          ~ Licensed under the EUPL, Version 1.1 or - as soon as they will be approved by the European Commission - subsequent
          ~ versions of the EUPL (the "Licence");
          ~ You may not use this work except in compliance with the Licence.
          ~ You may obtain a copy of the Licence at:
          ~
          ~ http://ec.europa.eu/idabc/eupl
          ~
          ~ Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software distributed under the Licence is
          ~ distributed on an "AS IS" basis, WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either
          ~ express or implied. See the Licence for the specific language governing permissions and limitations
          ~ under the Licence.
-->


<document>
	<properties>
		<title>Tutorial for soapUI JMS Support</title>
	</properties>
	<body>
		<section name="Getting started with JMS testing in soapUI 3.5">

			<subsection name="Introduction">
				<p>
					In soapUI 3.5 we introduce support for JMS messaging allowing you
					to send and receive both text and binary messages.
					For this purpose
					SoapUI integrates with the HermesJMS open source
					application which
					supports many different JMS providers.

					<a href="http://www.hermesjms.org">
						<img
							src="http://hermesjms.com/confluence/download/userResources/HJMS/logo"
							align="right"></img>
					</a>
				</p>

				<p>
					For the purpose of this tutorial we will need to download the new
					SoapUI
					3.5 installer which integrates the installer of HermesJMS.
				</p>
			</subsection>


			<subsection name="HermesJMS with binary distributions">
				<p>
					If you want to use binary distributions you need to install
					HermesJMS 1.14
					manually
					<a href="http://hermesjms.com/patches/hermes-installer-1.14.jar">(download here)</a>
					and set its path to Preferences->Tools.
				</p>
			</subsection>


			<subsection name="Installing soapUI 3.5">
				<p>
					When starting the new soapUI installer you will get an option
					that you can
					select to install HermesJMS also. This is mandatory if
					you want to
					try this tutorial (unless you already have HermesJMS
					1.14 or later installed).
				</p>

			</subsection>


			<subsection name="Downloading ActiveMQ and starting the server">
				<p>
					Also for the purpose of this tutorial we will need ActiveMQ (a free
					JMS implementation).
					Download it from the server
					<a href="http://activemq.apache.org/activemq-520-release.html">here</a>
					. Unpack it and start activemq.bat file under bin folder. This will
					start activemq server on your local machine.
				</p>

			</subsection>


			<subsection name="Setting HermesJMS sessions">
				<p>
					For purpose of this tutorial we will create one session in
					HermesJMS.
				</p>
				<p align="center">
					<img src="images/create_hermes_session_button.gif" alt="Create session in Hermes button" />
				</p>

				<p>
					Open the Preferences editor and choose the Providers tab first at
					the bottom.
					Select Classpath Groups on the right and choose 'Add
					Group', type the name 'ActiveMQ-5.2'
				</p>
				<p>
					Than add these two jar files also by clicking on 'Add JAR(s)',
					activemq-core-5.2.0.jar and
					geronimo-j2ee-management_1.0_spec-1.0.jar.
					(These jar files can be
					found in %actvemq_home%/lib folder).
				</p>
				<p>
					Now choose the session tab in HermesJMS and make sure that your editor looks like this.
				</p>
				<p align="center">
					<img src="images/hermes_preferences.gif" alt="Hermes Preferences" />
				</p>
				<p>
					Here you can COPY-PASTE serviceURL: service:jmx:rmi:///jndi/rmi://localhost:1099/jmxrmi
				</p>
				<p>
					We have now created a session in HermesJMS named activeMQSession with two queues and two topics which 
					we can use from within soapUI.
				</p>
			</subsection>
			
			<subsection name="JMS in soapUI">
				<p>
				Now that we have configured our session in HermesJMS, lets go back to soapUI and use the sample project that goes with 
				the soapUI installation %soapui_home%/Tutorials/sample-soapui-project.xml
				</p>
				<p>
					Open the project and left click on interface SampleServiceSoapBinding and choose 'Add JMS Endpoint'
				</p>
				<p>
					The following popup dialog will open
				</p>
				<p align="center">
					<img src="images/add_jms_endpoint.gif" alt="Add JMS Endpoints" />
				</p>
				<p>
					First set the Hermes Config path to the folder where hermes-config.xml is (usually .hermes),
					than select the above configured session and last the queue/topic for sending/publishing and queue/topic
					for receiving/subscribing. You can choose send/publish only by leaving
					Receive Queue field blank and also receive/subscribe only by leaving
					Send Queue/Topic blank.
					</p> 
					<p>
					Example:
					<ul>
						<li>
							send only      jms://activeMQsession::queue_testQ1 
						</li>
						<li>
							receive only  jms://activeMQsession::-::queue_testQ1 
						</li>
						<li>
							send and receive jms://activeMQsession::queue_testQ1::topic_testT1 
						</li>
						
					</ul>
Last one is usefull in cases when you send something to a queue and checks topic as response imediatelly as it first subscribe to this topic ( durable subscription )  and then send to a queue.					
					</p>
	

		
					<p>
					
					All combinations are allowed. Available queues
					and topics depend on what we have configured in HermesJMS, so if we
					add another queue for example it will be available in this combo box also.
					You can add as many JMS endpoints this way as you need.
				</p>
				<p>
					Next we need to create a new TestSuite and TestCase and add a Soap TestRequest.
					Select the operation to invoke (for example the Request login), which opens the editor with a corresponding default
					message. Select an endpoint where the send queue and receive queues are the same and submit the request.

				</p>

				<p>
					Special note for TIBCO EMS users: Add tibjmsadmin.jar and tibjms.jar to %SoapUI%\bin\ext folder, and restart SoapUI application after that.
				</p>
				<p align="center">
					<img src="images/request_response_view.gif" alt="JMS Request and Response" />
				</p>
				<p>
				As you can see, the message we sent is shown in the response window since 
				we sent and received from the same JMS queue (for the purpose of this example). 
				You can specify JMS Headers as well as Durable Subscription Name, Time to Live (miliseconds),
				 CliendID and you can filter messages with Message Selector. 
				Response has a JMS inspector showing all JMS Headers. 
				  
				</p>
				<p>
					You can also set custom JMS Properties for your request;
				</p>
				<p align="center">
					<img src="images/jms_request_and_properties.gif" alt="JMS Request with Properties" />
				</p>
				<p>
					Another important thing to set is the Timeout property
				</p>
				<p align="center">
					<img src="images/timeout.gif" alt="Timeout" />
				</p>
				<p>
					where you set the time to wait ( in milliseconds ) for the receiving/subscribing queue/topic.
					If this is not set or set to zero it will wait to infinity. 
				</p>
				<p>
				Also here you can specify username and password if needed.
				</p>
				<p>
					Since the response is a standard XML message, all XML-related assertions apply (XPath, XQuery, etc), but 
					also two new assertions are available for JMS testing; JMS Status and JMS Timeout.
					The JMS Status assertion will check for JMS specific errors (for example connection errors)
					and the JMS Timeout assertion will check that the message is received within the configured timeout.
				</p>
				<p>
					The method described above allows us to  send/publish and receive/subscribe jms text messages, but 
					we can also use the first request attachment to specify the payload of the message; if the content type of 
					the attachment is text, plain or xml then this attachment will be sent as a text message, otherwise it 
					will be sent as bytes message. Correspondingly, when receiving a bytes message its payload will be shown as 
					a response attachment..
				</p>
				<p>
					Note that only the first attachment is treated as the payload for the message.  
				</p>
				<p>
				Another important thing we have to mention is that you can also use Groovy Script Test Step if you want something else to do with your queues and topics.
				Here is one example of how to use our API to browse messages from one queue without receiving it.
				</p>
				<source>
import com.eviware.soapui.impl.wsdl.submit.transports.jms.JMSConnectionHolder
import com.eviware.soapui.impl.wsdl.submit.transports.jms.util.HermesUtils
import com.eviware.soapui.impl.wsdl.submit.transports.jms.JMSEndpoint
import hermes.Hermes
import javax.jms.*

def jmsEndpoint = new  JMSEndpoint("jms://activeMQSession::queue_testQ1::queue_testQ1");
def hermes = HermesUtils.getHermes( context.testCase.testSuite.project, jmsEndpoint.sessionName)
def jmsConnectionHolder = new JMSConnectionHolder( jmsEndpoint, hermes, false, null ,null ,null);

Session queueSession = jmsConnectionHolder.getSession();
Queue queueSend = jmsConnectionHolder.getQueue( jmsConnectionHolder.getJmsEndpoint().getSend() );
Queue queueBrowse = jmsConnectionHolder.getQueue( jmsConnectionHolder.getJmsEndpoint().getReceive() );

MessageProducer messageProducer =queueSession.createProducer( queueSend );
TextMessage textMessageSend = queueSession.createTextMessage();
textMessageSend.setText( "jms message from groovy");
messageProducer.send( textMessageSend );
textMessageSend.setText( "another jms message from groovy");
messageProducer.send( textMessageSend );

QueueBrowser qb  = queueSession.createBrowser(queueBrowse);
Enumeration en= qb.getEnumeration();
while(en.hasMoreElements()){
	TextMessage tm = (TextMessage)en.nextElement();
	log.info tm.getText()
}
jmsConnectionHolder.closeAll()// don't forget to close session and connection
				
				</source>
				<p>
					Also we need to mention that you can use Rest Request Test Step and Http Request Test Step to send its first attachment as TexMessage or BytesMessage over jms endpoint.
				</p>
				<p>
					That's it for now, we hope that you will find this tutorial helpful to jump start your JMS testing with soapUI.
				</p>
				<p>
					Happy testing, and please don't hesitate to give us your feedback!
				</p>
			</subsection>
		</section>
	</body>
</document>
